the okay now all looks good thank
you for joining us today frederick the
floor is yours thanks so much everyone
for being here my name is phil
and i'm going to talk about the
matter among convert
option route to musician to date
just to as a reminder you are
able to tune the chatroom onto a
metal wall comes to the department site
just go into the into the talk
card and new ability to join to
there
the chest to two if you if
you ever got some questions i can
answered
okay so here's what we're going to
talk about today first of all i'm
going to introduce myself then we're going
to talk about the prerequisites for me
condition rated tradition with metal then we
will talk about how you can find
your first optimization high to use then
how you can prioritize these harnesses using
some c
part of frameworks and how you can
use matter more buicks analytics features in
the process how to write your testing
that both of his and how to
make your head and he tests using
maternal system features
so with digital analytics and crm consultant
i've been working with several companies and
several organization independent settle
i i am specializing developers open source
for the is for about two years
now
and i also was a peter the
technical director about from of digital marketing
master so i'm quite used to teaching
and building can
teaching programs here you can find lining
up being tiny if you are interested
okay so what do we need to
to do conversion rate optimization with matin
the first thing we need to do
is to define what performance is so
i have a definition here her performance
expresses the level of achievement puppy object
is person
so here's really something important to the
people to to know what we're talking
about because we are talking about something
which is performances it's really important to
know what we are meaning would be
safer from us
so now you need to define the
objectives which means the business goal
first of all going to to give
you an example you may want to
increase the part of people whom you
purchase one of your products sharp and
commerce websites and then you need to
define the level of achievement which means
the indicators the trestles and the seconds
so for instance for the ecommerce
conversion rate the pain de coteau gear
ecommerce conversion rate we could decide that
this result is two persons and we
could decide that distressful is for all
users and to keep going through this
process we will use her two main
talks the first one is the kpi-jci
from work
and the second one was the miserable
clan and the tabletten
when you want to do optimization on
and then it seeks to slight matter
on you you'll need to have
as many data as possible to to
have a granted analysis so it's really
important to have a proper tax planning
proper keep you out from
so what is atp iii framework
basically it's a document that explains how
you're going to measure performers through different
level of engagement from the user point
of view
hope you start you always start with
your business goal and in the scope
of reach the first level of engagement
you want to increase the visibility of
your sights on the level engagement you
want to increase the number of qualified
users on the weapon the platforms you
may also want to
engage the audience and you may want
to divert the visitor base within the
digital ecosystem if you have several websites
or apps
on the conversion level you want to
facilitate to unlock the realization of actions
having a direct impact on the business
and on the advocacy that you may
want to maintain and develop the relationship
create the site's audience increase the number
of contests in this jar empty up
visitors on social networks and then the
interactions on the community
pity her on social networks so for
each of these business goal posts you
will honor the gpl level which means
macro indicators you have you define certain
indicators so for instance for reach and
increase the visibility of websites you want
to increase traffic volume
then you have the description of the
metric you have the matter moon at
which you have the threshold and you
have the source
so here we are going to take
a look at this part here but
it's really it's really important to have
all the levels of customer engagements so
that you know if you have your
preferences is good or nuts for instance
on a monthly basis and surely
also you can see that sometimes you
have a matter more as the main
source of data and you'll also sometimes
have external tools such as as your
tools and sometimes social media
on this document there are some things
that are missing but i just wanted
to show you a big picture of
it what is missing is the segment
and what is missing is also the
calculation of the indicator
what you need after that is to
the measurement plan and the measurement plan
is to document where you explain
what are all the actions you're going
to track with metamorph mainly using
even tax so for instance here you
have the page template and all the
actions that the users can do on
the specific pitch templates the type of
attack he sure you're going to use
in order to move and then the
pocketed tour of your event category action
and name
says this is a really important also
because we are talking about kitty eyes
me which means we're talking about indicators
that we will give to the top
management but sometimes you are also
marketing teams that want to
they increase their level of engagement and
their level of some events some realization
of events so it's important that list
everything here in that you can have
that in your matomo instance
and once you have your permission and
plan then you can go on and
write down your tagging plan and here
this is the technical part where where
you tell her the dev teams what
type of coach to push on the
page so here we have the data
layer for the
events and here you can see the
tracking code and all that the different
town veterans that are pushed to them
to load the data there
and then last but not least you
also have to add otho that different
values for you we will be using
as some custom dimensions
this is really important also to to
add a really granular analysis and two
people to segment all your optimizations
okay now you have sure katie i
from work you have your tagging plan
you can start with mason so we
defined what performance is not what we
are going to do is define what
conversion rate optimization is the name of
what we are doing you are probably
new search engine optimization all kind of
stuff doing optimization but the it's it's
quite specific here because cr one is
sir i have a definitional so it's
the practice of increasing the percentage of
user who perform the desired action on
the website but i have a problem
with this definition because acumen example below
if you increase have if you suddenly
drops of salt if you drop the
prices by power same ninety percent you
will have a really good impact positive
impact on your conversion rates but that's
not what you want because only increasing
the conversion rate
is is not enough
i think we should talk about conversion
volume and value optimization in not only
conversion rate optimization
okay
now we have defined what we will
be doing help how can we find
our first optimization ideas i took the
example of an ecommerce website because this
is really an example where we're talking
about money so performance here is already
simple to understand
when you have your indicators you can
compare the metrics between the different segment
and the audiences for for instance we
decided that our average conversion rate should
be that say two percent
and when we compare the conversion rates
by mobile desktop tablet we see that
there are huge differences so now we
should ask ourselves questions which will be
why is there such differences between devices
being in the real world we knew
that most of the time
people
made their first visits with a mobile
device and then finished the audio on
a laptop or desktop but cheerful the
example we will assume that people start
their session that visits on the device
and finish or don't finish to the
purchase
process so here we see a huge
difference between desktop and mobile
what should we do we should go
and looking to the e commerce says
for them to see if we a
freaking see any difference in the checkout
steps between the different devices
so what you're going to do is
you are going to go in the
funnel records and she got the different
steps so here is her potent application
sign up payment and conversion
and what you want to do here
is to use segments moving matter more
and see if you see any difference
and if you see any difference then
you may want to try to optimize
if you see a huge dude smooth
for instance at the payment information step
let's say for mobile users you may
want to investigate further but this is
not what we're going to do now
bitch
because we're going to see that step
four how to use matter what your
accent features not we're going to to
continue and talk about conversion rate optimization
frameworks
because we need to structure our approach
to ego transitioning we could do what
we call your mystic analysis
just to have two words about what's
yours to candidates is is just you
go through your websites through your congressional
journey and used you take notes on
what's wrong from your point of view
might say on the product page i
find that pictures are too small i
think that the etiquette person is not
printing it enough it's below the fold
of stuff like that you can also
to some kind of benchmark with competitors
saying yes i'm on the product page
me to stuff that you don't and
i think this this could be a
good idea but it's quite risky because
once again this would be your own
opinion and we have been marketing so
our own opinions should should not wait
that long
such in our decision so that's the
reason why we should rely on data
and on the frameworks
so i engage you i give you
here i unnatural three or four temple
of of of cr of are the
first ones t i e
which is a model done by a
wide funnel
in fact you have marks here for
every
lift organization zones and you have three
items the potential of the change the
importance of the top the changes in
the ease of the changes and then
we'll have scored in the high court
miss
the first the optimization should be done
then you have another example of seattle
framework which is the ice model which
was created by sean ennis asher again
you have three items the impacts what
will be the impact if this works
confidence how
confident am i that this will work
in peace what is the ease of
implementation that
this year i have a problem with
it how confident am i since it's
something that i'm going to propose
i think that i will be confident
in it that confidence is not something
really scientific or so
at this this exists so this is
good to know that it exists but
it's it's not something that i would
recommend to to use
you have also another model by done
by had wire
and here you have one points or
zero points for each item so let's
say
this optimization a optimization idea will support
the companion matrix
yes or no one or zero
are when the test has changed on
the results opening pages just for notebook
again on pause or is it a
change above the photo below the four
okay i'm looking to to to explain
everything that you understand the principle of
one or zero and the higher the
note the quicker
the tests should be run
and the last one it's the p
x l framework proposed by conversion xl
and again it's a it's a a
march imitation system with one zero or
two and the higher the note that
the most important to the test
so what's you what you have to
do what he wanted optimization is to
go through the data go through other
websites and look for huge differences in
one you find once you find those
huge differences then you have to investigate
further
and when you want to investigate further
that's when the wax analytics features come
to this
i mean you saw that in the
check out to payment info it's really
lower for mobile users but you you
don't know exactly what the issue is
when you only look at statistical data
with a metal so you may have
an idea
but you have to confirm that your
aunt here is a ghost in the
right direction
so here is what you can use
as features of pinnacle
here it's it is examples taken from
the material the more website
i i think that you all are
aware of what session recordings optum grip
going to just re explain it just
in case what it does is that
it takes video snapshots of
users turn on the website so it
allows you to watch to watch playbacks
video playbacks of users turns on the
website so for instance on the on
the example i took on the payment
info you see that mobile users don't
can go through entered
don't finalize their purchase so you can
ask madam what to record
to curb this behavior and then too
you can watch the playback just to
confirm your your hypothesis that might be
i don't know it's it's it's not
to mobile friendly or i don't know
what you you can watch the videos
just to confirm the idea you have
about why it's not working
and as it should
so he tests again a screenshot of
what it does you have here the
movement of the mouse
on the on the on the page
what you can use also as multiple
features for
just to confirm you on your idea
is to use the it maps feature
so imagine that scene you have this
payment info page and you should click
on the accept the terms of sansa
and you see that people don't click
on it because it's
is not not that visible so here
the the heatmaps will helps you to
confirm the fact that people don't click
on it because it's let's say it's
below the fold it's not visible enough
so that's the reason why people can
go through the purchase process and maybe
they don't see
it and they can click on the
next button so that's the explanation you
have and it's confirmed by the by
the it mats
another interesting feature that you can use
maxima is the form analytics feature
especially when you're talking about
chicken processes just to make sure that
there is no be sure with some
specific fields
for instance you may see that some
fields are left blank or there are
some formats issues with some fields here
it's it's interesting to to have also
information
on on the different horse and what
type of issues can occur on the
defeat to her phones
and last but not least the user
feedback plugin is quite new feature
and it allows you to ask feedback
to users using the tech manager so
if you have that user mobile user
that's in the payment page payment info
from he's about to leave you can
trigger an exit that can use an
exit trigger the trigger and then present
this person
this model saying okay was what went
wrong on this page what could have
been done to make it work
this is quite interesting
there there there was
i anxious it was so yes it
was this morning at ten nine that
was at a conference held by thomas
pearson
i encourage you to watch the playback
of this
a position because this is really interesting
because it's all in matter more it's
not an external tool you have all
the feedbacks in metal you have
the the completion of the feedbacks sent
that can be sent as events so
this is really something he can to
take advantage of to have to better
understand what's going wrong on our pages
okay so now you have your optimization
and tears you have sorted them by
priority you have collected more info with
your ex analytics features and you can
describe the shoot marched at thirteen so
as as said before for mobile users
in the
payments for the acceptance of said button
is not visible enough you saw that
on possession recording because you saw that
the mouse moving and nuts are clicking
the button you saw that also with
the events you prepared on your taking
pen for mobile users see the the
click rate up this
button is is really low you also
see with the hidden obstacles assaults armed
with a maps that people don't click
on it and which makes the next
button inefficient you can click on next
to go through the through through to
go through to the purchase process so
these users do not
stan was wrong and then the pitch
so now you are able to write
down your test of this but this
is really important when you want to
to do ab testing you should use
this pattern if i'm in here describe
what you are going to do on
the page
then users will and then you describe
the change respect the user's behavior
so you're
if i make the accept terms of
sales button more visible in tickets their
payment info vulnerable users then they will
click on it and be able to
go to next steps and complete their
purchase this is what you think is
going to happen when you
make the change
once you decide that syrup i popescu
will design
a page
and then
you will redirect a certain amount of
people to this page and the other
go through the regular page and you
you will want to to check if
there is any difference in the performance
of humans being the the conversion ecommerce
conversion rates and you can start configuring
your or two more ab test feature
but before that you should use a
simple size engine
russian calculators because
if we want the tests to the
statistically significant we need to make sure
that we have some requirements for instance
here with at three percent conversion rate
with eighty ninety five percents confidence level
eighty percent
statistical power and minimum fifty percent conversion
rate lifts and three variants
the calculator says okay if you want
that to be statistically significant you need
to have at least twenty three thousand
had
a sample size per round and also
here it gives you the the lengths
that the tests should should be in
here for how the the minimum detectable
effect you would see
in the duration of the test
so once you have these you know
that you have you need to have
this level of
of for sample size this duration then
you can go on and start configuring
your ab tests so i recommend that
you follow each step on the maternal
interface called for that can you give
a name to your test syria write
down your test hypothesis
this
you're just the description of the test
and the number of variation that you
have
and then again the tablet pages
then you
sorry i guess it's the same no
it's not the same as your you
go through the success metrics matter what
we suggest you some metrics that you
could use as a success metrics that
you can decide to use totally different
metrics
sheer chief the success condition so sheer
the minimal minimum detectable effects you want
to have by default it's fifteen percent
that you can you can write to
defeat number but it's a necessary minimum
the confidence threshold is most of their
time for
all ab tests tools about around ninety
five per cent so just leave it
as it is most of the time
it's okay it's just something that says
it's the probability that it's that the
result will be the same over the
time it says okay you this is
not true
due to a random result
here you have the target pages
i was a target until the ab
test when and vista will not enter
the test when
here you have the traffic allocations so
here you have one hundred percent of
people on going through the desperate search
it's not to a twenty that that
that to that level alone most of
the time here you have that again
the traffic cap allocation
for each variation it's shut
let's say
template patient factor in the test
in here you have the and the
you are a petition to have pitches
here you have to open the start
and the end of the page put
that aside and then the code you
will have to continue pitched to him
to make the the test actor
and yeah
i put a screenshot of an ab
test example coming from
the matter move timo websites so when
you wrote down that i put it
into hypothesis in the
in the interface here it's going to
be reproduced
here you have description and although the
person performing sir
metrics
since hunting the tests has been running
and here you are at the overview
of the tests so you have the
conversion rate for each of our nation
the original impair they apply now so
we have an average conversion rate in
here we have the difference between the
two of them and the detected lived
here since we have a statistical significance
of one hundred per cent we have
a clear winner which means that on
this test
when you say if you change the
top six years on the individual chuck
page to the inaction about the chunk
more users will apply to the job
so the hypothesis was good because we
see here that there is a real
difference
in in the way people acted
add that to a contraction
okay so i'm done
maybe i was a bit too quick
i don't know it's one thirty five
so if you have any question just
feel free to ask emma on the
chat
yeah pigeons
okay so
i don't see any questioning
okay so since there is no question
that i proposed to stop the the
recording
and that soon to end the session
thank you for for this interesting session
frederick i guess people might be feeling
a little bit shy now but of
course the chatroom will be open so
everyone you can also continue the conversation
there if you want to discuss
cast farther with frederick about this session
and what was discussed here so frederick
once again many thanks for attending muthama
camp
thank you bye
nine