hello everyone thank you for joining this
session and sorry for the technical issues
now we will welcome Nathan who is
the founder and director of the guardian
project an award winning open source mobile
security collaborative in this talk using a
clean insides neither the survey analytics based
on matomo you will learn how to
use the cleaning
sides sdk from the guardian project to
maximize maximum privacy for your users lets
your nathan stock for more
great thank you silver thank you lucas
and everyone who's organized mahama camp really
excited to
be here with you and to start
you have more collaboration and just to
learn from all of you how you
are using a moto mo to achieve
better privacy and control of of measurement
and analytics this is
kind of near and dear to our
heart at guardian project which is
an effort that i started
almost twelve years ago when smartphones were
becoming very interesting and possible but i
also quickly realized that while
these devices that we carry around in
our pockets are quite powerful they are
also clearly you know tracking devices as
well as you know the potential of
apps which you know i've been working
in mobile since for twenty years plus
back to the palm pilot and apple
newton that the fact of you know
all of this by
binary code running on these little devices
and these little super computers in our
pockets was going to cause a lot
of trouble
so at guardian project our focus has
been initially
from the beginning was saying how can
we bring great privacy technologies that exist
in open source and and desktop computing
to mobile devices that we didn't even
know if that was possible so if
something like tor or pgp or au
tr encryption for chat could you run
that on a phone and people did
i believe that you could and i
thought he could so one of the
things were best known for his bringing
tour to android and more recently ios
with orbit the version of tor that
runs on your phone that can provide
a vpn and through the tor anonymity
network so there's a case where a
very clearly connected to confidentiality and privacy
concerns and work with one of the
leading projects in the world and on
on that effort another
other piece of the puzzle that we
quickly realized in the mobile space was
needed was appetizer attribution beyond what you
know the the gatekeepers of say google
or apple or others provide and that
much like debbie and i really is
the debian system is really built upon
the process of a community building and
curating packages and distributing those and ensuring
that you have good quality free and
open source software we needed that for
android and the after a project had
already existed to be clear we did
not found it but it was something
that we really appreciated and wanted to
support and have become a big part
live through my one of my main
collaborators collaborators hans christoph steiner
so we're really proud of the work
we've done and supporting that effort for
a privacy you know an app store
that actually tells you hey this app
is tracking you you may not want
to install it as an example and
that also itself doesn't track
the it another piece of work we've
done in the middle there the icon
is called
proof mode and this is work we've
done with witness which is a human
rights organization focused on gathering eyewitness reports
through video and photos and media captured
on phones and they had the the
vision that now there's cameras everywhere in
every pocket and what can we do
about that and of course many people
there might think oh we need more
time
tracking and analytics and surveillance of every
photo and every picture because we need
to use this as evidence for justice
but that's tricky you know we don't
we yes maybe we want some of
our the things we capture on our
phones to be used to help people
but we don't want ourselves would be
part of the sort of panopticon surveillance
state of
of surveillance infrastructure in all times
building on that we built an app
called haven with the well known privacy
activists edward snowden
who again had this kind of interesting
idea of like could you use your
phone as a personal security device to
monitor physical spaces like if you're a
reporter a journalist and activist to monitor
a place like a home or an
office when you're not there could it
be a kind of a watchdog or
a you know i often think lie
like a small robot like a r
two d two that is on your
side and helps monitor and protect you
as opposed to a skynet type but
anyway snowden ed snowden had this idea
and we've worked through it and built
something called haven which is quite interesting
and lastly we've been in recent years
working with trade unions and all
organized labor and in many countries around
a project called weep lock where workers
are saying i want my data about
my work day i don't want my
the corporation or the you know on-demand
platform to be the only one who's
tracking me like there's value in me
knowing about my own day
and then i having the i should
have the power to share that data
with others to collectively organize and use
the power of that data so these
are all the kind of dances and
investigations and things we've been doing around
who should measure who should have analytics
who should have this data and why
and where and how when
and you get this very either precious
asset of gold or toxic asset of
you know oil or how do you
take care of it appropriately
and yeah we're very proud of that
work and we have a great eye
a lot of great relationships in the
space around privacy security open source software
and
this is some of some of the
team and benjamin earhart and the top
middle there is based in
austria is been real lead on the
clean insights project as well as a
lot of our work with tour so
i want to give him a shout
out we also have kerry winfrey whose
thinks about consent and the user experience
around consent and how we engage users
with more than just a pop-up box
so we'll be talking about that today
i mentioned han
steiner who works a lot with f
droid and debbie in and reproducible builds
and dr gina helfrich has been a
supporter funder mentor organizer and really thinks
about equity and again the sustainability of
open source and how measurement is part
of that
and then in learmonth who has worked
at tour on measurement works in debian
and works is just great on infrastructure
devops and a lot of other really
important pieces to this solution
so a little while ago i got
inspired and wrote a manifesto around clean
insights that was inspired by the soap
this brand of soap we have called
dr bronner's soap which is kind of
you know quite old maybe over nearly
what eighty years or something and on
the soap bottle there's always this slightly
do
you know creative and separate words around
what the soap is about and i
thought well if he can write such
great lyrical prose about soap maybe i
could write something around
our work and put it on an
interesting product that people can read every
morning and and i did and we
actually make coffee that is part of
our our sort of instigation are are
are hoped to be a catalyst and
you can
read this manifesto and more at the
end
on the link they are clean inside
cetera it's less beans which gives you
a sense of yeah this is a
little bit crazy
but it's also you know we really
do on a change beyond just our
software we want to change some ideas
and thinking about measurement and analytics and
privacy and and how it's done and
we need a manifesto to do this
and also we need lots of coffee
so if you want to join us
you'll see and you go to that
link
that you can actually get free coffee
we have a distribution network nearly global
of our insightful beans and we hope
that every morning when you're making coffee
he'll read our manifesto and think a
little bit more about this and it's
important this is really important have an
and i'll go
through this more in my talk about
about why and how it impacts our
whole lives so but free coffee if
you sign up for a meeting as
a follow up to this talk so
that's the enticement
to do this work for me and
us as a team began a project
i was in at harvard university am
based in boston so it's nearby and
i'm a fellow
affiliate fellow now at the berkman klein
center for internet and society there
as sort of a twelve week workshop
called assembly where we are meant to
take some ideas and and put them
into code and my colleagues on my
team they're on my cohort were from
apple google square and the un and
then myself and we brainstormed
a lot of use cases unfortunately my
need emerged which was i have all
of these apps and technologies and solutions
and communities that i'm trying to help
but i'm afraid to measure them because
i feel like there isn't a solution
out there yet that can and with
uphold the privacy kind of compact we've
made with them and that
i i want to know more about
what's working what's not working but i'm
i don't want to do anything that
would harm them and so this team
took it seriously and it was really
a brilliant group and kind of we
we kickstarted so to speak the first
implementation of cleaning sites and we also
started by look
looking at what was happening in the
market and and we saw that often
not just in apps and websites but
you have things like the emergence of
smart cars of you know machine learning
based platforms where there's so much measurement
and analytics going in order to make
the self driving better to make the
key
car better to make the product better
whatever but then so often that same
data was being used against customers journalists
people inquiring about the product right and
so this was a case where a
journalist had written an article critical of
tesla and then
they elon musk went and pulled out
all of the data from that journalist
drive and said well this is what
you did here and this is your
turn here and you went too fast
here and this is how how you
drove wrong right that was kind of
i know there's lots of details in
there but it's pretty shocking to me
that the corporation could do that take
that data and use it back against
their critic so easily in real time
and that's something that was meant to
be beneficial to the customer was being
used to harm them or to counter
their claims and this has happened in
a number of key
bases around driving and accidents and other
court cases with some of the tech
in tesla
there are also other cases where you
know someone was a criminal and in
this case there was a homeowner said
his house burnt down but in fact
turned out to be arson and the
way they discovered it was arson was
they found out he had a pacemaker
and they
they extracted data from his pacemaker that
maybe he didn't even know was there
that and to show that history wasn't
right about was he when he was
sleeping and this i mean this is
like the most to stopping dystopia like
like your you're the thing keeping you
alive in your body
your cybernetic implant the police are jacking
into it and sucking out data in
order to like you know convict you
now he's a criminal sure but you
know obviously there's a slippery slope and
the more and more that we have
technology in our bodies how and when
can it be used against you you
know and i know
no as a small aspect of this
many in the u s at least
there's programs called wellness programs that where
you get to a free fitbit and
then it taps into your company's systems
and if you wear it you get
some coupon or credit or bonus or
something because you're proving you're healthy right
or
or and yeah and so
what next you know after that in
the workplace and and you know we
know already know that amazon and others
are using kind of again things that
are supposed to benefit you to improve
your life to improve the service are
being used and too often
i know there are some highlights and
i we had the chance you know
through this the program at harvard to
work with professor cynthia dork and those
people thinking about really you know new
kinds of maths in the order of
do you know what end to end
encryption and kind of the work there
has produced and there's similar
or work around
statistical privacy and computing data that were
inspired by and that we're hoping to
work towards and we have dabbled in
but this is sort of like you
know there is something on the horizon
here there's many things on the horizon
and we were kind of able to
tap into some of that thinking we
are also you know solve it
what we were doing isn't just a
activist
cyberpunk cypher punk you know a dream
this is something that apple was actually
already implementing as an example because they
wanted to know what images were popular
but they didn't want to log every
single thing you were typing because they
understood that that was a toxic asset
and not something they wanted to hold
onto but
they needed to know you know just
how popular the poop emoji was so
they could decide where where to put
it in the order of moses but
that actually had a benefit without harm
so it could work
so you know we have we have
we knew that the problem was monumental
we knew that like there is some
possibilities and i should i should also
say you know back then with you
know p wc and and matomo like
we were always inspired by this work
in this community building open source self
hosts
it analytics that you know kind of
fit in the world of the web
that we believe in and in terms
of decentralized technologies and self hosting and
we always like look these these guys
are doing it this this team is
producing products that people are starting to
adopt you know and and could we
build something like that or build on
it right into the seeds or already
have
they're for connecting the work we're doing
with with the matomo community
now
most recently you know in the last
year we've also seen that there's continued
to be kind of big gaffes and
missteps and problems with even beloved software
and open source community i love audacity
i'm a huge fan of use it
for a long time and you know
we saw
a real misstep by this new parent
company that acquired the code or the
team and and all the details but
the point is that there's still a
lot of lack of awareness around like
why would it be bad to just
drop in you know perma cookies in
your new ids and commercial toolkits into
this product like that's what we do
dude that's what everybody does right there
still a basic
huge actually chaz and across around what
what is what is ok what is
okay to do you know why shouldn't
we and even in the human rights
community and even in you know the
harbor community but people just drop in
google analytics and i know that's a
thing that you all are working on
and probably have a lot more experience
and how to get people to understand
the
the other possibilities and and what can
be done there and that's part of
our work especially in open source community
and we also see this continued kind
of an attack on users around conflating
usability improvements with advertiser tracking for advertising
and i think that is a big
thing that gets still combined quite a
bit where you said oh we need
your help to do x y and
z and make this better
but then that data is you know
combined for other purposes and again if
we are building software for human rights
humanitarian purposes and then this kind of
gets introduced in the process where we
say oh you have to use this
other tool and then it's going to
track you it's it overwhelming kind of
number of datapoints start being collected on
people we're trying to help and you
know i don't i kudos to apple
for what they've been you know some
of the moves they've made have been
really interesting with injecting into the user
experience around consent a new model you
know i think people are starting to
respond
and it's interesting to see how it's
impacted companies like facebook
and and then you know with with
the pandemic you know we saw a
lot of emerge and in recent years
emergence of smart kind of civic and
health technology you know be it and
measuring people in cities measuring people around
each
other you know having more data about
you know covert and testing and having
more public infrastructure like in new york
city these wifi hotspots that are meant
to provide people without access to the
internet free wifi and chromebooks and all
of this stuff and you know
we we've been through a lot and
you know i hope all of you
you know are are doing well and
your families are are well and that
you know we're all on the road
to a better brighter day but there's
been a lot of kind of changes
and again what what is happening in
our society around infrastructure and you know
on the one hand there's there's
as horrific security which different topic for
most of these things but on the
other hand you know again what is
what are you collecting and why and
when what data is collected how long
do you retain it and all of
this that i think is is very
different country to country as well so
i want to recognize that based on
different regulations but there's
still that vision like if we just
knew everything everything would be okay so
so you know back to arc our
core story and we have a lot
of these users that we want to
help authentically to make our software that
doesn't track them it doesn't harm the
better but we don't and we haven't
been in and we needed to figure
out a way to do that and
so there's a lot of others that
are in the same
quandary and that we work with and
that we've been trying to provide a
solution for in our space and i'm
here today to kind of share that
work and see maybe there's broader adoption
possibility
so as i said the tor project
has actually done a lot of thinking
about this and they are a big
inspiration with their metrics portal which is
completely public and it's so interesting that
an anonymity system actually has the best
measurement and analytics system as part of
it but they fee
figured out how to do it they
found that compromise and that way to
do it without cock their users and
they've communicate and it's a kind of
a key very transparent piece of their
system to say his tour working how
many people are using it what's the
throughput in a where is our infrastructure
located so all of these things
r and r there and i know
they continue to do this and really
have been excellent there's others like the
open observatory of network interference and other
groups doing measurement that we take inspiration
from we also did an outreach in
a row
a research project with that is published
on clean insights dot org and through
partner sites with groups like keepass cubes
tunnelbear least authority siphon umbrella a bunch
of different projects to say hey how
do you feel what are you doing
with measurement and how are you do
so if we could offer more what
you know would you take it and
this is the big question really and
how they interact with their users and
what they expect and so we were
excited to collaborate and there's a lot
to learn from that report and and
part of it was also that fed
into a symposium we held last year
your
and we have told another one next
year that really brought us together into
a lot of the the questions around
consent and kind of what should they
know and what should you know and
how should you measure it so out
of all of this finally getting to
the point here do we
decided to build some software and i
you know i mentioned my collaborators earlier
and we said look can we actually
build something that you know and when
we had tinkered since twenty seventeen on
different little pieces and trying things but
i think we struck get a much
clearer idea in a specification of what
we would use
use in in a toolkit for measurements
and how what we would need as
part of that and a big part
of it was just this idea again
i mentioned the idea of toxic assets
and liability and how do we separate
that risk from the actual thing we
want to know and so our model
is not to log as
everything and then figure it out later
but it's to ask specific questions and
measure specific things and do edge client
side processing in browsers in mobile apps
and then submit the data in a
way that is as clean as possible
so
do you know some of the basic
kind of guiding principles is around that
but we have are displayed here and
and we work through a variety of
mechanisms to achieve these things about aggregating
and averaging and pointed focus data collection
and measurement wind
does wear of time so you don't
get specific timestamps
getting consent to opt in and how
we fish explain what's going to be
measured this is all part of what
insights is designed to do
i
and a bit of a different view
of this i should mention at this
point we decided very early we don't
want to build our own back end
system we want to focus on our
client side st ks and so we
chose moto mo as the sort of
infrastructure we wanted to do
integrate with the analytics and visualization and
kind of long term or short term
storage of data and it's been great
and it's also interesting because many organizations
want to use moto mo for their
their basic web analytics for their webpage
for their marketing still and that's fine
what we're talking about our application
ns and infrastructure specific interactions and so
it actually works well together to say
lt i set up a tomo will
run it for you dropping the you
know the javascript in your website let's
tune it for privacy there's a lot
of great settings hematoma we love for
that and then for your app for
your other things we'll use clean insights
on top of that and they
get this really great combined view of
kind of what they're used to with
something new and we've been really you
know happy about that and so do
a lot of that back and i'll
talk about the privacy proxy in a
moment but we have this client side
st ks that are configured and have
measurements of events and views
that have a bit of processing in
the storage queue and then are sent
at a certain period back to this
privacy proxy we built and then that
goes into matomo
so as of today on git lab
and unclean insights dot org we have
actual st ks that have shipped and
are very exciting to to proud that
they're there and we're integrating in applications
kenneth as we speak for
lots of languages and i think we
actually also have the rust sdk is
our newest one you know and i
know rust is emerging in many environments
is like the most secure way you
can build something that is you know
a binary kind of application but we
support server applications through python we support
apple
full android javascript so there's lots of
ways to start dabbling in it and
using our code in different environments and
then i'll talk a bit more about
potomac proxy so this is all on
our website everything's to get lab published
in the places you'd expect for dependencies
and so on so she very easy
to end
great
and a piece early on that we
realized we needed to achieve some of
our goals was a privacy proxy in
front of mahama and this is what
our sdk speaks to in order to
do
interact with the data in the way
we collected and then put that into
matomo in the appropriate way so this
is this isn't a great slide but
this is really the information from the
the the git lab in the read
me and a benjamin earhart who's here
design most of this and but we
had certain requests
garments and the idea was we would
you know we we kind of aggregate
records together so they're not always being
logged in real time as an example
we also wanted to filter some of
the headers from mobile devices and things
and so that we could really control
some of those things before they ever
went into matomo and and recognizing
that in some case the number one
with all the materials went maybe as
precisely as they wanted and yeah and
it's a pretty simple layer but it
was great that we had them tomorrow
a poi to work with them that
we could build this layer that we
needed so again it's about flexibility control
and it was awesome
that that this was possible and
been working out very well
so when you work with and clean
insights the steps are that first you
set up a campaign and this is
through coups de son or configuration file
that defines kind of the measurement period
and some
local persistence how often to measure when
to start and when to end and
this can be set very broad or
can be set very narrow and so
one of the ideas as you might
say to users i'm just going to
measure you for two weeks we're doing
a study for two weeks do you
want to join it's going to be
focused on improve
seeing this feature and you can join
and participate in this study that's a
big key concept here which is not
sort of endless measurement and we think
people are more likely to opt in
and say sure i'm excited about that
if they have that ability so then
we get consent and we have some
various you x i'm going to get
to
quickly cause i'm running out of time
and then you choose to measure specific
events with custom data or specific views
some of this relates to what you
might be used to in them and
tomo st ks around events abused because
we knew the data was ending up
there in the end so we wanted
to be able to map it into
some of what you would see in
the image
item on the backend right so where
it's you know there there is that
heritage there and thinking about the data
but how we process it and it
gets there over time so you might
do a bunch of measurements of someone
clicking on a button or interacting with
something and then once a week that
data is aggregated as account couch
sent and sent to the server as
opposed to off you know going constantly
to the back end
so clean insights dot org has a
lot more information on this and we
are also doing a workshop tomorrow morning
that do you know if you really
want to implement we're going to be
ready to talk to you about your
specific needs so and and i'm always
available
a big part of this in our
apps was also this idea of consent
and we've spent a lot in consent
user experience design a lot of energy
around the messaging contribute for the number
of time you know we'll be doing
these things to gather these pieces of
data and here's how you'll benefit and
we'll reach back to you and so
really make it a pi
tory co-design process to improve your software
or your site in a way that's
transparent and collaborative this is key for
us and we think it's an important
model moving forward you know you again
you could say we're going to measure
you for a year or for a
month or longer time periods but i
do want to kind of have it
an experience where they you know it's
like
people in the u s there's a
thing called nielsen ratings where it used
to be super excited in the old
days of television to be a nielsen
family because they wanted to know what
you cared about and which tv shows
were good and you had a box
in your house and it felt like
everyone wanted to be that family and
i think we're trying to recapture some
of that positivity around
and providing feedback to services
and yeah ultimately there's an idea of
why what you're gathering and why and
that we want to tap into so
i'm going to keep going so we
have a bunch of designs figma files
blog posts through our partner okay thanks
carry on our team is that's her
design studio and
really has done outstanding work here and
we're actually building all of this into
multiple applications like this i mentioned earlier
and f droid themselves have already implemented
a piece of this though we haven't
fully done the consent you user experience
but if you go to the after
a blog there's a post on clean
insights and that the ideas was we
wanted to understand the insight was how
often do people fail to install an
app they choose and then one of
the most popular apps this week across
all repositories
and that felt like something that they
were comfortable using clean insights to measure
as people opted in and that would
be that people would be excited maybe
to share that right and so those
are the idea of insights that we
feel are clean that we are able
to generate there
so you know in the future there's
a lot more we want to do
with more advanced kind of solutions and
more filters and how to to batch
data we're also looking at secure multiparty
computation and some of the interesting work
there with kind of you know how
to headaches expert
and what we're doing into larger datasets
and have solutions for a broader market
and again free coffee
so good so delicious so if you
come to our workshop tomorrow i think
you got free coffee sent to you
and then so good and
you know but this is also if
you please if you go there you'll
see you know it's a chance for
us to connect and we really wanted
to we have so much to learn
from you and from people that i
have already been doing measurement are already
implementing things like madame i've been through
this or who have other thoughts or
other ways that they've solve the issues
we have brought up
so we're really wanting to get that
that feedback for sure and and
hope my slight is a little messed
up but i'm you know and eight
fr eight nate freight
in many places on matrix nathan a
garden project at info and clean insights
dot org and benjamin earhart is tl
a he's often around in various rooms
and yeah so i think that's my
talk for today and and we have
have time for questions i think because
we did start a little bit late
but i also want to know
respect all of your time so i
love ending early and i have more
time tomorrow so if you have deep
questions and want to work on this
more with us tomorrow is a good
time as well
never said the coffee
i
yeah i think we're also i mean
in an area that while i'm waiting
for questions please ask away and we
do want to talk to we know
a lot of people use matomo with
web analytics but we are really interested
in people that are using them a
tomo as mobile st case and and
and how you've been
degraded into native apps would be great
to hear from you either now or
tomorrow or through the chat rooms
and to kind of talk about how
you we might you know you can
migrate to using clean insights the sdk
instead perhaps
or why you wouldn't
thanks beyond our hey appreciate that
goodness this easy softball i will say
and boy are hans just posted something
in our our feet about how android
apps can track users based on their
wallpapers and and it's you know there's
so many problems on mobile devices in
this area with
you know perma cookies are essentially fingerprinting
a device as a way to get
a perma cookie and i guess wallpapers
the latest so i i was
you know i often set custom wallpapers
so i'm you know that's a problem
i have and yeah okay well thank
you for all the kind words and
i will be attending other presentations today
as well so hope to hear all
of your other work there and seeing
i know there's a lot of other
relevant topics so but again please come
tomorrow morning if you want to talk
through your own implementation or sign up
at clean insights dot org slash beans
for a private consultation with caf
lee and stickers to get stickers there
we go
i think we're done then if there's
no questions
many thanks nita i think people are
a little bit shy for the moment
but it can also continue the conversation
in the chant sure i'll be there
and in the cafe as well
thank you thank you
you should i have my ukulele or
guitar here and i can play a
song but i can't find it at
the moment
hm
won't be found though no next time
know where it went children took it
i have been home from a date
the
alright this is an
this instrument is a i'm nathan by
the way if everyone's wanted this is
called a drum yen or tibetan banjo
and it has double strings
and the interesting thing is the bottom
string is kind of a drone
like a bass
and it's not tuned up because this
is more of an instrumental ornamental instrument
but yeah it's a really beautiful instrument
and er
this is just waiting music or figuring
out the technical difficulties anyway
it's a pretty fun instrument it's got
this cool like bass drone like like
i'm kind of tibetan mongolian you know
that throat singing sound that was a
real low base and then you play
the melody on the top strings and
yeah i brought this back from tibet
many years ago this beautiful skin there
okay we're going to go with the
pdf file