A wonderful afternoon again from the Matomo Camp Conference.
It is a great pleasure for me now to introduce our next speaker, Udo Trautmann.
Udo Trautmann is a freelance IT consultant and takes care of customers when introducing portal content management systems,
mainly on the topic of Web Analytics with Matomo.
In this context, we will also talk today about the geolocation of visitors from websites.
The lecture is about the various possibilities and data sources for the location investigation of website visitors
and compares the resolution quality of the databases.
Without further ado, I hand over the floor to Udo Trautmann.
Thank you very much for the introduction. Then I can briefly summarize myself at this point.
At the beginning, he also sent a message to me.
Most of it has already been said that I have been filming in the Internet industry for over 20 years,
then I have been self-employed for 9 years.
I also blog about Matomo on my website and also send newsletters to my subscribers about Matomo topics.
So that I, I would say, have gained some knowledge about Matomo through blogging
and not only about customers.
Yes, what do we want to look at in concrete terms today?
First of all, I will go back to the various approaches of location investigation in Matomo.
What is behind it? How do you have to use the whole thing?
Then I will go into the subject of consent in the location investigation
and also see if the anonymization of the IP addresses can be an alternative.
I will go into the possibilities of the resettlement of the consent, i.e. the user consent,
in the location investigation.
And then we take a look at tests and the quality of various geolocation providers
and highlight the difficulties and challenges that these providers have
to return location data and name solutions that providers choose there.
And at the very end we look at an individual solution in the Tag Manager,
which saves the location with user-defined dimensions.
What is meant by location investigation in the first place?
The definition is relatively broad.
This is the investigation of the location of a visitor based on IP addresses,
GPS coordinates, mobile phone cell data, WLAN information or voluntary data
that users have left at any time on the website or in an app.
For example, voluntary data could be that users indicate their location in a contact form
or that they are asked where they are when using a map.
These are all additional topics for which a user has to be proactively ready to give this information a price.
We are already looking at what I have marked green here on the topic of location investigation with the IP address.
The IP address is the only thing that the user always gives a price for,
because it is technically sent from the browser to the Matomo server,
and of course also to the website's web server.
First of all, as I said, let's take a look at what Matomo offers out of the box for location investigation.
We have a screenshot from the Matomo backend provider selection in the agent menu under system location recognition,
where you can make various settings that, as I experience in practice,
are technically more complicated for most customers,
so that they actually leave their fingers behind and maybe choose what is offered with standard.
I have tried to summarize these different providers as compactly as possible in a table
to explain what these different settings actually mean.
On the one hand, of course, you can deactivate them first,
so that no information about the location and the country of the visitor is saved in the visitor profile at all.
The standard setting is an investigation of the location based on the browser language,
so not based on the IP address.
The pauses have been installed in addition to the language of the user interface.
For example, for Austria, DE-AT is sent for Germany, only DE,
or for the English language of the Americans, EN-US,
and with this mechanism, the country of the standard provider Matomo is investigated at this point.
But in this sense, this is actually not a standard investigation, not a geolocalization,
which I will probably use as a synonym here more often in my lecture.
More exciting, or rather already more in this direction,
with standard investigations based on the IP addresses,
there are two provider settings that hide their cryptic name DBIP slash GOIP2 for visitors.
These are providers that use databases from the providers DBIP
or from the company Maxmind with their GOIP2 database to track the IP address
and then receive data from the database about the location,
the region, the country and the continent of this IP address
and then save them in the visitor profile of Matomo.
There are two options available for this database query.
One with PHP and one with Apache Engine X, i.e. two web servers.
The PHP variant works in such a way that within Matomo with PHP,
so Matomo is programmed in PHP, the database queries.
The data or the IP address does not leave the Matomo server in this case,
but the database is on the server on which Matomo is installed,
so that the query takes place locally.
The variant with the web servers, with the web servers, i.e. Apache and Engine X,
takes place within the web server where Matomo is installed
by an extension that has to be installed and configured in the web server.
This web server extension also works there with the local data bank
and then transmits the information from the site to Matomo via the server variant.
It is a rather technical process.
I will go into more detail about when to actually use which of these providers in the field.
Let's start with Apache Engine X.
Here you definitely need someone outside the IT department,
someone who takes care of the web server.
This is in contrast to the settings with PHP or the standard settings,
which a Matomo administrator or a Matomo supervisor can take up on his own.
By the way, I also made a point here.
PHP and MaxMind GeoIP2 database are the settings for those who use the Matomo Cloud,
or the chosen provider, which, in my opinion, cannot be changed there either.
Everything I do now, you still have to understand in context,
do I now have the Cloud solution in use?
What does that mean for me if I use the GeoIP2 PHP provider
or have I installed Matomo myself?
Then, of course, I have all the flexibility to take this setting into account.
In terms of completeness, I would also like to mention a plugin,
which is available in the marketplace for free.
The plugin works with another provider than the one previously mentioned.
The provider IP2 Location is used here.
The IP address is also asked in a database either within Matomo with PHP
or there is a web service access to the provider.
A registration is also required to make the whole thing work.
When are these settings useful?
When does which of these providers offer?
On the one hand, we have the standard provider,
where the language information of the browser is accessed.
The situation that this can be useful
when the available IP addresses have been anonymized,
either with two or three bytes,
and in this way can actually no longer be used in a meaningful location.
Here it just makes sense that you say,
OK, then you just go back to the language information of the browser
and find out what it is.
There can also be constellations.
It rarely happens, but I have 10% or maybe 5% of Matomo installation setups
have already seen that for technical reasons
the actual IP address of the browser does not even arrive at the Matomo server.
This is usually the case when network infrastructures,
put simply, are so complex that through firewalls, load balancer, proxy, server,
which do not pass on the original IP address of the user,
but only somehow pass on their own to Matomo.
We have a constellation here that Matomo does not have this IP address under circumstances.
The db.ip2-geo.ip-provider with PHP is then useful
if we have the entire IP address of the user,
or maybe only have one anonymized byte available,
or even if we do not normally track with Matomo,
not with JavaScript, but work with server log file import,
then you actually have to take this provider,
if you want to investigate locations at all,
because the other providers, in this case in the case of server log file import,
can't work at all.
You also have to choose this provider,
by force, if you want to work with IP geolocation,
if you let the Matomo run in a shared host,
because usually you can't get to the Apache or Nginx
at the Apache or Nginx
and can't make any configuration there.
That's why this PHP variant is the only useful one.
In practice, this is very common in installations with WordPress,
where you can usually run your website at a very low cost
at shared host.
And then you can finally only use this provider
for developing the IP standard.
The provider for the web server with Apache and Nginx
is also in this case only really useful
if you have the IP addresses completely or with one anonymized byte,
or if you have this more complex network-technically complex situation
that the client IP addresses, i.e. the IP addresses of the visitors,
have to be investigated by the web server by means of web server directives,
where you can give yourself the remote IP address
to be able to conduct the stand-alone investigation with that address.
Or if the web server in which Matomo runs is already doing geolocation,
because, for example, he also checks the IP addresses on a website
based on some content delivery or content blocking measures on a large portal
and decides which content he wants to play or is allowed to play.
Of course, you can use the information provided there in the same way
to hand it over to Matomo and don't have to do it extra Matomo again.
The provider can also be useful if you are able to conduct the whole application
individually for the stand-alone investigation.
I'll go into that in a moment and show you an example
of how you could do that in Engine X.
The provider, as I said earlier, is not just so easy to activate
by a Matomo administrator,
but you need a web server administrator who compiles the TRIP software,
installs it in the web server and then also provides the appropriate configuration.
As far as I know, it is only possible with the solution of NextMind
if in the chat in the expert format or otherwise.
You can also correct me there.
I haven't found a setup yet that has found something
where you can do that in the web server with the DBIP database.
But maybe the software from NextMind also works with the DBIP database.
I don't know, so I didn't find it documented.
That might be an interesting feedback for me today in the round
whether that is possible at all.
Yes, and then let's look again at the plugin from IP2 Location.
I'll go a little further here.
I can't give any recommendations for this plugin
or for the quality of the determined standard results,
because in a test that I did,
I will also show you the test results in detail,
it was actually only correct with, even with the full IP address,
the country, but again the state,
in addition to the local data,
it was correct with the Geo Location provider,
so that I can't give any direct recommendations here at the moment.
The topic is the obligation to vote and anonymization.
Is anonymization an alternative to the obligation to vote
in the development of the location?
I've already mentioned this in part,
but we have the legal situation in Germany
that a location investigation without the consent of the visitor
is not allowed to use the IP address.
It's not even about the storage of the IP address,
which is definitely not stored on the subject at Formatomo,
but it's about processing,
because you have to prevent that a personability can be produced.
The whole thing was established long before the DSGVO,
there were decisions by the top authorities of the Data Protection Conference in Germany
in November 2009,
I have posted two links here, if you can read them.
One spoke and said that a shortening of the IP address is possible,
that is to say, anonymization of individual bytes,
which then allow processing without consent.
In the former formulations,
it's not about how many bytes you have to shorten.
Maybe that's another input that someone can give in the round.
I have this to show you what it means
in terms of the impact of the quality of the location
with anonymized IP addresses.
I've done a few tests.
The MaxMind company offers a tool,
a console tool that you can download,
which you can run to test the database of MaxMind,
with which you simply enter an IP address
and then get the data back.
It's an easy tool to test for any IP.
I have chosen random test IPs.
Here is my example, the 188, 172, with two anonymized bytes.
Matomo then replaces the x with 2.1
and then makes the query for all users
with whom the IP addresses begin with the first two bytes.
As we can see, we have an IP address
where this range is incredibly large.
And here, with this GeoIP2 database,
IP addresses are not only from other European countries,
but are even from South America, North America and Asia.
So in this respect, you have to come to the realization
that if you take two-bytes anonymization here,
the result of the location investigation
does not necessarily correspond to the topic that is important.
But there can be, I have to say openly,
IP ranges where the first two bytes
can be found in two or three countries,
maybe even only in one country.
So I think, especially in the USA,
where so many IP addresses are assigned,
it can certainly be that with an anonymization with two bytes,
the hit is still only for the USA.
Yes, with an anonymization with one byte,
it looks much better.
In my tests, it was like that,
especially with German IP addresses,
that the state was actually always uniform
and in most cases also the place.
In any case, say, in rural areas,
it could happen that smaller towns,
smaller cities within these 552 bytes were found.
But at the end of the day, you have to say,
with an anonymization with one byte,
the results are still acceptable
and can be described as good.
Yes, what possibilities do you have at all
when the legislator prescribes here
that you have to make a decision for the local investigation?
With the out-of-the-box possibilities of Matomo,
so for the things we have talked about today,
if we want to do a local investigation
with the full IP address,
we have, I'll put it this way,
we have it relatively difficult
because we have to even link the whole thing
to the consent for tracking
with the version with the PHP provider,
because Matomo does not support
individual consent in the local investigation,
but the whole topic of consent management in Matomo
always refers to the question,
do I want to track a user at all, yes or no?
And in this case, we have to, so to speak,
if we do this with the provider,
design the application banner,
the cookie or consent banner in such a way
that our visitors, if they agree to the tracking,
then they are also informed
that they agree to the local investigation topic
and if they reject it,
then they should not be tracked
and then of course no location is investigated.
With the provider version with the web servers,
here we can act a little more flexibly,
here we can evaluate the cookie
that is available to us in the web server
to the consent
and can only then
carry out the local investigation in the Matomo web server.
If the user has rejected or the cookie is missing,
then we would
hand over any default value to Matomo as a location
that Matomo later says
the user did not register here.
Yes, here you could actually design the content banner individually,
either for tracking or for the local investigation
or only for the local investigation,
if you have decided for tracking, for example,
not to register.
This is always an example
for someone who also administers the web server.
So you can here in the Nginx web server,
but in Pechigi this is also possible,
you can
ask for the cookies and here in this case
the cookie named Claro,
so this is the framework of the consent cookie name,
if it is assigned to Matomo,
then I can get the various information
from the geo database
for the continent, for the country,
even the geo coordinates,
and then I can write them into these variables
that start with mm
and they will then be handed over to Matomo by Nginx
and Matomo
then writes them into the visitor profile.
Yes, and if the user has rejected this consent
or the cookie is not there at all,
I just put the country,
the information of the country, on unknown,
I could have written in here, rejected or something,
so some information that is then processed
in the visitor profile in Matomo
and based on which I will later recognize,
okay, these are now visitor data,
or visitors who have not given
their consent.
Okay, now let's go
very quickly, or let's make a very quick
side trip away from very specific Matomo
topics and look at various providers
on the subject of location research or
geolocation
and look at why it is actually
so difficult for them,
in all cases, at least always good data,
reliable data to provide us
and with which, I have now called them intelligent approaches,
with which approaches
these providers work to increase
the data quality and also the actuality.
Because their problems are
actually, as I just said,
the actuality on the one hand and on the other
the accuracy, i.e. the exactness
of the determined location data.
I'm going to go into that in a moment,
I have a map of Germany in the background
with yellow dots.
These are not random points, but
these are actually test results
from tests that I have carried out
from my location here in Berlin
and these are IP addresses that belonged to me.
The larger the yellow circle, the more hits
it has given in the locations, so you can see
that it has already given most hits in Berlin,
but I was also spread across all of Germany
with the complete
full IP address.
So a customer's image, so you can't
really talk about accuracy anymore.
I would like to add right away
that these points are the test results
of all possible providers
and that the best providers
have delivered
much more concrete or rather much more
more precise results
and have located me much more often
in Berlin.
Before I show you the results, maybe
briefly describe the test scenario.
I have seen 14 offers in a year.
I tested the whole thing over three months
with then repeatedly changing IP addresses
from Berlin.
Ten tests took place with DSL,
so with a DSL connection with Vodafone
and ten tests with a mobile phone connection
with LTE.
I have carried out the tests with the
freely accessible offers of the providers on the website
or with the databases that could be
sold in Matomo.
The result of the following test results
are different providers.
I have mentioned Max many times before.
Here, nine out of ten times
can be located in Berlin
with a DSL connection.
Four out of ten times
can be located in Berlin
with a mobile phone connection.
I don't want to go through the points one by one.
You can download the file.
The link is also included in the presentation profile.
You can see here that next to Max,
who offers both a commercial
and a free database,
IPregistry.co and Big Data Cloud
have achieved results
that have been found in this quality area.
After that, we already have providers
who have brought results on average.
Then we have a whole bunch of offers
down here that were only
in some cases correct
or partly not at all.
Here I also have DBIP,
which has a commercial and a free database,
and IP2 Location, which is also
marked in Matomo.
That's why I mentioned earlier
that I can't recommend using them here.
What came out of it,
what you have to say about the so-called
test winners of MaxMind,
IPregistry and Big Data Cloud,
if their results were wrong,
then I wasn't located here in the surrounding area
of Berlin, but the results were really wrong.
Then I wanted to go to Baden-Württemberg, Hamburg,
Niedersachsen and so on,
in areas that were partly hundreds of kilometers away from Berlin
and then were completely wrong again.
In some cases,
the providers were not yet able
to give back the locations in all cases.
So if the results were wrong, then only
federal states were given back.
Especially in Baden-Württemberg,
I was often located.
But you have to say that at MaxMind
and Big Data Cloud,
which offer their customers quality announcements
on their website,
that these quality announcements
have also been made at my tests.
That means that at DSL, 80 to 90 percent of the hits
were in the tolerance circle of 50 kilometers.
Correct. And with mobile phone devices
or mobile phone use,
the accuracy of hits was about 50 percent.
So that's also what the providers
promise, at least for Germany.
You can check with both providers
what they do for other countries
for quality announcements.
That can also vary, so that the results
are even better.
The smaller the countries,
the worse.
Why is that?
A brief overview. What difficulties do they have?
A big topic is the actuality of the data
with which they can work.
Because the Internet Service Provider
of course puts the data where the IP address
is assigned to which customer,
never live to them.
In that sense, they do not access
all Internet Service Provider in the world live.
That is of course one topic. The other topic
is that you generally,
that is now more from the customer's point of view,
often have wrong expectations, because you
have the IP address and location data
related to the expectations. That would be the geo coordinates.
But that is actually a wrong expectation.
Then it may be with some
fixed-installed proxy servers, but for example
for smartphones, with which the people are on the move,
it can never be a geo coordinate
that is delivered to them as a request.
Then there is the rotation of the IP addresses
that are dynamically assigned to the customers
on this topic.
Most people have
IP addresses that are dynamically
assigned to them by the service providers.
That can be a problem almost every day.
Of course, this is also a difficulty with which the service providers
have to fight.
Then, of course, users of mobile devices,
in a literal sense also mobile.
That means that the IP addresses of mobile devices
are never at the same location.
For example, you have to get in line in advance
and drive 100 kilometers, maybe even longer,
and the IP address does not change at all.
So that is also a topic where you have to understand
that with mobile devices the returned location
can't really be right so often.
Finally, you still have
the whole topic of proxy servers in the company
and the employee sits in the home office,
but surfs over the company's proxy server,
or people surf over VPN networks,
over anonymization services,
where the IP address is never actually,
or rather unconsciously, not at the current user location.
The providers have different solutions
with which they try to get all this
problematic in the head.
They try to collect the OZ data
that they have received from the service providers
with their own information,
which they collect additionally with their own mechanisms,
where they take back some of the algorithms
that they have implemented,
where they also take back feedback from their customers.
This can be data that is
also available here.
Or not all of them are available to all providers.
For example, there is something like a trust value,
i.e. how reliable can you estimate this OZ data at all,
whether low, medium or high.
There are circumference data
to the radius of the accuracy of the OZ data.
These are, for example, typical ranges
that individual providers share with us.
MaxMind, for example, can provide such information
as well.
I have to say that Motomo does not process it.
Then we have information
whether it is about mobile phone network providers
with the IP address,
whether it is about VPN or the museum services,
cloud services, or whether the IP address
has already been used in the past for any
traffic issues.
Most of the time you have to pay for such
additional data.
So, apart from the MaxMind
database, where this is still available for free
for Germany at least,
and only for the USA, I only have the other
information from cost-effective providers.
Yes, if you use them,
so to speak, if you close a contract with such
a provider, then you can
of course decide for yourself whether to process
these criteria and whether you will then
process the location value at all.
If, for example, you find that it comes from
an anonymization service or a VPN,
then I ignore the location.
And I would like to show you this
in an individual example shortly,
where the project with the tech manager
has been implemented.
It was also about considering the
willingness of the visitors of the website,
the geolocation provider, who is then
approached via a web service interface
and with whom we have evaluated the topic
whether it is about spam or cloud trading
and then saved the location as a user-defined
location.
That was with the provider ipregistry.co,
which I think is located in France and which
also supports the HESC-IVO.
And here we have, we are here on the left,
two custom dimensions,
for the country and for the city.
And here we see in the screenshot the saved
information from the city. In brackets we have
country information with saved.
Yes, this is a look at the, and a very simple
look at the JSON structure that
ipregistry provides. I have the
local information here and I have a set
of security parameters down here
that you can check. It is a spam
IP address, cloud IP, proxy, VPN and so on.
And this information
we have partially, or I have partially
evaluated in the script
that has been executed in the Matomu Tech Manager
as a tag, which has been called
after the page view trigger.
And we see here, just briefly,
I'm just getting the country out of the JSON structure.
The city, the spam information
and the cloud information, and if it is not about
spam and cloud, the country and city
are then pushed into the data layer
from the tech manager and
processed there as a tech manager event,
as a data layer event.
And then there is also tracking
towards Matomo, implemented manually.
The tracking event
as dimensions,
the whole thing is therefore
tracked again with the event here and not
with the page view, because the standard investigation
takes place asynchronously and
can take longer than the page view
needs.
Therefore, the whole thing, I say, is tracked a little bit here
not as an event, but as
a user-defined dimension.
And last but not least, again a look at Big Data Cloud.
Here we have in the JSON structure
this confidence parameter, which
indicates to us how trustworthy this
IP address is at all, or this standard address.
And here on the right is
the cell phone address, whether it is
a mobile phone network,
although you have to find out about algorithms.
This is not an information that the service providers
provide.
And finally, I want to quickly summarize
the two recommendations for you.
When using out of the box, of course, the recommendation
goes away from the standard settings, use
the MaxMind GOIP2 database, you have to register.
However, you can use the
free version.
Then the whole thing is set up in such a way that
you update the GOIP2 database
weekly, because MaxMind
makes the database available again weekly.
But do you always have in mind that
anonymization with two or more bytes does not bring any meaningful results?
Do you have in mind that
80 to 90 percent of local results
are correct for 50 kilometers
in a circle, while mobile phone devices
are only at most half?
It is difficult for me to give a really good,
qualitatively good recommendation on how to
filter out these mobile phone locations.
A rough approach could be
to build a segment in Matomo by
filtering out mobile mobile devices.
Which of course does not mean that
mobile phone devices can of course also come over a WLAN,
would then have used a DSL connection again.
Or vice versa, of course, someone can also be
on the road with a laptop and use a SIM card
and would then still appear
here in the segment result.
But it would be an approach to at least
provide a sample overview of the locations
of the visitors on my website.
If you want to be tracked
without tracking,
you should be tracked
by a user without tracking.
Oh, then you still need a
recommendation for the location investigation
and you have to submit it in the consent banner
and then it is only possible
via the version with the web server.
Then I can simply recommend you
to make your own individual solutions with other providers
via a web service API.
You can speak as a user-defined dimension,
as I have shown you.
Of course, you can also write your own plugin,
but of course it is much more complex
to write a Matomo plugin. In this case, you could
deactivate the normal location investigation in Matomo
and provide even more information
with your web services than the providers do in Matomo
and can still select these additional criteria
and save very detailed
or rather very precise data
in Matomo. You can only do this
if you really have the consent of your user.
So, with that I am now
through the quick run.
Now I will ask you
if you have any questions.
So far, everything is clear.
Yes, thank you very much.
There were actually two questions in the chat,
although one has already been answered
in the course of the lecture.
There was also a feedback on the legal
questions about anonymization,
that the anonymization should be sufficient
for one byte. However,
especially with a German competitor
from Matomo, it is also TÜV-certified
how it is done, because the DSGVO assumes
that a personal relationship of a group size
of 15 people is no longer possible.
However, it also states that it is not
legal advice, but not quite
a reasonable truth.
It is also
completely clear to me.
At this point, I do not have the right
to make a legal advice on this topic.
For me, or for the situation
with Matomo, it is of course the case that
we, because of the anonymization
at the location of the development, if I want to
make a legal advice, then I have
of course also saved it in the visitor profile
with only one byte.
Of course, we always have the Matomo
back-end in there, that the anonymization
in the visitor profile with two bytes
is recommended. Now I have to briefly
look at where the screenshot was.
Well, anyway,
you can make the anonymization
with two bytes
in the visitor profile.
And by doing so, of course, many data
protectors from the front say, I want to have
another anonymization with two bytes in the
visitor profile, then of course I can
do that in the location development.
I also have the additional question
whether the country should not also be usable
legally without consent, i.e. without
consent. I think so, because
if you now read the formulation from
this recommendation or this program from 2009,
that back then
it was actually only about this
personability. I mean, if you
google it, there are also bloggers or
other platforms and agencies that of course
also write what to do if you have
your only customer e-commerce shop that
is located in North Africa
and makes an order for you
and that then even the country is still
sufficient to find out
what he actually has here from the
Matomo visitor profile.
This is always something that I find
in practice with the data protection
tasks of the respective website or
individual customers.
My experience is that they are usually
very different and not all,
let's say, the legislation is also
the same in the petition.
Question back to Joachim, recommendation is
with two already analysing
visitor profiles.
Yes, just as an explanation,
the stream is always 40 seconds delayed,
that means it probably takes a short time until the answer
comes from him to the question.
In the meantime, there was also the
question whether you do DSL with a
dynamic IP or a fixed IP.
I only tested once a week
or sometimes after 14 days
I also had a new IP address
checked every time.
Joachim answered that.
Yes, okay.
If there are any other questions,
then it is best to ask now.
Otherwise, the chat room will
still be open if there are any
further discussions.
Otherwise,
thank you very much for the
presentation, which was really very interesting.
And yes, next up is Joachim
Wickel, who is already very active in the chat,
even with a presentation in German.
And yes, I hope there are still many
interesting conversations at the conference today.
Again, thank you very much, Udo.
All right.
See you soon. Bye.