the one hello everyone and welcome in
this talk
and today we are going to talk
about how to configure Matomo for SAAS
and get relevant data for your business
though i'm your speaker for the next
minutes and presenting myself my name is
Ronan Hello i'm an independent web developer in
france and i'm also a web developer
teacher in several school and or two
years ago i built up a MOOC
website
i called her one of dasha hello
dot fr and will contain many couses
about digital analytics and their development
techniques
and i'm also a metal contributor and
i contribute or make many contribution i
like attempts all our plugins the one
it's docked him to turn your modem
interface into dark google tend to and
prevents incoming users to me
to move unf in from google analytics
to the metro interface and they will
love the google tim
playing to the metro interface and a
captcha widget plugin which provide you many
widgets that you can put on your
dashboard and will generate tiny widgets with
a single kp eye on it
the purpose of the stalker we are
talking about memo advance configuration and how
to collect specific data we are adding
more context to the data we are
collecting and how to create awesome reports
in your says and then we are
going further is premium plugins
we are not talking about infrastructure because
there are many peoples admitted mowjcamp already
added it better than i can and
it's not the purpose of my talk
we are assuming that you already have
our gdp our compliance so you already
have a deck cookie a cookie wall
or cookie banner because we are going
to use the visitor log the user
id and user profile and dos and
do the functionality require a user
consent and being in gdp are compliant
so and i imagine that you are
in a basic metal configuration so you
already have deployed the default trucking gun
on every single page you want to
track and this default bear tracking code
will provide you some data such as
pages and stations
unique and new visitors that some default
events the hardware and software configuration visitor
have to to walk through your website
under sometimes i shall have an internal
search the terms basically tracking some real
time action the loads enlightened as a
default events and the ip based location
so that's all the data on a
part of the data that matter more
already collect fire
and you need a bit more unique
user segmentation you need and a well
synced user profile to assess you we
need again to add more context to
the data we collect and we we
are we will be able to create
a custom events custom goals and we
will see in the cylinder
part how to create a report of
a javascript error that the user will
find on your smartphone
the first part of this talk is
about collecting or even data and in
a single time we will see how
to apply them in a property reports
are directly in in your assess battle
one of the first thing you have
to do is to switch between the
basic metal configuration to the metamorph tag
monitor configuration and to do this you
just have to switch between the tracking
code that provides by meta mode and
placing this meta tag manager code
on every single page you want to
track
don't forget to place the default meta
mo statistic dagger which allows you to
recreate the default madman configuration metamorphic manager
provides you a cool interface to create
tags are configuring some awkward stuff like
custom events and many many things
that we will see her in the
in this talk
the things that will have very very
help us to configure metamorph while yosef
is building up custom events during a
long visit the your user will perform
key actions on your software on your
website and you have to track and
the older johnny of your users
to trigger those custom events and collect
them into your meta mo or interface
at this present event will be a
send back to meta mo and i
collected and displayed in the events reports
are right in your meta mo or
instance
and to start regularly i create two
basics event based on the form submission
there is the login andor register from
submission on your says and we just
have to create this a kind of
evans
so look you go adjusting your back-office
creates a metamorph analytics a dagger you
switch then and the target to the
trucking type of evens
and then you have to configure your
evens i said the event category two
else to keep looking and register event
under the same name and define uneven
name as a login
we then have to create a trigger
as a form submit and we just
plug that trigger to the form id
and listen for reason or perform some
form submission sorry so we have to
find the form id
just have to inspect your website and
search for the id of your login
or register form here is a login
that form id and then your trigger
will be created and assigned to the
metamorph event tag don't forget to publish
a new
container on your website or it will
won't work and then you earn you
your dresser in these few steps have
the ability to collect every single time
a user he just looked in in
your suspect form and don't worry about
that you can create the same thing
for register events and fought
many many things i'm talking here about
some entities that you are that you
manage on your suspect form
let imagine for a crm platform that
you have a contact that the user
can create every single time they create
a contact on and have another kind
of entity they can and made the
staff like in development we say he
took credit credit for create read update
and delete the other four
main action that you can do to
almost any entity on your platform
and it will be interesting of collecting
dues action and placing them in the
in the visitor johnny on your website
and one of the four action of
the credit the red action is already
tracked by meta mo only if the
the entity has a one page like
for example if you see an air
bnb and when you can you created
a newer logement and a new house
three the house will be available for
everyone directly from google also matter mo
can correct them
as as a bureau of the this
entity but for the create a date
and delete there is no custom events
by default so you have to to
set them up just as we saw
with the form submission event
another application that i already made for
the rule platform is like when you
have a suspect from wiz
with many workspace on many teams a
user can create one or many teams
and then you can add a member
remove a member or deleted him this
is a factual example of how you
can manage your different custom events and
how you can name them to to
to to them finally visual of them
are right in your
or metamora instance don't forget to earn
package all that different event of the
credit under the same event category name
this category name it will be a
team event probably
then now you have your custom evens
deployed on your platform and you have
the ability in metal to create custom
goals based on those events so madam
will provide you a nigger uneasy interface
to configure a goal and mark all
the session that achieve one or
while many goals and to consider that
said that the visit has converted you
you are a user into a lead
or a customer
so far this or this part you
just have to create a new goal
like a leica at one of the
three you can see there for the
login as you see my goal name
is log-in the description is for a
user connect to his account and the
goal is triggered when an a user
send an event under the event name
is exactly a login
what we said we set up at
the producer site
another huge bot that there will be
a really really interesting and to add
context to our two met timo is
using custom dimensions because he the data
that metamora collect basically is very lacking
contexts and for some reason we are
using metamorph to earn two
added this context to the data
custom dimensions are not really hard to
set up but you have to follow
some rules and here in our configuration
we are using metamorph tag manager and
a madman tag manager we have to
set up a data layer like the
with a piece
of code you can see and because
they bet you you just see an
under screen discard snipe it's an easy
little layer that i filled with two
custom value the looked in actually set
to true and the usual plan actually
set to premium
and then in your or madman tag
manager you just have to go back
to your main meta most artistic tag
and changed the configuration of your matter
mo
value valuable
in this madam available if you scroll
down you will find this section about
custom dimensions m you can create you
can add an earn automatic tracking of
your custom dimensions here the first index
is for use or plan and the
signum index is for logged in honored
user
so about the two custom dimensions i
already tell tell you as you can
see when you are locked in we
just display true in the that a
year and when you are an animal
spirit people are not just not look
in we set false end of the
day or doozy
true kind of data will be and
will be here upload to matter more
every time you change the page and
we will have a full vision of
the status of the user
the single dimensions i already have set
up many times is the user plan
based on
the business offer many suspect from will
be a freemium to premium strategy and
the first time you we have many
individuals but people are using a free
plan that's what you can see in
the further delay you're displayed on the
slide and then the user will try
the soft
using a trial period long as one
or many weeks and then depending of
your solution and then a during his
period i send specific code as a
trial for the value of the user
plan viable in that a lawyer and
then when the trial period as handed
my user i just switched to their
premium plan and ice i just them
did i just send that value into
that at a year of metal
now we know how to create custom
events custom goals and custom dimensions but
we have to attach all of those
data to our user because we are
in a sass configuration and we have
a login and a user
our user is our main entity and
we have to attach of the data
so we are going to know how
to pass a visitor to a user
mademoiselle has a free and as a
completa functionality about user id and two
way of deploying it into yaka here
the first line as you can see
is back that besh a set user
id his father default multiple tracking code
or if you are using metamorph tag
manager uk
can continue to use your data layer
and just add accustomed valuable as user
id and then as value the unique
identifier you just choose between data of
your database the user id will act
as a bridge between your database and
the meta mo database it will be
it will allow
oh you to track a user across
different device they use at home like
a smartphone or a laptop or a
business computer or you you will be
able to track them and then we
as you will see in the next
slide you are able to see every
single
visit an action an event a triggered
right on the profile generated in the
metamorph site so here is my own
profile
and as you can see i'm at
one hundred er visits in reality i'm
very very far off hundred visits vary
more but and the profile is limited
to the last hundred visits
at the display i'm sure that you
can expand this value but actually it's
locked to the hundred and you will
find on this profile every every action
and every events that the user trigger
on the matter my difference you will
see this in the in the next
slide that we won't you die
prickly these ribbed profile to the on
metal but we prefer asking the ici
to create a keystone profile right on
your ass
and then because you're a company you
have to gain some money and we
have to configure metamorph and hence ecommerce
for isis and it's a functionality that
is a built in meta mo you
can enable it just by turning on
the switch to
e-commerce enabled and set up the currency
you use you have your own two
other fully implementation of metamora enhanced ecommerce
you have to configure your data layer
and add some code on the product
page or in the optional a different
pitch
the metamora e-commerce retrigger trigger some events
and those events will be
readable in the events report right in
madame of all the events you will
trigger will be under the even category
of subscription and as you can see
on the screener that i just picked
on the demo the condition because of
my website is not an e-commerce website
and i can't take screenshot of
of my customers and so thanks to
a metamorph on the screen
and as you can see owe the
event action are saying that cancellation and
upgrade about the subscription plan for all
of your users so it will be
pretty cool and as usual you can
add value to events and this value
will will be used to calculate minimum
value of another age vary
you of your revenue
then meta mo we provide you for
two hundred euro per year a funeral
or e-commerce plugin that will allow you
to do two pizza kind of become
in your funnel to define where are
your users are leaving and the spa
town and the
why
the the user are leaving they cut
their cart so they are trigger every
year at every step accustomed events and
this event will be or will be
catch by meta mo and generate some
cool stuff uncle event base a report
but this is on a premium feature
so now we're we are able to
collect data but the most important part
is to retrieve the data and create
some cool reports and analyze them to
take a good decision in the next
time
for this first a folly second part
we will talk about segments because your
metamora instance is no filled by useful
data and we are not going to
visual them in the proper reports using
segments
the first category of segments that i
will create will be gold segments based
on achievements honored of a goal and
here as you can see we just
create cool blue segments which allow you
to filter the visits
the one using the achievements of a
goal and here i thought the goal
to subscribe
which is a if a user have
triggered an event subscribe which convert the
goal subscribe or if it will be
a feature in this segment it's critical
to to activate a segment and continue
to visualize all the reports in my
demo with a future
then the thing that type of a
segment i will allow you to create
is about dimensions segments earlier in the
seoul korea recreate to that custom dimensions
a one father looked in user and
this one one for the user plan
and we can have five types of
results of his dog only logged in
user from user in trial period users
and premium users all of these configuration
will be for me a custom segments
so here for the example i just
created a segment for premium users
so you can select in the first
dropdown the user plane and this is
obviously your custom dimension and then the
operator is is and the value is
about premium
so you will be able to store
as many segments as you want in
your selector and then switch between them
and it will be easier for you
to track and to visualize the johnny
of your user or right under my
remote interface
this signal bouts will be better for
technical or developer person and i invite
you to enable javascript tracking error right
in your meta move configuration for metamora
tag manager user it will be in
the meta mo statistics are available on
you yet just
have a checkbox to enable and it
will collect for you a javascript tracking
error
this report will allow you to regret
the decision of the user who uncontrolled
an error in an attempt to reproduce
it and it will be very very
important for sus owner
the
the functionality a will catch error displayed
in the console and trigger an event
ah which one are all grouped into
the even category of javascript error here
as you can see i have fought
javascript are triggered from the beginning of
the months or so
we have the five so i have
to fix it and as you can
see in then the second part in
even action you will have at the
time that you are all of the
html page all the javascript file which
contain the il
and then if you switch to the
event name you will have the message
right display in this table it's a
copy of the message which is normally
displayed in the console of your web
browser though it will help you to
to view a difference error
to exploit those information or you have
to create a segment this segment will
be uneven category based on javascript error
look at jack evans category is javascript
or this segment will be applied to
all of your information and then you
can switch to the visitor log and
as you can see
this is though force visits that have
encountered a javascript error since the beginning
of the months
there is an kind of problem with
this and because as you can see
every visitors that you can see on
the screen has just made a one
page you and have three actions because
of a javascript trucking and trigger an
event and an event in
metamora are
account into their actions as you can
see a user who just
work through one page has tree action
counted so it will break the ratio
of their actions per page or actions
per session and it will earn
not let you have clear information or
maybe it will be fun to find
a solution to not match those events
into the action counter
and then we enter in the in
my favourite section of the stoke it's
about the reporting a p i saw
a meta mo is no fool of
data on metal heaviness of great and
powerful a poi so why not using
it in your back office to generate
context all chats
this is a screenshot of my own
websites our i provide some contents mainly
textual content and here are some blog
post as you can see in my
homemade back office i have a chats
and his chart is generated directly from
metamorph
in korea met him i p i
provides me the data i need and
and those that are are organized a
page per page so i asked the
metal api i providing and the post
you are all and the metamora api
i i'll let me
find data that data i just configured
them a demo a poi to answer
me in a decent format and then
i i i took those data and
used them to build a homemade charts
using the html library charges
and as you can see it's pretty
nice and i have the information right
in my back office and i don't
have to connect to my multiple instance
to visual them and adjusting the rights
of the chats you can see my
visit kp i information and the bounce
rates of every single
episodes and as a real user i
prefer looking at those chats right in
my back office then switching to the
metro interface and searching in their page
reports
to to to get those informations
and then we can do exactly the
same thing with user a i based
data and so here is my own
profile because i don't want to show
you or other providers but here as
you can see i have is already
set up on my website and the
set the user id let me asking
the ip i have my demo
to get every page you earn sessions
and from earth specific user so he
here though jason the thought of his
rise in a custom job to grant
a clear position of the user visits
as you can see i'm pretty active
on my website and their first and
nov i have
had a long work to reorganize contents
on our site so i made almost
four hundred and fifty visits but i
can see if a user is still
active on its on their website
and an id of a cms integration
of that metamora a poi is because
of the tenements about google search engine
and the integrating their core web vitals
so here and it's an idea that
we can build a plugin for cms
like wow
press a to show up just on
the line of the the table that
display all the page all the posts
are published on though your website a
clear indicator read to a green indicator
to to determine if the page load
faster on it
and i am not graffiti but i
just make that little lower visualization based
on the this is a screen from
the the documentation of repress i just
add pagespeed under a greener green lights
but as you can see it will
be a bit array to have this
kind of informations
and then and to go further and
you can also create custom announce but
this you can create to someone else
for unmoved area every supporter not even
not only sasa suspect from but i
i create all the time customer asks
about dropped and visit to drop in
revenue and if you're suffer from drop
in subscriptions and it will be very
important for you to to keep an
eye on it and you can do
it simply by installing the custom adults
plugin who is already available on the
market which undone
marketplace of fatima
and then to go or to continue
and go further and furthermore there is
a premium bundle of begin which is
specifically into reasons for your sass and
as a heat map and session recording
which generates an amount and amount of
data but will allow you to recreate
the position of your user just imagined
that this plugin mixed with the jess
tracking error and you will be able
to recreate exactly the position of the
user to try to reproduce their own
the the the the gs era that
he uncontrolled in inherit visits and we'd
be pretty pretty useful for fires us
and especially if you have a platform
that shackleton's for many users as a
content at the door and visitors you
will be a friend you will be
a really are
interested in the media and eight explosion
which allow you to track a video
and the audio and give you information
such as the lead the lengths of
the video that user really watch all
and then the the level of the
volume when they're here are some audio
or video
and the next one on the day
i didn't found her on the base
is the user flu
plugin that allow you to track to
visualize not to try to visualize all
of your users and on the on
the platform and but it is very
more specific
and through a to certain kind of
sauce
though thank you for watching i will
look for the different edition you have
to to to to ask to me
and the and thank you for all
the people who are still there until
the this presentation
so as i can see i have
one question is can you disclose the
name of the suspect from you applied
a dos implementation
i actually for the demonstration you saw
mine and the the other one startups
at not in the city where i
live actually and and i i think
no i can't they those name
according to you and all what is
missing within metal
what is missing in matrimony
i don't think it's if it's missing
but for me it's about
the data storage so if your interests
in google and attics three and four
as you can see they are they
break the the change for thou thou
breaking them that at her age to
another one based on event and matomo
is a mix of
and as you can see for just
tracking all ecommerce tracking they are all
based on events and which is pretty
cool and i think the way of
the future followed for analytics software but
it's a break many reports and simply
because the older either
that's all i do
mixed a mirror under on the same
place so to get a clearer vision
we're we almost every time have to
create a customer segments and to to
see only specific events we need one
maybe the events report will could be
better
is there any other christian i
don't think
and let's wait just a few more
seconds to make sure that nobody else
is making questions in the chat ok
okay i have another question why i
poi did you find a solution to
have less five and a tenant it
on a specific page
i
and my ip i called all based
on the timestamps at the door and
i guess it's about day not five
or ten minutes it's a specific and
i don't remember because all of my
the time selector or abe's on day
weeks and months acidic or not
about two minutes but maybe i am
sure you will find your answer or
writing the recommendation
and how hard is it to extract
data out of the reporting a poi
of meadow mo and show it on
a webpage like you did it really
depends of the skills you already had
so the metamora idea is pretty cool
and pretty easy to use and it
respect
to stand out offer many many a
p iso if you're a web developer
you're already familiar with the use age
to you the use of apia so
the metal part is not the harder
for me i think the hunter is
tuned to recreate the interface the interface
or in your back of his butt
asking metamora via the ip i to
get the data you need is just
about
twenty minutes if you have to read
the documentation and
i think i spend most of my
time about
haters and i will quit requesting to
the ip i but not to
that is pretty pretty simple to to
set up maybe i will make a
video tour to explain how i met
him or a p i will work
on the tradition that actually it's not
so hot
and valentin asked a pr is powerful
but what are the limits
the limits of the ip i and
especially i so that when i when
i try to room
to create lists so i out on
my own back of his i have
a list of all my posts with
vegetation and stuff like that and i
will use the ici to to display
informations right in this list but it
will very very be heavy to carry
on and the will make
many many regrets mere many requests to
metamora for the update were
set on this main page they think
the metaphor idea is powerful to send
data through metal and to ask them
but only in a main entity page
so i as you can see i
just used the metamorph a p i
n a
view page of a single entity as
a single post entity or single user
entity but not in a page with
several entity because of the amount of
requests we have to create if it's
a a data table visualization or beach
and what are the limits the limits
a is a is like all the
a p i n so if you
follow the the arrests documentation which are
which one is a kind of a
guide for you who buy who built
a napier and if you followed those
guidelines and
you may be have to create many
requests to get just one information she
want to create some custom reports about
it's not about matthew a p eyes
must about gerrick a poi guidelines
i hope that i answer your question
which was a bit
large
is there any other questions
and apparently there are no further questions
in the chat
thank you for joining a convent for
this very interesting session
thank you thank you too i think
you are all of you for for
being there today and thank you for
the organisation of this wonderful event
do so we finished a little bit
earlier with this session but i'd like
to invite everyone to join me to
join us at five pm for the
closing notes thank you