of the different conferences
this evan to could not have been
without lucas winkler who is the guy
who took on his shoulders
a huge in their melons an impressive
amount of work he was here all
the time where i couldn't manage anything
anymore because i didn't have more time
i didn't have more energy and this
is where did the guy who is
doing kind of everything
we even met summer camps where would
like to thank him silva's when we
joined the team during to the evolution
of the creation of metamora camp she
was the one in charge of the
moderation of the different talks was all
communication apart i would like to sink
as well us define
i connect from the netherlands with a
book who helped us a vodka will
help us with all the system administration
the i t infrastructure for the lake
has weather was here for the duration
of the talk in french a huge
huge thanks to open digital us who've
an autumn buzz who is the one
hold the all the different streamer and
sings to him the true that we
got the recording of all the different
conferences i would like to sank as
well although digital is the ab team
and in particular thomas jefferson that some
of the attendees i've seen many time
i'm not one percent sure about the
number of told us that he made
but i think it's close to five
and they were all
incredible so thank you very much tomas
would like to thank as what stiff
and given to him as a number
and israel really came near careful the
organizing team lucas am i missing anyone
here within the organizing team
i can't think of anyone at the
moment hopefully i also don't miss one
book
i would like to thanks again or
to speak else they were coming from
all the different countries that i've made
or greats and impressive speech and of
course lucas when crowe zoo i came
they can richest duck from the inner
crust company was making
the conference favorite times of difference of
twelve i was from new zealand high
power else from the digital is a
b team in sweden tomatoes at moment
from germany nathan fight us silva as
well the italian team that represented by
that he did pull vecchio pierluigi to
cease
a close you shall again thomas chinese
stiff and connect pizza worker to my
stepson christian i dunno they're not embarrassed
about the steven victor vic safe from
an garish various boutique niche of headache
foster or hated pulse catchy new bay
from the united
kingdom and all not at all i'm
sorry lucas same questions again did i
forgot anyone here within this list i
hope you didn't
cause i mean they saw an adult
be complete and sorry for my pronunciation
as well i would like onslaught to
thank all sponsors so metromile who on
small hello has to create and use
a logo which is similar to
sales and those were a little husky
was met to move even though communication
support was well supported us in time
of communication also probably we felt was
communication impact we couldn't have reached today
or at least some of you guys
so i will like on small to
say thank you met tomorrow
of course to provide the world with
a free software and the gpl license
i would like to thank as well
of han digital who as i said
out the one in charge of all
the streaming part i would like to
sync on small the company of a
stiff and couldn't even get us who
missed analytics so as a soul no
heart from peter
our worker and styles from ligaments and
many was a
as well that i would like to
thank who as i said many organizers
have been speakers during this medical camp
and who has spent a lot of
time and energy within this this project
and of course us when i'm shortly
off cost of under the organizers you
forgot to match
of course europe or na who initially
had the idea to organize hematoma camp
and that ivana getting everything started and
are planning yeah there's a whole concept
from the beginning so thanks again for
this yeah thank you thank you so
much i have to
she said that i couldn't make it
without all of you guys and without
all that said i t free software
technology expertize i have to set up
my myself even with all the analogy
that i brought into it it's
i just put the nlg of someone
who to create an event and and
that's it do that thank you thank
you very much i i appreciate that
and of course thank you to all
of you for ten years because it's
always hard to find though some time
i'll on our walking time to come
and assist all those conferences
thank you for all your kindness because
we didn't have any any trolling experience
on the social networks you have been
all nice to each other as for
the chats you played the game you
accepted to i posted some question on
shut up not moved at all you
send some questions
and to the question that most of
you would probably ask are where the
materials off of the speakers and where
the rico did the recording of the
tourists off wanted the recording of the
talks correct me if i'm wrong lucas
but they will be posted on the
ul has named videos that metal candle
on
all within the coming days and right
eye gallery below to set up the
video platform in the next state and
editing the older recordings of cross will
take some time and we will just
go on and publish them once staffed
by this so if you follow us
on their social media accounts or if
you look on the tv
your platform every few days you've really
been notified whenever a new recording is
published
so yeah if you just the refreshment
to move can look all web page
from time to time issue follow us
on the social network which senses that
we will announce at some point that
the videos are live you can already
find one which is the one about
the pre maximo camp the event and
if you have some time i invite
you to a breaker meet that nakamura
combat dog which is the based on
walk adventure which is a social place
on which you can move and meet
different people who are connected on the
platform and then interact with them in
in in real
timing video on webcam and i'm going
to go down in something like two
minutes on safe finish the slide and
hope that they will have the opportunity
to meet some of you guys zealand
and to connect a little bit more
like if you're wearing a physical presence
lucas then on top of view of
any
any things left that you elect to
do so before we close officially the
oven
nothing major from you just thanks everyone
for making different possible and such a
huge success with it was the same
for me to thank you for your
time out of your speakers and just
specially
perfect thanks you guys that kill a
few other good we can then fold
the one we still have time just
go on the admit that met to
move chem dot org and we will
be there only no doubt about it
have a great weekend and thanks for
spending some time with us had met
him again
that