Hi, everyone. Sorry for this small delay. So it's currently 14.04. The idea is to go
up to probably 14.50, something like this. Feel free to ask as many questions as you
can on chat.matamoochem.org. This presentation is a bit special because it's not oriented
towards, let's say, technical things about Matamoo, neither about the software. That's,
I guess, probably the only conference talk, which is about business. So you may say, oh,
okay, that's kind of a dirty subject and so on and so forth. But I really think that's,
let's say, one of the key issues which are dealing with Matamoo, which is about how to make
a community growing. And one key thing about making a community growing is, of course,
to get attention from the outside. And one, let's say, one big thing which is out of getting
attention is how you can make a living out of Matamoo and how some individuals can
make it more like a business job opportunity and then have good reasons to work on a day-to-day
basis on Matamoo. So let's say how they can move from their current job that they maybe
not love into a job that they love, dealing with free software, which was my case. Of
course, when I started as an analyst, I was mostly working with proprietary solutions,
such, of course, as the one of Google. But thanks to the business opportunities I got,
I got the possibility to switch from Google Analytics Solutions and others to a full
activity around Matamoo. And that's really what this conference is about. It's about
my feedback, about how I succeeded in developing business opportunities based on Matamoo,
and as well what I observed on the field about what other companies are doing, what it works,
and what doesn't. And that, of course, you as an individual or your company can take an advantage
from and maybe, thanks to this feedback, help to develop more products and services based on
Matamoo and have as well afterwards contribution to the Matamoo community. So about myself, my
name is Ronan Chardonneau. I'm a digital marketing trainer at Matamoo Analytics since 2010. Back at
the time, more than a decade ago, Matamoo wasn't the software that it is today. So I have to say
that I've been probably one of the pioneer who bets on Matamoo. It's a few weeks at that time,
in order to start develop a business on it. I made the choice of not developing an agency,
of still staying a one-man business in order to not, let's say, be trapped into a system,
into an environment in which I won't have any control over my company anymore. I had the chance
to write five books about digital analytics. To be honest, I wrote three about Google Analytics,
one about Google Tag Manager, and one about Pewik. Pewik being one of the first that I published.
It unfortunately did not get the attention that I expected back then. And now, I mean, the attention
that it was in 2011 when I wrote it wasn't the same as today. I guess that today, probably, if I
have to write it, it will be, of course, far more consequent and will probably get far more
attention than it got back then. I'm associate professor in digital marketing at ERE Angers,
which is a university in France. I'm professor since more than a decade ago. I'm one of the few
Matamoo analytics certified professional when this certification was still on. You can still
find this certification on the project that I'm holding on a URL named FlossMarketingSchool.com,
on which I got the agreement from the Matamoo team to get the list of questions and revamp the
certification program in order to make it more like a free and accessible program to everyone.
So you can easily go on FlossMarketingSchool.com and look at the certification program and
answer to the different questions and get a certificate which is issued by the FlossMarketingSchool.com,
which has not much value, but which is here in order to test your knowledge about Matamoo analytics.
And yeah, I already mentioned it in the previous conference. I worked for Matamoo,
let's say the InnoCraft company, from July 2017 to July 2019. The purpose of this
talk, the following one, is to really give you some feedback about how to make a living
from Matamoo analytics. So make a living, I mean, it's like how you can make your first euros out of
it, but as well how you can fully live on Matamoo. It took me a lot of time in order to make it.
It took me about five years in order to make it, but I succeeded. And of course, it wasn't like
five years in which I wasn't working at all. I had my first and second employer who were, of course,
making me my main living and on my spare time, I was doing from here and then some extra services
on Matamoo, which give me some, let's say, trust in, okay, definitely there are some space in order
to build something up, but just to let you know that I didn't jump out into the late,
straight away took me up to five years in order to feel confident enough that there was enough
markets in order to provide Matamoo analytics products and services. But remember that it was
back then in 2010, so the market wasn't the one which is nowadays, which is, of course, far more
flourishing. This talk is mainly for one-man business that I call freelancers here and agencies.
And this is a business oriented talk, so I'm not going to talk about techy stuff or anything like
this. It's really more about business. My business history is the following one. Here, of course,
business history means Matamoo analytics history. So, in 2010, I got my first client sign for
training thanks to a landing page. So, in fact, my history with P-Week back then at that time
really started because I was a SEO practitioner, so search engine optimizer, and I was working for
a web agency which was providing free software website creation services. So, to say a web agency
which was providing the creation of website with jumla technologies, WordPress technologies.
At that time, it was named Magento as well, PrestaShop, all that kind of free software
technologies. And as a, let's say, web marketing specialist, I just was a bit curious that, okay,
we are all the time creating all those websites, including Google Analytics within those. And I was
wondering, okay, is there another technology on earth which may be a free software, not
proprietary software that we can embed on the website that we deliver in order to be more,
let's say, privacy compliant or in order to align with the mission of what free software is about.
This is where I discovered that there was a technology which was named P-Week. I had at
that time people within the web agency which were passionate enough in order to deploy
a P-Week instance, so to say, a server running P-Week on it. And then because we had this server
and because we were starting to deliver some website with P-Week included within it,
that I got the idea because I was also in charge of publishing content on the
web agency's website. Okay, why not just creating a landing page in which I will announce that we
are delivering a training about P-Week Analytics that at that time I didn't even know about.
So we just start with a bet that we just sent in the lake in order to say something which
wasn't true, I have to say now, that, hey, we are an agency and we deliver trainings about
Matomo Analytics. And I did that with several technologies. I did it with AWStats. I did it
with Open Web Analytics, which for some time has been a competitor of Matomo Analytics. And one
day the phone rang and it was one of the biggest companies in France who was on the phone. We were
really a small agency. We were dealing with really small clients in my hometown. And this
French multinational company just called us and said, okay, we saw on your page that you are
delivering P-Week Analytics training. We want you on board. We want you to come in Paris La
Défense, which is the biggest business center in France. You go in this tower on the fifth floor,
on the 50th floor, and you go and make the training. Wow. I don't know for you guys,
for the people who know what Matomo looks like more than 10 years ago, but it was not like the
fanciest product to show on Earth. And they had to deliver a training about it. And the thing is
that during the training what was even funnier is that we didn't even have an internet connection.
And the training that I did was probably one of the worst that I ever delivered. But the thing is
that I stressed so much about it that I over trained myself on the P-Week Analytics documentation,
that I got enough in order to write a full book about it. And then I went to a publishing house
edition that I already worked with, and I said, okay, look, I have all this content material. I
can make a book out of it. And this is how the story starts. So, I just start with a bit, with a
big client, big pressure, big contract, and then enough, let's say, money in order to take a risk,
which is about publishing the content that I wrote, that I made over my weekend's periods.
So, this is how it works. Then I got this book, which, of course, in the mind of people makes you
like a superstar, whereas I have to say that I didn't get many sales, probably around a thousand
of books have been sold dealing with P-Week Analytics. And then what I did from 2012 to
2014, you know, I was still working with proprietary solution, and I was still frustrated
that P-Week was not, let's say, getting that much attention. So, I decided to create two websites
in order to attract some leads. It started to work. I gave some conferences here and there.
It helped me make me more confident about talking about the software. I started to link a bit more
with the community. I've been involved into a measure camp. I don't know if you know measure
camp. It's kind of the biggest analytics community that you can find on Earth. I started to spread
the word about that measure camp. And I started to have more leads dealing with the time it was
in P-Week. And it was really making me confident. And it was really the kind of leads that I wanted,
like they were overseas. The projects were very empowering. And every lead that I got made me
even more comfortable and really made me realize that proprietary solutions are just not
showing you the full story and not helping you to educate yourself better. And that free software
is like offering you far more possibilities in terms of learning and education, which makes them
really great opportunities. And in 2015, I felt enough confident in order to say, okay,
what do I want to do in my life? And this is where I really saw that the mission of a free
software and mathematics in particular really align with what I want to do for my future.
And this is where I said, okay, I'm going to invest some money in order to join an accelerator.
We call it also an incubator in order to have some mentors, people who can tell me if my project,
so to say, to create a full company based on mathematics services is reliable or not.
And it just took me, in fact, three months. So I hired two interns in order to build up
a new website, in order to test some stuff around tools around Matomo and so on and so forth.
And in three months, that was it. In three months, I got enough contracts in order to
make one year living. When I say one year living, I'm not talking about millions of euros here.
I'm talking about the time in 2015. I'm talking about a limit of 30,000 to 35,000 euros of turnover
for a one-man business. So I'm not talking here about a high-paid person. I'm really talking about
what is making enough for one person to live only on Matomo analytics services.
And I reached, in three months, I got the contract for 12 months
lengths of 30,000 to 35,000 euros of turnover. I have to say today, I prefer to disclose the
information right now that I'm making still as a one-man business 70,000 euros a year.
I don't want to make more because if I go more, I definitely go for a limited company,
which is not the thing that I want. But I can tell you that right now on the market,
if you are good enough, if you know how to be a good salesperson, if you are ready to go
international, that's the key thing. Most of my turnover, 60%, closely to 60% of my turnover
is not on the national market, which is France. It's on the international market.
From 2017 to 2019, I joined the InnoCraft team. So let's say it's the first
maintainer, the first contributor to the Matomo analytics project. That has been probably one of
the greatest experience that I got in my career. I got many, but this one really helped me a lot.
This morning we got Richard Stark, who gave a conference to which I asked what it is to
work at InnoCraft and really what he said aligned with what I said. I haven't been fired by the
company because you can see here that I left the company in 2019. It's just that InnoCraft is based
in New Zealand, so it's a 12-hour time zone of delay. And it was very exhausting on both sides.
I mean, like attending the conference by 9 p.m. in like once or twice a week is really
dramatic in terms of family life balance. And I came to a point of doing it for like two years
working with 12 hours time of delay. I just said, okay, I cannot continue. I'm destroying my family
life. It was a bit the same thing for them. So that's why I decided to say, okay, I'm probably
more helpful staying in Europe, helping from Europe, developing the Matomo Analytics community to
expand rather than being within the InnoCraft team. But I have to say that those two years have been
extraordinary in order to understand what is the responsibility of holding a software such as
Matomo is. And from 2019 to now, this is what I said here, I succeed to double my revenues, so to say
70,000 euros. And I'm now, in fact, helping partners around the world to as well make a
living out of Matomo. This is the list of the different services that I identified by which
you can make a living out of Matomo. I'm not providing all of them, but I have some partners
who are delivering them. So I can, of course, say a couple of words about it. So first one is about
web hosting, which is mostly what big agencies are providing. Then you get the consulting part,
which is probably well as a lot to do, which is about solving complex issues. By solving complex
issues, I mean measurement plan, support any issues, analytics things like creating reports
and that kind of thing. Training. So training is really the thing that I'm known for, that I like
the most to do. But this is a small personal thing, which is about sharing knowledge about
how to use Matomo. Then the first one that I identify is translation. It hardly ever happened
to me, but that's possible to do. It's about translating Matomo. And trust me, there are a
lot to do because it's a software which is evolving a lot and which is supporting almost
all the languages on Earth. Custom development, which is about how to create something which
does not exist yet within Matomo. And the sixth one, which is about writing documentation,
which happen far more than we can expect. So those are, let's say like six different services
that I identify. And the idea is to give you some feedback about those so that you can identify a
little bit more about what you could do if you would like to expand your set of services or if
you would like to sell services based on Matomo. That's web hosting. This is really what I said
most of agencies are doing. What is great with web hosting is that it brings constant revenue.
So that's of course the most obvious thing. It's like you deliver websites. Why not you add to it
the possibility to as well offer when you sell your website to sell a web analytics package.
It brings a lot of opportunity to sell other services. And I'm quite amazed to see that a lot
of agencies which are already delivering websites with Matomo including are only ever taking this
opportunity to sell more services on top of it like consulting. Because you don't really need to
be like, I mean, you don't need to have followed some analytics studies. I mean, I did it myself,
I mean, I did it myself, but most of the time when a client has an issue, they more have an issue
with not about understanding the data, but which is more about how the software is working, how the
UI is working, which means that agencies think that they cannot easily sell consulting services
because they think they don't have the expertise. Whereas definitely they could because they have a
lot of different clients in which they deploy Matomo. So it means that they probably already
have the knowledge that their own clients need, but it's just that their own clients
do not really know how to express themselves in order to say, hey, I need some help. So I really
think that web hosting is in fact one very good way to sell consulting services. The disadvantage
of web hosting is that scaling Matomo is far more complex than it seems. And that's probably the
issue that most of the clients that I'm training do not realize that they just think that Matomo
is like Google Analytics and they totally forgot that they need to have a system administrator on
board. And as they never know about, as they never heard about what is a system administrator, because
when you use a Google Analytics solution, you don't have to care about this part.
Well, they don't know that they need a profile for it and they don't know how complex it can be to
host and manage a database which is growing day after day. So this is clearly the thing that
you need to take into consideration if you provide web hosting is that if your client
has a lot of visit, it means a lot of trouble. Not as well that this part is really the bring
a lot of opportunity to sell other services is really now far more easier to do than the
Matomo team has developed a plugin specifically for WordPress, which means that in one click,
you can already deploy WordPress without taking care of the Matomo database installation,
which makes it of course very easy to handle a Matomo project.
Web hosting is of course not something that one man business can easily sell because you need
different expertise. That's more service for agencies. And as I just said, you need to have
a system administrator on board all the time, because if you have a complex installation,
so to say an installation which has a lot of traffic, you will need to have someone on board
in order to help you with this. The second service, which is consulting, the pros are
here. The pros are the following one is that it can bring you constant revenues if you can
take care of your clients. That's really a part which is important. In consulting, it's not really
about just delivering the thing. It's also about ensuring that the fix, that the support that you
provided help your clients to go further and go to another issue. Of course, an issue which will
come by him, but it's really important here to keep going on the contact with your client
if you want to have this constant revenue thing. It cannot work if your clients cannot find
the solution based on the data of Matomo, because you will see that most of the time when there is
a silence, it probably means that you don't know it, but your client has an issue with Matomo,
probably a server issue, or probably the answer that you give them. Let's say he lost hope in you,
let's say. Let's say silences are not good at all. If you want to keep selling consulting,
you have to ensure that your clients got the answer thanks to the solution that you provided them.
If you are a good salesperson, and this is clearly what is happening for my company and as well my
partners, is that you can sell big contracts. What we call by big contracts is big clients,
and those big clients have a lot of needs dealing with measurement plan. As measurement plans are
very complex, as it implies a lot of different meetings. Let's say high expectations in terms
of project management. This is where big contracts are coming, and this is where you can start to
save your company. This is where you can save your year. This is where you get the most interesting
project, because it's highly motivating. You can clearly see that you have enough to eat for the
next two years, and those are really the biggest, probably the greatest thing in order to start to
build a business based on that. It's really to find those consulting projects which are very
close to what we sell in analytics in general. Let's say measurement plan, meetings, helping
the company to grow and learn in terms of knowledge, and those are really the most important
thing. The disadvantage is that they can be super complex, so here this is where you need to be very
careful, because Matomo can be embedded into a very complex information system on which the
expertise is very rare. Here I'm thinking, for example, about companies or institutions who are
deploying, for example, Matomo and Microsoft SharePoint, and here in order to find out the
people who have the expertise about Microsoft SharePoint. Wow, there are not that many people.
Probably those people are as well very busy, so it's really hard because there are not that
much documentation. You need to test a lot, and there are some places in which you cannot embed
the tracking code, and so on and so forth. Of course, if your client is disappointed,
it's a complicated project. You get some gray hair, and so on and so forth. This is where you
need to really well identify before starting the project how complex it's going to be.
Tomorrow I will have a great conference that I will add with a client of mine,
Katie Newby, on a project that I didn't know, so I fully recommend you to assist to this conference
in which I will explain the way we decided to work, but just to let you know, well study your
project before saying yes. Of course, this is the work of meetings that you do prior starting the
project in order to see if you feel confident to do it. Sometimes it's hard to get your money back.
It goes back to the super complex project that you can get or the wrong subcontractor that you hire.
People will not make a measurement plan which is really reliable or even submit. It happens a lot
on longer projects. The people that you get in contact with are finally laid off or at least
who have some issues, and then your project starts to be late, and this is where you get
your money back a little bit late, so this is where you really need to rely on more than one
client in consulting if you want to make a proper living. Training is definitely the thing that I
love to do the most and that I'm doing as well the most. What I really like in training is that it
brings you high revenue in a short period of time. There is a lot of demand, far more than what we
can expect because there are of course the people who are searching for it, but there is as well the
people who would like to have one but who has not yet expressed that they would like to have one.
It's all about knowing who is using Matamor and once you know it, it's really easy when you get a niche
market, for example the educational market, let's say the universities, when you know that
there is at least one demand from one guy and that the other universities are using Matamor,
it's kind of easy to knock at the other door and say, hey, by the way, are you interested in training about Matamor?
When I do the training, even if I'm not overselling myself here, clearly I'm getting a lot of consulting demands.
I think here, the key thing here is that when you do training, just don't be the guy who is here in order to
just deliver something and then run away. It's always good to show, of course, with let's say hiding the name
of the other client, but to show how you are working and the way you work as a consultant is very interesting
because then you are showing them that you have an organization and what kind of services that you are providing
or your partners are providing and then they feel very confident. You can do as well cross-selling.
This is definitely what I'm doing here with some other people who are at Matamor camp today,
such as Enprunt Digital and Digitalist AB or even the Matamor team itself is recommending premium features
or talking about one specific cloud infrastructure and so on and so forth.
That's really something that you can do. In fact, the attendees of the training are looking for as well.
They are not just interested in your training themselves. They are interested in the possibilities
that one can have with the product and services. The cons of the training is just one short revenue.
Most of the time, it's hardly ever the case that the company will take a training from you
unless it's a very big company will take another one. It happens in some cases when the company is growing
and they get new employees and they want those employees to get trained and they know that you have done a good job
the first time, but most of the times they hardly ever come back for a training.
The second cons that I put here is more for agencies. Most of the time, an agency will spend a lot of time
in training one specific employee or this employee a bit special because he succeeded or she succeeded
in training herself or herself and decided now to go on its own. Then it's really hard to find a resource back,
someone who is motivated. I think here, if you are an agency, it's always good to secure this resource
by making him a stakeholder or something like this because this resource within your company
is really of high value. Just to let you know that it takes a lot of time to train a trainer.
Google Analytics, for example, in six months, you can succeed in having a beginner trainer.
In Matomo, even after a decade, I still don't know everything about Matomo. Just to let you know
that it takes a lot of time because it's a lot of concepts. It's not really about the solution
in itself, which is complicated. It's about understanding what is the free software philosophy,
what it implies, and to not be scared of the techy part. That's server, deploying something on a
server, SSH, all that kind of thing. That's the kind of thing you need to have an interest in
in order to understand how the solution is working because probably the trainer will be as well
the middleman for all your different projects. The guy talking with the developers, with the analyst,
with the salesperson, with the system administrator, with the client. That's where it
takes a lot of time in order to understand all the expectations from one another.
The fourth service that I'm thinking of is translation. I haven't yet received any
demand for money for that, but I can clearly see that there are some demands because Matomo is
evolving a lot with new plugins, and those plugins do not get translated sometimes,
or at least not in some specific languages, which means that when you have big companies,
let's say, for example, a company based in Japan, in Taiwan, or even in, I don't know,
in Venezuela or in Norway, just imagine that those guys, when they install those premium
features on those two plugins, they've got a UI of Matomo, which is Norwegian and then English,
or Japanese and then English. It's like a two-sided person and a two-sided coin in one,
and it doesn't make sense. This is where they look at the software and they say,
okay, you recommended me to install this software, and it's not even fully translated, so you are
just giving me half of the software. Could you fix that? This is where you can definitely
find the people to translate it. The translation service, which has been recently put
on Matomo, is very instinctive and helps you in translating it straight away. You also have some
plugins which are specific, which allow you to make some extra translation. Here, I think that
there is a lot of business opportunities to sell translation services for Matomo for your
end-customer. It's just that I never succeeded in selling one yet. Custom development is one of the
sexiest services to sell. The problem is that it's very, very, very long. The pros of it is that it's
very exciting. It's a non-project. You can really empower Matomo, but the cons is that it requires
a lot of expertise and energy in order to kickstart the project. Here, I'm not talking about
one-man business or an agency who will create the custom plugin itself, but more like an agency or
one-man business who is chasing, finding out the profile, who is able to create the Matomo
plugin. Those developers exist. You can easily find them on the community. I'm thinking here of
Peter. I'm thinking here of Stefan. I'm thinking here of maybe Lucas. There are some people within
the community who can develop those plugins for you. It's just that you will be the middleman
in charge of listening to your client, writing the spec document, and then on-link it to the
web developer. What I found out within those custom development project issues is that,
in my case, I'm working a lot with French institutions, is that when you work with a
French institution, it's not that easy to hire a resource from the outside. Let's say outside of
your own country, so France, which, of course, makes the process even more complicated.
You need to find the right profile to ensure that, according to the law or according to the
constraints which are given to you by your clients, you can find the right profile.
Then you need to not screw up when you write out the spec document. Then you need to ensure that
the spec of the client corresponds to what the developer is able to provide because of the core
of Matomo. It's a really exciting project, but it's really hard to start to kick it to get paid.
Something which could, by the developer, be issued in three weeks will probably take
one year or two years in order to be delivered. Just to let you know that custom
development is, as well, a complex project. Last but not least, a service that I'm thinking of,
which is, to me, as well, very exciting, which is writing documentation. It happens quite a lot,
mostly by institutions who do not want to rely on the documentation of Matomo.org, which,
by the way, is really well done, but they want something which is more specific,
with words which are different, with screenshots which are using their own data, with probably
another language. That's really great. This is how you can develop your skills dealing with
marketing materials. As I said, there's a lot of demand. It's just that those demands are mostly
coming from big clients, not small ones, which, of course, make it more like a niche project.
The only issue that I can see here, which is, of course, subject to discussion, is that the
licenses on which you are writing those documentation can be restrictive. Maybe you're
not going to be able to use those documentation that you write for, let's say, a public project,
which, of course, is a bit heartbreaking, but that's part of the game. You get money for,
and this money that you get for, you are under restrictions. Most of the time, it's under
a closed license. The biggest mistake that I'm seeing on the field dealing with businesses
is that you cannot know everything as a one-man business. You will have to learn about
subcontracting. Really, at the beginning, I thought that I could be able to handle all the
parts of Matomo, and I just find out that it's just too big, that I cannot be good in everything.
So, you need to have a network. It's not like tomorrow you can decide to create your own
business based on Matomo. No, you need to have a network. You need to have guys who are good on
board. Definitely, those guys, you can find them on chat.matomocamp.com, because people
who are attending today are probably already familiar with Matomo Analytics, and probably are
familiar with it. You can find them as well on forum.matomo.org, but it's all about network.
I cannot deliver all the products and services that I'm saying today if I don't have my network.
Matomo is not Google Analytics. That's the biggest mistake that most agencies are doing.
So, just think that it's a clone of Google Analytics. Even if it's the mission of Matomo
to have Google Analytics as a free software through Matomo, that's not at all the same thing.
Matomo is a free software. With this, it embraces the free software philosophy, which means that
even if people will correct me about it, it's a techie solution. If it's a techie solution,
you need to be at least techie in order to understand the heart of it, how it's working,
and, of course, how to sell it afterward. You have to understand the free software philosophy, and
it's a huge piece. It's a long-term return on investment. As I said, it took me five years in
order to be able to make a living out of it, but it's really worth it. You cannot succeed if you
don't love the software. That's the thing. Don't blame the software. Blame yourself if there's
something which is not working, because if there's something which is not working, it probably means
that there is something that you are missing somewhere along the education of the software.
How to promote your Matomo services? This is the list of things that I'm doing which are
working, but all together. It's not just one single thing. Writing books, tutorials, publishing
marketing materials, or education materials is working. I have about 500 videos running on the
internet, and it really helps. People are not coming straight to us thanks to those videos.
It happens sometimes, but it's making you visible, which is the most important thing. People can put
a face on your name, and then they can rely on you if they have any questions. Other websites or
several websites introducing your services. I have about close to 300 websites talking about what
I'm doing, which helps a lot. Give talks and conferences, share with the community, have a
network, and then create your own network. That's as well one of the reasons why I was
interested in setting up this Matomo camp. That was about opening all the possibilities of connecting
with other people, finding people who can be subcontractors of my project if I have too many
demands, or if I cannot do something, or as well potential clients, and so on and so forth. That's
the way it works. Mention it to your existing clients. Do not forget to always be on social
networks. Connect with those clients of yours, and tell them about the changes which occur on
Matomo recently. Involve yourself within free software projects. That's as well very important
to understand the free software philosophy. That's it for this conference. I really hope
that you enjoy it and that you have plenty of questions. Okay, Lucas. Well, I guess
we don't have any questions for this talk. I hope everything was clear. Thank you,
once more, for choosing this conference, and hope you are all having a great Matomo camp. Thank you.