the higher one a sorry for the
smaller delay and so it's currently
when or for the idea to go
up to her probably fourteen or fourteen
fifties or something like this
i feel free to ask as many
question as you can and shut that
metal candle on this song presentation is
a bit special because it's not oriented
towards let's say technical sings about matter
more nasal but the software that same
guess probably the only
conference talk which is about the business
so you miss the oh okay that's
kind of a dirty subject and so
on and so forth but iracing that's
it said one of the quiche issues
which are dealing with that we've met
tomorrow which is about how to make
a community growing and and one kissing
abouts are making and community growing
of course are to get attention from
the outside and one let's say one
nixing witches out of getting attention is
how you can make a living out
of metal and wholesome individuals can make
it more like a business job opportunity
and then have good reasons to walk
on a day to day basis an
unmet tomorrow let's said how's it can
move from the trencher that there may
be not love into a job that
they love dealing with free software which
was my case of course when they
started as an entity
as i was mustang walking with proprietary
solution now such of course as the
one off of google but thanks to
the business opportunities i got i get
the possibility to switch from google analytics
solutions and others to have full activity
around national
and that's three what this conference is
about it's about my feedback about hoi
succeeded in developing business opportunities based on
matter more and as what what i
observed and ashamed about what was our
companies are doing what he talks and
what doesn't and that of course i
you as an individual all
your company can take an advantage from
and may be sancta this feedback helped
to develop more products and services based
on matt moore and and have as
well afterwards contribution to and multiple community
saw that myself or my name is
a whole naushad enough i'm a
digital marketing trainer about met one eight
since two thousand and ten back at
the time
is there more than a decade ago
matter more wasn't the software that it
is today so i have to say
that i've been probably one of the
pioneer oh that's an unnatural to weaken
the time in order to stop developed
the business on it i made the
choice of not developing an agency of
still staying
one business in order to nuts that
said be trapped into a system into
an environment in which i won't have
any control over my company anymore
i had the chance to what faith
looks about digital analytics to be honest
i wrote three about the google analytics
one about the google tag manager and
one about piwik p rica being one
of the first that they that they
published it unfortunately did not get the
attention that they expected back then and
the now
the attention that it was in two
thousand and eleven when i wrote it
wasn't the same as today i guess
the two they're probably if i was
asked to write it it would be
of course from a consequence and we'd
probably get far more attention than than
guts back then
i am associate professor in digital marketing
at yale atmosphere which is a university
in france i am professor since more
than a decade ago and i'm one
of the few met one analytics certified
professional when the certification was was still
on you can still find the certification
on the
project into time old ding and you
will have named for us not getting
screwed up come on which i got
the agreement from the matter martina to
get the list of questions and the
reason the certification program in order to
make it more like a free and
accessible program to everyone so you can
easily go on frost marketing
quill dot come and look at the
certification program and and insulting a different
question and gate to a certificate which
is issued by different marketing schooler dot
com which has not much valued but
which is us here here in order
to test your knowledge about metamorph matrimony
and yeah would you mention it in
the previous conference i walked for metamorph
or let's say the inner craft company
from july two thousand and seventeen to
july two thousand and nineteen
the purpose of this talk the following
one is to give you some feedback
about how to make a living from
that my antics will make a living
i mean like how you can make
your first euros out of it but
as well how you can fully live
on the on matter more it's dopey
lot of time in order to make
it technique
it took me about five years in
order to to make it but i
succeeded and of course i wasn't like
five years in which i wasn't walking
at all i got my first and
second player well of course making me
my main living and on my spare
time i was doing from here on
then some extra services of metamora which
give me some to trust in okay
the fifty there's some space in order
to bring something up that just to
let you know that i didn't jump
out into the lake straightway took me
up to five years in order to
feel confident enough to
there was enough markets in order to
provide met one eighty six
products and services but remember that it
was back then in two thousand and
ten when the market wasn't the one
which she is nowadays which is of
course far more flourishing
this talk is mainly for her one
man business that they call for themselves
here and the and agencies and this
is a business oriented talk so i'm
not going to talk about tacky stuff
or anything stylists would be more about
business in my business history is the
flying one i
of course business history means matter more
than that it exists three saw in
the two thousand and ten i got
my first client signed for training thanks
to a landing page so in fact
my history with
a few week back then and the
time when he started because i was
a su practitioner saw such an entity
myself and i was walking for web
agency which was providing
free software and website creation services so
to set a web agency which was
providing to the creation of website with
joomla technologies wordpress technologies at the time
it was named magento as web prestashop
and all that kind of free software
out there
no nudges and as let's say when
marketing specialist i just was a bit
curious that's okay we are all the
time creating all this website including google
analytics within those and i was wondering
will cap it
is there a nozzle technology on us
which may be a free software nuts
proprietary software that we can embed on
the website that we deliver in order
to be more let's say a privacy
compliant or in order to align with
the mission of what free software about
and this is where i discovered that
there was a technology which wasn't him
the week i added the time people
within the web agency which we are
passionate enough not to deploy a piwik
instance to say a several running p
weaken it and then because we had
the sovereignty because we were starting to
deliver some website with p we concluded
within it that they got the irish
because i was upswing charge of publishing
content on the web agency's website ok
why not just creating a landing page
in which i will announce that we
are delivering a training about pb kinetics
that all the time i didn't even
know about sorry just stuffed with a
bet that we judge
just sent in the lake in order
to say something which wasn't true i
have to say now
that's a real emergency and we deliver
trainings about matter what it takes
and i did that with several technologies
i did it with a w stats
i did it with the open web
analytics which for some time has been
a competitor offer of met one that
he takes up and one day the
phone rang and it was one of
the biggest company in france who was
on the phone we haven't really smaller
agency we're dealing with really like small
clients in in my own town so
and this french multinational company just caught
us and sell care we saw on
your page that you are delivering to
be reconnected to training we want you
on board we want you to
come in fairyland a false which is
like the biggest the business center in
france you're going this tower under the
fifth floor under the fifties floor and
you go and make the training while
i dunno for you guys for the
people who know what's up
met tomorrow looks like more than ten
years ago by twas while not like
the fanciest product to show on us
and the yet to deliver training about
it and the thing is that during
the training what was even funnier is
that we went we didn't have an
internet connection the training that i did
was probably probably
one of the worst that they will
develop but the thing is that ice
chest so much about it that i
have to train myself on the pi
week analytics documentation of the times when
people go talk that they get enough
you know they'll write a book about
it and then i went to a
publishing house
edition that's already walked with a nice
okay look or discontent material that can
make it boot camp out of it
and this is how the story starts
so i just out with it that
we will be client nick pressure big
contracts and then enough itself money not
enough to take a risk
sc which is about publishing the contents
that i
that's it that they wrote that they
made over my weekend's volume so this
is this is hoyt walks
then i got this book which of
course in the mind of people makes
you like a super style whereas i
have to said it's i didn't get
many scientists from around one thousand of
of of books i've been sorta dealing
with with pb kinetics and then what
i did from two thousand and twelve
to two thousand and four
ten and you know i was still
walking with proprietary solution and i was
still frustrated that the week was nuts
let's say getting that much attention so
i decided to create two websites in
order to attract some leads i started
to walk i gave some conferences here
and there it's hard
me make me more confident about talking
about the software i started tuning can
be more with the communities i've been
involved into a measure camp i dunno
tional measure comforts kind of the biggest
analytics community that you can find on
us i started to spread the world
about that measure camp and
i started twelve more leads dealing with
the with the time it wasn't in
the week and it was really making
me confident and it was worried the
kind of kids that they wanted like
the well will they'll seize the project
well very empowering and i want every
little that i got make
me as a more comfortable and what
do you make me realize that's appropriate
to establish an unjust to show you
in the forestry are not helping you
to educate yourself a bit though and
that free software is like offering you
far more possibilities in dem of learning
and education which which make them really
great
opportunities and in two thousand and fifteen
i set enough confident enough to say
okay what do i want to do
in my life and and this is
where i really saw that's the mission
of the free software and that two
thousand and six in particular already align
with what they want to do for
my should show and this is why
it's okay i'm gonna invest some money
in order to jaina to join an
accelerator and call it also need be
beta and although i have some mental
people who can tell me if my
project so to set to create food
company based on metro atlantic services
is reliable or not and it just
took me in fact the three months
while your high elder twin towns in
order to build up your website in
order to test some stuff around the
tombs around met them and so on
and so forth and in three months
that that was it in three months
i got enough contracts in order to
make it
one you are leaving and i said
well when they said one you're leaving
not talking about millions of shore here
i'm talking about the time two thousand
and fifteen i'm talking about limits of
seventy thousand to seventy five thousand euro
of tunnels though for women business guess
i'm not talking healed
doubts
high pay for some i'm re talking
about what is making enough for one
person to leave only on net to
more analytic services and a rich in
three months i got the contract for
twelve months lengths of thirty to thirty
five thousand euros after another i have
to say
today i prefer to disclose the information
right now that i'm making still as
a woman business seventy thousand euro yeah
i don't want to make more because
if i go more i'd definitely go
for limited company which is not the
thing that i want but they can
tell you that trading on the market
if you are good enough
if you should know how to be
a good sort of spell son if
you are ready to go international that's
the kissing most of my tongue avail
fifty sixty percent closely to sixty percent
of my tongue avila is not on
the national market which is france it's
on the international market
from two thousand and seventeen to two
thousand and nineteen i joined the ino
crushed him so let's say the first
of many to nail the first contributor
to the net two one eight x
project that has been probably one of
the greatest experience that i got in
my career i got menus but this
one
really helped me a lot this morning
we go to reach our stock we
gave a conference to which i husk
what it is to walk up in
crofton and really what you said line
with what are you and what they
said i haven't been filed by the
company because you can see here that
i left the company in two thousand
and
and nineteenth just that's
you know cost is based and use
it and so it's a twelve i
will time zone of delay and it
was very exhausting on both sides i
mean like attending the conference by nine
pm in
like ons or twice a week is
very dramatic in terms of family life
balance and they came to a point
of doing this for like two years
walking with twelve hours of delay as
a socal i cannot continue destroying my
familiar life and has it been the
same thing for them to dissuade decided
to stay
i'm probably more helpful
staying in europe had been from you
up developing the met to one eight
six community to expand rather than being
into crafting but they have to say
that those two years have been extraordinary
you know they'll understand
what is the responsibility of owning software
such as metal noise and the from
two thousand and nineteen to now this
is what i said here i succeed
to double my revenue so to say
seventy thousand euros and i'm now in
fact helping partners around the world to
as well make a living out
of metal
this is the list of the different
services that they identified for by which
you can make a living out of
have met them all and i'm not
providing one of them that they have
some partners while delivering them so i
can of course so couple of world
about it so first one is about
to a boston which is mostly why
what's the agencies are providing then you'd
get the consumed king but which is
probably where else as a ruler to
do which is about solving complex issues
by solving complex issues i mean the
measurement plan supports any issues and then
he takes things like
creating revolt and that kind of sing
training so training is ready to sing
that i'm i'm known for that i
liked the most to do but this
is a smart person or thing which
is about sharing knowledge about how to
use multiple than the first one that
identifies translation it
how did he have that happened to
me but that's possible to to do
it's about translating matter more and and
trust me is a lot to do
because it's a software which is evolving
a lot and the switches supporting like
almost forty two languages on us custom
development which is about how to create
something which does not
exist yet within metal and a six
one which is about writing documentation which
happen far more than we can we
can expect so little saw let's say
like six different services that they identify
and the idea to give you some
feedback about those so that you can
identify a little bit more about what
you could do
if she would like to expand your
set of services or if you would
like to sell and so he sees
based on the method that flip austin
and this is really what they said
most of the agencies are doing what
is great with web last thing is
that it brings content revenue so that
that's of course the most obvious thing
it's like
you did eva websites white nuts you
add to it
the possibility was well offer when you
sell your website to sell the weapon
at it's expected
it brings a lot of opportunity to
settlers of services and i'm quite amazed
to see that a lot of agencies
which shop or would you delivering website
we've met too including only about taking
this opportunity to sell more services on
top of it like consulting
because you don't truly need to be
like i mean you don't need to
have followed some unedited studies i mean
i did it myself but most of
the time when the client as an
issue seemed more of an issue with
nuts about understanding the data but which
is more about how the software is
walking how the us is walking which
means that's
emergency sinks that they cannot easily set
of consulting services because the things that
don't have the stuff tastes well as
definitely as it could because they have
a lot of different plans on which
to deploy matawan it so it means
that's the poverty they already have the
knowledge that they're unlikely and need but
it's just that they're on the fence
do not we know how to express
themself and not to say hey i
somehow saw racing that's why busting is
in fact one very good wish to
sell consulting services and the disadvantage of
web hosting is that's a skinning not
too moist far more complex
then it seems and that's probably the
issue that most of the plans that
i'm training
not realize that the just saying that's
tomorrow is like google analytics and that
totally forgot that's the ne twelve system
and you're straight on board and us
never know about us they never held
about what is a system indestructible because
when you use a google analytics solution
you don't have to care about this
stuff was i don't know that they
need to profit
fight them they don't know how complex
it can be to austin manage a
database which is growing deaf don't it
so this is relish the thing that
you need to take into consideration if
you provide web hosting is that if
your client does a lot of visit
is a lot of trouble not that
well despite his his way to bring
a lot of opportunity to settlers of
services is really now somewhat easier to
do than the met with chin as
developed a plugin specifically for wordpress which
means that in one click you can
already deploy wordpress without taking care of
the metal that amazing stuff
a nation which make it of course
very easy to do to one dollar
maximal project
and whereabouts thing is of course not
something that's one man business can easily
sell because you need different expect price
and that's most obvious flaw for agencies
and as i just said you need
to have the system administrator on board
all the time because if you have
complex installations to send installation with
she has a lot of traffic you
need to have someone body know that
i'm sure
the second service which is a consulting
up the pros of the flying one
is that it can bring you constant
traffic news if you can take care
of your clients that's the three part
which is important in considering it's not
really about just delivering the singer it's
also about ensuring that the fee
x the the superbug that you provided
help your clients to go fidel and
go to another issue of course and
you sure which will come by him
but it's really important here to keep
going on into contact with you with
your client if you want to have
this constant revenue sing okay
it cannot walk if your clients cannot
find a solution based on the date
of vegetable because you will see that
most of the time wednesday's assignments it
probably means that don't know it but
your client as an issue we've met
more probably a separate issue i'll probably
the end so that you give them
an
let's say i make some
he lost hope knew you and the
unnecessary silences on the good at all
okay so issue want to keep sending
consulting you have to ensure that your
clowns gun and self thanks to the
solution that you provided them is showing
good satisfaction and this is clearly what
is happening for maker
companies and as well my my toughness
is that you can solve the big
contracts what we could a big contracts
is like big clients and those clients
have a lot of needs dealing with
measurement plan and as a measurement kind
of very complex as it implies a
lot of different meetings
and let's say high expectations in terms
of project management this is where big
contracts are coming and this is where
you can start to save your company
this way you can save your yo
this is where you get the most
interesting project because it's highly motivating and
you can
really see that you have enough to
eat for the next two years and
those are what need to the biggest
the the bit for me the greatest
thing you'll do to stop to build
a business based on that to me
is rare to find disconcerting a project
which all very close to what we
sending in ninety kicks in general so
let's say measurement plan meetings helping the
company grow and learn in terms of
knowledge and also read the most important
thing and the disadvantage is that they
can be super complex so he'll this
is where you need to be very
careful because of
vegetables can be embedded into very complex
information system on which the expertize is
where you were young i was thinking
for example about the companies of institution
who are deploying for example
i met him on the microsoft checkpoint
and here in order to find out
the people well the expertise about microsoft
checkpoint while i was not that many
people are appropriate those people were very
buzzy so it's it's pretty it's pretty
hard because i'm not that much documentation
you need to test a lot then
through some places
she cannot embed the tracking code and
so on and so forth and of
course if your client is appointed it's
it's it's complicated project you'll get some
great have and so on and so
forth so this is where you need
to leave why didn't you fight before
starting the projects whole complex is going
to be
toy will have great concerns that they
will end with them
a client of mine
kitchen you buy on the on the
project that they didn't enough the sawai
fleece i recommend you to assist with
this conference in which i would explain
underway we decided to walk but just
which tunnel were studied your project before
a single yes of course this is
the walk of meetings that your new
prayer and
prior to starting the project in order
to see if you feel confident to
do it and yes sometime it's up
to get your money back it goes
back to the super complex project that
you can get off the wrong sub
contractor that you hire people who will
not make a measurement plan which is
really reliable
or as on some it happens a
lot longer your projects that's the people
that you get in contact with are
finally laid off or at least while
some are and some issues and then
your project starts too it's a tool
to texas to be late and this
is where you
get your money back early to declare
this where you wouldn't need to rely
on modem doesn't want clients in consulting
if you want to make a priority
training training is definitely the thing that
i love to do the most and
that i'm doing guess what the most
what are we like training is that
can bring you high revenue in the
short period of time there is a
lot of demand far more than what
we can expect because they of course
the people while searching for its days
as one piece
people who like twelve one that was
not yet express that they would like
to have one so it's one about
knowing who's using multiple and ones you
know it's it's really easy when you
get to niche market for the for
the educational market let's do the universities
when you know that there is this
one demand from one
guy on the day was that even
vestiges of all using metaphor it's kind
of easy to look at deals will
do and say hey lady where are
you interesting that training about maximum
and when you when they do the
training as an if i'm not well
setting up myself here kelly
and i'm getting a lot of consulting
demands i think he it swearing during
the kissing here is that when you
do the training just don't be the
guy was hitting on down to just
that he felt something and then run
away it's always good to to show
off corso with the
let's say hiding the name of the
game was a client but to show
who you are walking and and the
way you walk as a consultant is
very interesting because then you offering them
that or you have an organization and
what kind of services that you are
providing off your path and also providing
and then the philip
i'm very confident you can do as
well cross setting this is definitely what
i'm doing here with some of the
people who are about to move him
to death such as upon digital and
digital east eighty ivan met with jimmy
surface recommending premium features all and talking
about once pissed
cloud infrastructure and so on and so
forth that that's pretty something that you
can do and that in fact to
the attendees of their training out looking
for work so i'm not just interesting
enough training them so so interesting and
the possibilities that one can have with
the product and services and the coolness
of the training out is just
one shot revenue okay so most of
the time it's the case that the
company would take a training from you
unless it's a very big company will
take another one it's happened in some
case when the company is growing and
they get like new employees and the
one just no place to get trained
and know that you have done a
good job
time but most of the times the
elderly have come back for training
and thus this here the second comes
that they put here is more full
of our agencies most of the time
and agency will spend a lot of
time in training one specific complete nissan
for your bit special because he succeeded
or she succeeded in training and get
certified self and decided not to go
on it's own
and well then it's pretty hard to
find a resulted back someone who is
motivated so i think he'll issue all
emergency it's always good to secure this
resource by making a mistake or do
something i do because dismissals within your
company's way of hiring and just retinal
that
it takes a lot of time to
train a trainer
we've got an eight x five is
important in six months you can succeed
in in think a big enough trainer
in met tomorrow isn't enough to tell
a decade i seem to know everything
about metal so let's just to let
you know that it takes a lot
of time because it's sort of concept
it's not really about the solution in
itself which is complicated it's about time
just wondering what is the free software
philosophy what it implies and to not
be scared of the tricky part about
cellphone deploying something on the salvo ssh
all that kind of thing that's the
kind of thing you need to have
an interest in in order to understand
how the solution is walking because probably
that china will be as web domain
the man for audio different projects so
the guy talking with the devil lapels
with the unnoticed we have to sub
spell son with the system administrator with
the client and and that's where it's
takes a lot of time in order
to understand what the orgy expectation from
one enters
the force of is that i'm sinking
off his translation and i haven't yet
received any demand for money she ok
for that but i can clearly see
that the awesome demand because met always
evolving a lot with nuclear again and
those against it doesn't get translated sometimes
or at least not in some
specific languages which means that when you
are like a dick companies let's say
for example a company based in japan
and taiwan all even in in i
dunno in venezuela are in no way
just imagined that those guy when things
started to sprinkle the future again guts
you why if not tomorrow which is
a no region and then english or
japanese and then english so it's it's
like the two sided belsen and the
two sided coin in one and it
doesn't make sense so this is where
as i look at the soft grounds
it's ok
you recommended me to install the software
and it's not even fully translated so
you are just giving me like alpha
for software could you fix that and
this is where you can definitely find
people to to translated the translation service
which has been recently put on the
net too
always a very instinctive and hope you
in translating it straight away you saw
some plugins which are specific which allow
you to make some extra translation
so he i think that there is
a lot of business opportunities to sell
translation services for matt to move for
a year and customize just that i
never succeeded in sending one yet
custom development is one of the sexiest
selfies to to solve the problem he
is that's and it's very very very
long so the pros of it is
that's very exciting it's in the project
you can ready
and i will matter more the dickens
is that's why quick rails that are
lots of fixed bow ties and the
nlg in order to kickstart the project
here i'm not talking about woman business
an agency who traits do custom plugin
you deserve but small like nudge
since you're a one man business who
is chasing finding out the profile who
is about to cry the met to
move plugin
those developers exist that you can easily
find them under on the community i'm
thinking health peter i'm thinking off stiff
and i'm thinking of maybe lucas i
mean there's some people within the community
you can develop those plugin for you
is just that you would be like
demeter man in charge of listening to
your clay
lance writing the spec document and then
only get to the web developer and
what i found out within those custom
development project issues is that in my
case i'm walking lot with french institution
is a twenty walk with a french
institution is not
that easy to hire results from the
outside sorta sit outside of your own
countries of france which of course make
the process even more complicated and and
this is a yeah so you need
to find the right profile to ensure
that according to the law according to
the constraints without given to you by
your clients who can find a work
profile then you need to not screw
up when you write out the specs
document then you need to ensure that's
the spec of the client correspond to
what the developer is able to provide
because of the cough matt lawrence so
it's where
exciting project but it's pretty hard to
stop two tickets to get paid and
the something which could bite the developer
will be issued in three weeks will
probably take one year two years you
know that the you know they'll to
be dirty but also just to let
you know that custom devil
months he says one complex project
and last but not least a service
that i'm thinking of which is to
me as was very exciting which is
writing documentation and it happens quite a
lot i mostly by institution who do
not want to rely on the documentation
of madmen dot org which by the
way is
what well done but i want some
sandwiches more specific with swells with shell
different with spin shots which are using
that one day though we have probably
another language
that that'd be great this is how
you can develop your skills didn't river
with marketing materials as a sends us
a lot of demand it's just that
those demands are mostly coming from big
clients okay not not not small one
which of course make it more like
a like a niche project and the
only issue
that i can see here but which
is of course subject to discussion isn't
doesn't the licenses on which all writing
does the condition can be restrictive so
that's maybe you're not going to be
able to use those documentation that you
rightful and it said public project which
of course is a
it's a bit heartbreaking but that's i
mean that's that's part of the game
right you get money for and this
money that you get for you are
under restrictions most of the times though
cross license i guess makes stays that
i'm seeing on the field anyways businesses
is that you can't know everything as
a woman business you would have two
roundabouts of contracting ready at the beginning
i thought that i could be able
to endure all the power of maximal
i would just find out the
it's just too big that they cannot
be good in everything so you need
to have a network it's not like
tomorrow you can decide to create your
own business based on medical unit twelve
and a talk you need to have
guys who are good and board and
definitely those guy you can find him
and shut up multiple that one
because people are attending today or are
you really from yeah we've met one
antics and probably are familiar with it
you can find them as well i'm
from the metamorph dot org but it's
all about network i i cannot deliver
all the products and services that i'm
saying today if i don't have my
network
not always not on native that's biggest
mistake that most of the agencies i'm
doing suggesting that it's a crillon of
google analytics is the mission of net
html twelve like google antics as a
as a free software from that html
that's not at all something met to
me is a free software with this
it embrace the free of
philosophy which means that it's even if
people would correct me about it it's
a tricky solution and if it's a
turnkey solution you need to be at
least sticky order to understand the heart
of its heights walking and of course
how to set it off too
you have to understand the free software
philosophy and it's a huge piece
it's a long term return on investment
as i say it took me five
years in order to be able to
make a living out of it but
it's three was it
you cannot succeed if you don't love
the software that that's the sing don't
blame the software blame yourself if they
have some sandwiches not walking cause if
there's something that she's not walking probably
means that say something that you are
missing somewhere along the education of the
software
i how to promote your mat to
mobile services this is the list of
things that i'm doing which are walking
that all together it's not just one
single writing books to tell your publishing
marketing materials or education that toyota is
walking you have about five hundred videos
running on the internet than any treaty
help
keyboard on that coming straight to west
thanks to those video it happened some
time but it's making you visible which
is the most important thing that people
can put a face on on your
name and then they can relate to
you if you have any question as
a website of several website introducing your
services i have about
close to three hundred websites talking about
what i'm doing which helped alot give
tours and conferences share with the community
a network and then create your own
network that's one of the reason why
i was interesting in setting up these
met him at cam that was about
opening old
the possibilities of connecting with other people
or finding people that they can make
and that they can be subcontractors of
my project so you have too many
demands though if i can do something
all is well potential clients it's wonderful
that that's the way it was mentioning
to your existing clients do not forget
to always be on social networks connect
with those clients of yours and tell
them about the changes which will come
much more recently and involve yourself with
free software projects that is what very
important to understand the face of trust
she does have
and that's it for this conference i
would hope that you enjoy it and
that you have plenty of questions
what kind of gas while i guess
so
we don't have any any questions for
this talk i hope everything was clear
thank you on small for choosing this
conference and hopes you are well if
you can get a great mentor welcome
thank you