Yes, wonderful. I would have simply said, we are starting now, yes, from my side
also first of all welcome to Matomo Camp. This is the first Matomo Camp that we
also organize and I have, in addition to the fact that Lukas has organized almost everything, of course
, the honor of holding my own lecture here. We have decided in advance
that we also want to record this workshop. This should mean, for example, if you have
a video on or if you decide to say something or say something,
then that is not forbidden. But you should just think that we record it.
We actually planned it in such a way that we, so to speak, I now do the presentation
first. We just put the questions back a bit. We now have the advantage in this
workshop that we have the time until, so to speak, 11.45 a.m. and that there is now also the
lunch break afterwards. That means that if we can then ask questions afterwards,
then that is not so problematic, because you would not miss any other sessions and so on
. Maybe you would lose a little one or two minutes of the lunch break or something.
So that's why, as I said, welcome again from my side at this point.
My lecture today is just how to use Matomo correctly for SEO. That means, how can I
combine these two systems or how can I best combine them together to
get numbers out of Matomo that are very helpful for the search engine optimization.
And briefly to my person, my name is Thomas Zeithammel. I have actually been working in online
marketing in the field of SEO since 2001. At that time we did not even know that it was called SEO.
I have been there for so long, an old rabbit. I have already been through a lot and have
various customers from different areas, which of course also come from Google Analytics
and have also already worked with Matomo. And since 2009, simply out of private interest,
with my own websites, I looked around for software and at that time
I became aware of Pepeg. And yes, I have been familiar with the system for 12 years now,
give training, offer consulting and so on. And I would like to talk about the topic today,
what we can really combine in SEO and Matomo. The most important thing for me is
actually to really interpret the numbers correctly. And it is the case that we first of all
pick up a lot of numbers that we are actually more or less interested in.
So a value such as IP address, website title, for example the screen resolution,
with which language the browser works and so on. All these values are all
investigated and collected via the data layer or whatever, whether with a tech manager or whatever.
We now have all these dimensions on board in Matomo and can then of course
evaluate them. The question is, can I start something with the IP address,
which is anonymized, can I use it for SEO? Not really. That means I have to pick out here
which numbers are particularly important for SEO. And there I just picked out 10
where I said that is really something where you should always keep an eye on it.
On the one hand, of course, the search terms that you, for example, got from Google
and so on. In the end, the search terms are unfortunately no longer completely visible,
but there is a way in which I will then help you to unravel these search terms again.
The second is a very important number, for example the period of time. This is also underestimated very,
very often. But for SEO it is of course very, very important to see if I can do it with
my content, with my page, in the end, to keep the visitors on my page for a long time.
And that results again with the jump rate. If I see that, oh, it's very high.
That also means again for Google, of course, I may have a return to search
quota, a very high one, which sends a signal to Google that perhaps the content is not so good
or does not fit the search phrase. So that can also be important for SEO, so to speak,
and we have that here in the system. Webvitals, of course, the classic now of the last six,
seven months. Everyone who deals with SEO is just talking about these terms,
such as webvitals and the topic performance loading time. That has been very high in the last two,
three years, which of course also gives Matomo a very, very good plug-in
or opportunities to raise these numbers. Entry pages, classic, yes, certainly,
very, very important for the field of SEO, as well as the visitor sources. So not to see
where the visitors really come from, not just to focus on the zoom machine,
but perhaps also to look at the references. Technical aspects. Where do I have maybe 404
errors on my page? Where are there server errors? It may also be that this can of course be determined
by tracking or, in the end, by crawling tools. But here I have the
opportunity to say right away, wait a minute, so many have really called up. Of course,
such a dead link is always bad, but if I see in the web analysis that it has
never been called up in any way, then it's not that bad either. Then I don't have to
worry too much about it. While I, when I see that in another statistic, that a page
that sends 404 has been called up a few times, maybe even a day, then I have to react faster
and can also evaluate the internal search. Very important for the editorial team,
for example. Also this number, whether an article has been read or not,
I can somehow summarize in Matomo or have it issued. And of course the whole
topic of conversion tracking. These are the most important numbers that you will certainly have
in the SEO as points of contact with Matomo. I'm going to take out a few things now,
such as the delay and the delay. Because that has always been the topic of Google in recent years,
although they introduced a panda update back then in 2012, so it's been a little longer again.
But what happened is that the delay and the jump rate of Google can also be
raised. So Google has this data available and can integrate it into their user signals
and let these user signals flow into their algorithm. And you just need a few
points that you have to consider here in these two numbers, delay and jump rate.
And there I just set up six points that make it a little easier for me to
explain the connections. On the one hand, if I have a jump rate of 100 percent, then in Matomo
there is also a value of 0.0 seconds for these pages. That means if there is a jump rate,
so a jump is sent, then I don't have any delay in this session.
This is related to how the delay is calculated. And here it is the case that the last page,
i.e. the exit page, is not included in the visit as time. That means I always have
the last page of the visit with a value of 0.000 seconds delay. So unfortunately the exit page
always sends no signals as to how long you have been on this page. Because in Matomo, like other
systems, so also like Google Analytics, the distance between page 1 call and page
2 call is always counted together. And just as in the delay, with the jump rate,
then I have the entry page, then the exit page. This is how the jump rate is defined.
And then of course, because the exit page has no value, I have this value of zero here.
That means you have to understand these two metrics first of all, why sometimes
the exact value is not in there that you might expect. But of course you don't always have
a jump rate of 100%, but just less. And then of course there are users
who also send values here. So high jump rates are always a recommendation of mine
to take a look at such pages in the page analysis and say, wow, there may be
technical errors. We already had cases where a consent banner was delivered over the page,
but they were not so well integrated on the mobile device that the people simply
couldn't click these buttons anymore. So there was no way to accept, because it was too far
to the right outside of the screen and you couldn't scroll. And then of course we see,
ha, wobala, in the mobile area the jump rate is very, very high and not so high in the desktop area.
So you can also detect and detect errors. So such a high jump rate can
definitely be looked at. But a high jump rate does not mean that the page is
very, very bad, but a high jump rate in connection with a period of time
makes sense. Because the period of time is very high, I don't really care about the jump rate
in the end. Because it can also mean that the user has come to the page,
has been busy with the content for a long time, has read it completely and was then simply
more satisfied and then left the page because of that. Not because he was dissatisfied.
So that means just going to the jump rate is not so ideal here. The same is true
if I have a high period of time and a low jump rate, that is also a positive
value actually. Because the users have read the article, that's why this high period of time
and went on. I can see that from the fact that the jump rate is then just low. That
means I was able to keep the visitors on the page and maybe
navigate them better through the website through similar articles in e-commerce or through related topics
again on a news page or something. Or I have blog posts that I wrote about
and they are also interesting for the reader. So that is of course something that is very, very good,
which is actually the ideal step 5 here or this point 5. But of course there is also a
low period of time and a very high jump rate. That is always such a sign that you
may have been dissatisfied as a user. So, in general, you can't say that either. Just think of
the industry books. Industry books, I'll give you one, Dachdecker, Augsburg, I'll get to a page,
I'll quickly write down the phone number, I'll be on the page again. That means I don't spend
much time reading the content or something, but I just need to
contact you somehow quickly. I'll get the information out of it very briefly,
have seen everything. Also, if I enter which pre-election number the 0421 belongs to or something,
then I just give it to pre-election 0421. Then I come to a page, look at me, ah,
that's the one and the city, then I'm gone again. So please don't
always be so partial. And just when you say that, yes, I have to understand the characteristics,
then please also understand that detractors always play a big role here. I have
set up such a small screen at the bottom, where you can see that these average values,
which are unfortunately excluded in Matomo, which cannot influence either, that they can of course
also be influenced by certain pages. At the bottom of the screen, so I have different
pages, page 1, 2, 3 and so on, and this page 5 is so popular. If page 5 now has a super
deflection rate of maybe only 20 percent, but all the other pages are with a
deflection rate of 80 percent or something, then my average value, because the one page
here, the 5, is so good, would give me a little bit of a good feeling that the
deflection rate here is not a problem at all in this domain. So that means that these
statistic values ​​please always look at each other separately, really go into the data
, really break down and take a deeper look. So in the average values is often
simply something covered up, which you can see more when you go into the details. Especially when you
have pages that dominate very, very much. These can be, for example, pages like the starting page,
which of course always serves as an entry for many pages in the e-commerce area, which then
always sends positive signals, but maybe the product details at the back send all bad
signals. Then I should just look at them separately from each other. And of course the
segments help me very, very well. So in Matomo I have the opportunity to create these segments
among all these visitors. The problem is that they are more or less not given by Matomo,
but that I have to create them myself. That is always the first thing I do when I
go to a website with a customer or so on, to create these segments here so that the
users can then also compare these segments, i.e. the customers. And there I always recommend
at least to divide the channels so that I really have the channel direct, the channel campaigns,
the channel search engines, the channel maybe also references and also the desktop or mobile types,
i.e. what is available to us as a device type as a dimension in Matomo. Then I can
compare how the user behaves in mobile versus the user in the desktop area. Or just
make the comparison of how people who come from search engines behave versus people who,
for example, come via Google Ads, via campaigns or via direct entries. Because they
behave completely differently. And I would like to identify more precisely in the SEO,
how it is and how it works, for example. And then these values, such as exit rates or
or departure rates or also for a while, or side views and so on,
these will become much clearer. That first of all to pre-tension, yes, to understand that
these values ​​also have to be interpreted correctly. Otherwise it won't help me for my SEO
in the end. The second thing I would like to address is the data collection.
It should mean how I can simply evaluate or improve the values ​​that I measure.
And here the classic, the events. I still have the case very often that events have
not yet been set up. And now with the Tag Manager, for example, it is so easy to
set up these events. Of course, you need a bit of knowledge, perhaps from the HTML,
to recognize that this is the CSS class, the button is called ID and so on. Or here is the
link text. What is a link text? Of course, you do need a bit of foresight, but it is a
very nice opportunity to transfer these events, what happens on the page,
and so on, to Matomo. And with that the data will be better again. And then maybe
set up as goals. And there you can also distinguish two topics. On the one hand, my technical
problems that I may have on the page. That means I solve events if, for example,
a page of errors arises or is called up. Zack, same event,
Amatomo, Zack, page 404. The same also with a 500 error, if my server is not currently
reachable or something and I still deliver the error message or the error page,
or if the URL was just built up like that because someone from the forum has mistakenly linked it to our
website. Then I can also send these errors to the web analyzer right away.
And the same, of course, also on the page level, if I have certain topics there. For example,
if I notice that an article has been sold out. Here, Zack, please send to Matomo right away. Because I can
then make evaluations about it later and can say how many people have run into articles. I have
1000 visitors. And of the 1000 visitors, how many have run into articles that were really
sold out? What do I do with it? Do I let them run like that? Because they might come back.
So I can then think about my viewing measures more carefully. Or the
no search results. I also had an e-commerce shop myself and there I also found out
in the search what people enter. There is also this Google zeitgeist, where at the end of the year
always comes out what people are looking for wrong with Google, i.e. where the writing is wrong. There is
a word like couch, for example, always in the top ten, where I think to myself, oh, couch is
actually not that difficult. But that is one of the most common wrongly written words. If you
are now a furniture seller and then also notice, wait a minute, people enter couch
wrongly written and I have no search results, then this event can help you
point out that somehow these hits are not there. It is also very often simply not
set up. And I just went from bottom to top a bit, the page read topic.
So that is also something that you can then set up something similar to scroll depth very, very nicely
via the tag manager. Of course also manually. But in the end it's really about
really taking something like a scroll depth in here. We have the case very often,
you have a page, the people are on it, you have a period of time, but you actually don't know
when such an article will be finished. And that's what this content tracking format
is very valuable for. Because with it, for example, I have such blocks that are close to the footer,
you can also do it directly over the footer. But if I have such elements
above the footer, such as these social bookmarks or share links or something, then I can
just say that if that appears in the area of ​​the visible in the browser, then it has
dealt intensively with such an article somewhere and read through it. There are very few people
who really scroll down completely at the end, go up again and then start reading.
But the people already proceed in such a way that they scroll down one or two times, but do not scroll down the whole
article. And so I can see a little bit when I say when the footer is
displayed, then I know, ah okay, this article has at least been read. These two
numbers, pages, views and pages read, I'll call them pages read, I can then
see again in direct relation and say, okay, then I really have a problem here at this point
because I have a thousand views on the page, less than 20 at some point
have seen the footer. So I can grab these numbers a little better again and
especially then also locate in my editorial office and say, now look here,
we just have a more accurate evaluation now. And this scroll depth can be used in the
tag manager then also by percentage, which is of course much more
convincing. And of course please use your own dimensions, because that is
the most valuable thing that I can actually integrate into the evaluations. I can
take something like the release date, for example, or just the article type with
article type or also page types, I mean, is it a product part page, is it an overview,
is it the start page, is it the search page, are there topic pages, text pages, whatever,
I can transfer what I want. And these own dimensions are just
super suitable for this, as well as to include product categories and say, this is the
overridden product category, for example, this is food, this is fashion, this is that,
because later on in my conversions, for example, I can also divide it up more precisely,
or I can just say, aha, okay, our conversion in the field, for example, fashion is higher
than the conversion in the field of food or something, yes, or in other topics. You have
comparability through this. You can also include indexing, if you say you have
many pages on noindex, that is, these are pages that are excluded for Google,
but are still on the website, yes, I'm thinking, for example, of certain categories,
page pages and so on. Then I can also transfer these indexing values to Matomo and say,
okay, here, then I can see how much traffic I still have on my noindex page.
Then I can possibly think, oh, maybe with a little text enrichment I can
still put it from noindex to index, or, or, or. These are the points that you can
easily deduce. Or just the number of words, yes, that just makes sense in rounds,
so 50 or 100 words in rounds, but then you can see how the duration also behaves,
how the deviation rates also behave. And where I can see exactly, with all texts
that were below 100 words, the deviation rate was just very, very high, or just very low,
because maybe the information I have is already enough. So to transfer these values to Matomo,
also structured data, yes, filter, yes, if I have a shop, that also makes sense
to transfer to Matomo. Because to take everything in again and think about how
I can deduce measures and proportions from my numbers, that is what is
important for you in the end and then, to make decisions. What do we do with it?
Do we link this category more often? Do we put more text on it? Do we look at
technical problems? How do we get this done? Quite classic now maybe the loading time optimization,
if I just know that, for example, on the article type product page, the deviation rates are
higher and the delay is lower, then I can just see how the measurement data for the
WebVitals are. And if they are significantly worse than on the overview pages, then I can go there,
then I go there first and optimize there. So I can use the segments, the dimensions,
I can also use the segments, just get in here much, much better and check it out.
And also this search term is not defined, which means what the visitors came up with
on Google. Yes, Google was blocked back then, they said in 2014, because of the NSA affair,
because of our HTTPS encryption, we no longer transfer these search terms. But
the funny thing is, there is the Google Search Console that offers this data again. And here
there is a very simple plug-in from Matomo, although it is mandatory, but that is really one of the
must-have plug-ins that I need for the SEO area, because that brings me back these data
into Matomo. And that's the nice thing, because I have my segments here, I have everything
in the area of ​​conversions and so on running together. That means in the Google Search Console you can
also say, yes, I have the data there. But because I connect it to Matomo, it does
that much better, because then I can also see which conversions are responsible for which keywords,
for example. So this combination of this data again with my dimensions,
with my segments, with mobile versus desktop and all these topics, I can now
evaluate them much better here in Matomo and sort them out. That means
all the filter functions, everything I have associated with it, is just much, much better
for me. So for me a must-have. But you can also look at the functionality. I
also included it as a link at the bottom. You are welcome to go to the Matomo Cloud, there is a demo version
where this plug-in is also installed. Then you can see, aha, is there anything suitable for me or not.
That means you can definitely take a look at that. That's as far as what I should definitely
mention in terms of data points, i.e. events, content tracking and of course these search terms
and dimensions. These are the four topics that in any case, if you don't have that yet and
really want to evaluate it better in SEO, then you need these four measuring points
in addition. And now just a few more tips, so to speak, on improvement. And it's
about me just explaining a few things to you again, what you can do or how you
could really approach that. So in the field of SEO you are always looking for
these topics. So I already mentioned earlier, yes, especially this Panda update or
other updates that always target the same thing, namely where I have
thin content on my domain, bad content, little text, maybe and so on and so forth.
There are a lot of really cool SEO tools that can help there too, but the most important
metrics for these recognitions are always rather to be found in Matomo or in the web analysis.
And there you just have to look at two real values. I've already said that one
is in the end the jump rate. Please note here that this jump rate always refers to
the entries and not to the side views. This means that this 90 percent does not refer here
in the first line to this 31, but you really have to jump into the table where
the entries are also included. But that tells me here now, 90 percent of all people
who have arrived at this bottom page or even these 97 percent of these users who have arrived
here on the page, 97 percent of them are gone again, so really very, very many.
I can definitely take a look at that, but also in relation to the pass rate.
There I only see one second, so all the people jumped off and there was only one second
on it and there only three seconds. So in general there is a very, very low pass rate on the page,
which means that I can take a look at all of these pages. And then you often come up with
this problem of the jump rate that refers to the entry pages. You have to jump back and forth a bit
and also jump back and forth to the entry pages here in order to
show this jump rate in more detail. So here I also have 34 entries and
also 34 jumps, so 100 percent. So it does not refer to 90 or 100 page views,
but really only to these entries. And then you will find pages like this, for example
here on the example of the yellow pages where I have entered something, Matomo under Meitingen. Then
down here, dear users, there is unfortunately no hit in this radius for your search term. I have
a radius of 50 kilometers here, so I am the only one in 50 kilometers who seems to be dealing with the topic
and still have not been introduced. Of course, this is a very bad experience for users.
You will not say, okay, I'll stay on this page for five minutes now and take a
closer look at everything again, but either, of course, I enter something else at the top or
I turn my back on the page and then immediately go away and look for the second result.
So search in search is always difficult anyway, people usually go back to Google.
Or there are also pages where I notice that the button for buying is faded out, this product
may no longer exist. Yes, then of course I am quickly away from this page, because I
might have wanted to buy this now and it just doesn't exist anymore. Then I go back
and maybe look for someone else. Especially with Amazon it is the page, for example, buying PS5,
which is causing quite a bit of despair, because of course there is no PS5 to buy.
And you keep coming back to the page, but you see that I can't buy it at all,
then everyone is gone. And they don't read much more, because they were
already there five or six times. That's why for this page they also have a bad
jump rate and a low pass rate, that always pulls everything down a bit. Just
as a practical example. And now my tips on how to interpret these numbers correctly.
You have this little gear symbol when you scroll down within this evaluation page,
where you don't have these data in this grouping where they have the folder structure at the front,
in this hierarchical order, but you can also display these data flatly.
I always find that nicer, because then you can sort it out nicely with this flat representation,
where all web addresses are really listed on top of each other, without, pardon me,
groups. And then you can just say, for example, I sort after a
pass rate, I sort after a jump rate. So the clarity is just much, much better here.
A note, of course, that you always had to look at it differently from case to case.
That means that what I'm giving you here as tips is not entangled in stone,
because again, the industry books have different conditions, so it's different there.
The same goes for other pages, types, it always depends on it. But if you just want to say,
and I want to do that here, because I have very good experience in the field of SEO,
which pages should you look at, then everything that is over 70% in the jump rate,
yes, don't just throw it away blindly and say, oh, that's probably all crap,
but definitely look at it more closely. And just look at it, if I have 70% and higher,
where is the delay perhaps under 15 seconds? Why 15 seconds? Such a page always needs
time until it is there, until you orientate a bit. The structure is always top left, the logo
at the top right, maybe the goods basket. If you have a large navigation at the top, a search field,
then somehow there might be a text again. I don't even know yet, I have to
find my way around a bit. If it's a product overview page, then I scroll through it first
and look, ah, these are products that are exhausting me. That means this time to find my way around
at all, without me starting and reading text or thinking about it,
I always need between 7 and 10 seconds. That's why everything that is under 15 seconds was a
quick decision that doesn't fit for me. Let me just differentiate again. Of course,
if you only have a photo series with one picture on it, then that's faster than 15 seconds,
which of course doesn't mean, yes, always on your own, on your own body,
maybe play through it, make a fool of yourself, go to the page, say, okay, how long do I need
now, if I would now deal with this page for the first time. And these pages
also scroll up so much that you always have at least 50 pages of impressions or more.
So that means you can control that via the date at the top, that you say, yes, I don't just want
one day now, but the week, or if the week doesn't work out, then rather a month,
because of the statistics, I can't just make better equipment. The
Heinzberg study back then with Corona, yes, where they tested 500 and I think 700 people there,
said, well, that's how it has to be with 82 million Germans, I don't think anything of it as a statistician.
So then rather say, I just need more values, with more values I have a more reasonable
statement of strength, which brings these topics together, like delay and drop rate. And
through more data, I also smooth out these average values. Because so outliers that were then once a day
or something, I just smooth them out with it and through more data. And these pages,
as I said, please take a look in the browser to be able to understand the behavior,
to see, was that understandable, so why, okay, the users got the information here
, if they wanted to, then here is a drop rate, a high drop rate, not at all
surprising, yes. Yes, tip number two was already a topic earlier, so of course the
internet search is often not taken care of. You actually have to enter these parameters
at the bottom of many systems only under manage settings, which you then also use for the search yourself
. Or then maybe also send this information via Javascript,
also in the tech manager, please set it up, that is often the case, even if it is not present in the system
or something, you can also do it relatively easily, because it just brings a lot of great results
for your own evaluation. On the one hand, the top searches always give hints on what
are the topics in question. And people always search when the pages are not so easy to reach for
them, because they say, oh, the menu control is very complex or hoppala, I don't know
exactly how I get there, is that now in this category or there, there may be no
brand overviews, I know, but I'm looking for the product of the brand, so they are very, very
fast because they just say, oh, that seems very complex to me and I want to get to my goal
very quickly, that's why this search is also used. Normally, in the field of e-commerce or
other areas, 5 to 15 percent is now on average. Of course, that can also differ
from page to page and of course it also depends on the integration. Something like the yellow pages or other
industry publishers, yes, they have a focus on the fact that people are also looking there, that the
search is very prominent. Think of Amazon too, the search field is very prominent up there
, no one is hanging around because of these 40,000 categories that Amazon offers there.
But it is always a good indication of what people are really looking for. Please also pay attention to
large and small writing points here. We also have that very often, for example, that jackets
in large writing and jackets in small writing have two numbers in this statistic.
That makes it more difficult to evaluate again and also discover many new editorial topics,
write mistakes, I already mentioned that earlier, and also measure these zero hit results.
You can either see that in this search overview here or you send it out
as I suggested earlier. Tip number three, which pages should I
optimize? I say that very often because that is also an important aspect in SEO.
Yes, our shop may have 50,000 products. I can't optimize 50,000 products. No, but I
have the product sales data in Matomo. I know exactly how many purchases or how many
purchases have been made about it and what amount was also in the warehouse. So I have this information.
I just called it here small 1 to small 10 and counted some numbers with it.
But what I see again and again in the evaluations is that if I pull out the top 25 products here
and therefore this segment product pages and so on and also in the e-commerce area these
product SKUs and so on, then I immediately see which 25 products make the most
sales for me. And I have pages that make up 70 percent, the average is then more like 30 percent,
but of course these are the pages that I should optimize. That means I go through the top 25 here
and look at page 2, page 3, page 4. What can I do much better on these pages?
That's just, the effort can then scale. When I have the 25 products ready, I go to the
next ones. So I don't go and say 50,000, we need 50,000 new product texts now,
but first I need 25 new product texts. And if they work and if they work to some extent,
then I go to the next ones. But first of all, I always take out the most profitable names
and optimize them. Because the probability that I now have a product at the bottom that
is perhaps a storekeeper, that I make a bestseller out of it, is rather low. So look there,
what is in the internal search, is also searched often. You can
put these numbers nicely together and say, okay, it is searched often, these are one of our
most popular categories, I can see that from the page evaluation and I go to these products.
Tip number 4 is the visitor flow. We already have this transition in Matomo,
where you can see what are the predecessors and successors, more about that in a moment,
but there is also a very nice plug-in that is unfortunately also free of charge,
but also saves me work. That's why I'm always such a friend of such plug-ins,
which then save me a lot of work, where I don't sit in the evaluation for four hours,
but have understood in two minutes what is going on. For me it is always an argument
why you can say, okay, then I really go there. And as I said, I have good connections
for Matomo, but I also had to buy these plug-ins, but I also use them
often. And this user flow is a complete view of the entire domain, how the visitors
behave on my site now. And there I also see patterns again and again, that, for example,
people who go through the site and at the end of the visit, for whatever reason,
they go back to the start page, for example. So now I can think about where I want my
users to go and integrate that into this whole workflow. This
behavior flow. I have a few metrics in my hand right now that I have now simply visually
prepared better. On the one hand, I see dikes on the basis of my jump rates, which are
these red bars, where I simply lose visitors massively. If I already lose a lot of visitors
on the first page, then there is simply little left out of the back that then navigates
further through the page. What I can also do is show these details to me,
what kind of pages are in there, for example, and how many exits or further leading
visitors there are. That means I can really navigate through here in detail
and look at these paths and analyze them. That means looking at the top paths,
where the visitors go further and what they do there. That is very, very nice about this module
and very quickly and beautifully visualized by this plugin. I also have such evaluations
under it, where I immediately see this top path, where I see that the people who
all somehow get on the website analysis and then go back to the website
analysis. They just press F5 or take something through at some point. Or that the people
arrive at my web analysis page and then go to the start page. So I see
such elements now. As I said, my page is not that prominent now. I now
put relatively little focus on it, but it's not the best page either, I have to admit.
But of course it is also important for me when I say how my services are,
how things are. With a larger page, of course, it is much more interesting. Do I get the people
there? When do they start looking for it? And you can see that very nicely in these
top navigations. And of course also here, which is very nicely depicted in this user flow,
but I often want to take a deeper look at it, these transitions are then
under behavior. This is both in the menu as well as if you have the pages
displayed flat or if you are here on the URL level. So I only call it blue links.
Yes, then you have it available right when you drive over this field with the mouse.
That's just this nice butterfly graphic that just tells me where the people
came from on the clicked page. So I see here, I have 256 page impressions,
of which 50 came from internal and so on and so forth. Yes, and 195 from search engines.
So these are the predecessors of the internal pages. And I see, and that's just what is
next. What is it, so to speak, what happens next? Where are you going? And here just for a page
that has to do with crafts. And so I immediately see if someone was on the craftsman's side,
where is he going? And I can already see hoppala, these are just building instructions, very popular.
So if I go over this page, then people want to jump into these building instructions.
So, and now we come to SEO aspects where I just say, that's why it makes no sense to present a
fly-out menu on many pages. Better a menu where I can see where I am right now and where
I am right now. This is again and again where I have to discuss this with many customers,
because someone who is in ladies' fashion does not buy a furniture cabinet wall now.
He doesn't. But he is in his ladies' world or she is in his ladies' world and looks at things there.
If I'm wearing evening dresses, they bring you to the left, maybe blouses or jackets,
even further. But they don't jump back and forth like that. You can see that very well with Zalando.
They have three theme worlds at the top, ladies, gentlemen and children. And if you go into gentlemen,
then you no longer see a menu. You have no way of getting to the ladies' skirt,
which doesn't make any sense at all. And you can do that here, if you show this statistic.
First make it really clear to many. Look, you have so much, you have 200 links on the page,
but the relevant ones are these top 5, for example. And these are all themes near pages.
That means that no one clicks across somehow and the reach of the menu does not have to go down
to every third level so that I have 600 links at the top of the menu because I have such a large
product range. Or in the news publisher of the newspaper publisher, who then says,
yes, we have 84 places in the region and of course they should all be reachable. Yes,
but if the places are then really far apart in the region and you just say,
yes, here from north to south it is somehow 180 kilometers, then no one looks at that anymore.
So whoever is sitting at the very bottom doesn't look at the content at the top anymore, geographically speaking.
So please always evaluate that. Unfortunately, only these top 5 here, I think that's a bit of a shame.
I would also like, maybe for Lukas, you can, you can also listen, hopefully,
that you could just expand into these transitions again somehow, so that you
don't just see 5. User flow. As I said, for me it is always a very, very important topic,
because I can derive so much from it. So because I want the people, the visitors
of my website, the users, to come to my target pages, where I want them to be,
namely on the product pages, maybe in the shop, or on the overview pages,
on my news portals or whatever. I see how the user navigates,
that is what is also asked very often. Yes, how is the behavior on the page?
I can see that from this predecessor, successor. And when does the user start searching?
I can see that from there. And from that I can, in turn, derive measures for SEO. How can I
improve my menu structure and how can I improve the internal links?
So that is of course a very, very important aspect, always in here. Tip number 5,
the performance. It's nice that you know TUMO, yes, and I just see a great distribution here in the end
. You say, okay, everything looks like this, yes, it's at least the same. You
have one or two days here and a few outliers, but please, at this point, the page load time,
that's something that Google also sees very, very quickly. And there are currently,
in my opinion, too many error lines in this evaluation of TUMO. Because I just,
depending on where, for example, I put the TUMO script in and maybe
also load scripts beforehand and then reload TUMO only later. Because if that's with the
tech manager, it might be different, but with the normal one, it just always needs that.
That's why I always have a bit of a problem with measuring there. And also there,
often seen after the module is still very, very new, also available since version 4,
that I sometimes just see that there are still bugs in the preparation.
That's why my tip at this point, if you go in, for example, and say you want to take the
right loading time, then we take such tools as WebPageTest or Google PageSpeed,
because they set the standard. That means, if I check that today, if I check that tomorrow, I
always check it under the same conditions. In other words, the device behind it that
captures the loading time, that's still with the same configuration. Here in this
performance, you would actually have to filter it out now and say, for mobile devices and
maybe sort out different brands there, what is the loading time there, how is it on the
desktop. I would really have to go in here again and see where my problems actually hang.
And these two tools are really to be recommended. Nevertheless, of course, there is also the
topic of WebVirtuals, where I can quickly get these data into Matomo. And there are two
plugins that I would recommend to you. One is the Performance Auto Plugin. That is free,
is a bit tricky to install, I honestly write that too, because you need
Node.js here, because Node.js has to run on the server to calculate these values yourself and
then also to record for the pages. That means, a script runs through every night,
which then performs this calculation. The values that come out of it are very, very good.
So that also corresponds to what the other tools actually offer in this regard.
Plus, as I said, it's a bit tricky to install. But if you can do that,
then you have all these values. And on the other hand, there is a cost-effective one from
InnoCraft, i.e. from Matomo itself. That is cost-effective, yes, but at this point it is
simply, let's say, easier to integrate into this whole topic. The data
investigation is a bit different at this point. Here the API is pulled from Google.
That's nice and good, but not necessarily the super cool effect on very large pages.
Because you only have a certain number of API credits at Google and I think they go up to
10,000. So if you have a page where you say 15,000-20,000 sub-pages and I would like to have it for every page,
then this is not the point. Both tools, however, in the end show similar metrics.
They tell me exactly what is going on on my page, so to speak, in relation to these web
websites, bad, CLS, LCP, these values, also the overview average, which Google or in the end
which score is achieved there. You can see that in both tools. So it's about tip 6, the last tip,
so to speak, to identify the bad link givers. So bad link givers are of course
also pages that may bring me visitors, but then also send bad signals on my
page. And you should just take a look at the source. And you have
these actions here on average, how many actions there were. And if I have sources
in it, where I notice, for example, that visitors are coming, but unfortunately I get a very high
jump rate here. And the pass rate is also very, very low for the visitors. Then I can
read these out here right away and show them to me. And then see, also in the segmentation log,
which is also a very good overview. If you then drive over these links here, then you get
them already shown. Where did they arrive? And then see, okay, can I maybe write down the link giver
and say, look, this content there, it doesn't somehow fit with yours, what you
have linked. Can you maybe adjust that again? Maybe I could optimize it that way. Or I
can also think about it, because there are also many spam portals or referer spam at this
point, which can then also be filtered out or blocked out. So I can get a little bit of
a grip on that. And again, the best links are of course also the ones that bring visitors to me,
so to speak, count here as backlinks. I can then also take a look at them and
also derive measures from them for SEO. As I said, that's actually it, unfortunately
already at the end. I just explained that again as a summary of two minutes. That means
always see the jump rate and expiration date in context. I think that's very, very important,
especially to track sync content. The data layers, the data information that I have,
should be enriched with different custom dimensions, with events, for example,
to be able to filter better here and to see the data better. Use segments intensively,
so as I said, typical segments, channel type and device type, because then I can
also make comparisons again, use events more intensively, set up 400 or 500 errors
that an event is then sent immediately, use the scroll depth to identify
whether the article was really read down to the bottom. Of course, it is not that
significant, but it is definitely better to see 1000 pages and only 20 have seen the
footer at the bottom, because then I just see, okay, maybe the people have already
left before and haven't read it to the end. So be sure to use scroll depth.
User path, that's just very, very important for the internal structure of the website.
Do I maybe have a menu somewhere where I also, and that's what I always say,
I'm a fan of Zillowing and Zillowing means I only have links on my pages that are
in the topic environment. That's also what I find very, very well implemented in the fashion
area at Zalando, because when I'm in a world, in a
theme world, then I only have links on the page that also have to do with this
theme world and no longer 600 links over the menu. And just predecessors and successors,
that's exactly the point. There I can show these data to the customer and say,
look, these are the frequent links that are also clicked there. So the interest is there.
The internal search can help me to better identify these contents that are
searched for. With us it was quite classic in the shop that the people wrote a lot of brands wrong,
because they didn't know it better either. And in the end we just expanded our
internal search so that we could enter aliases there and then in the end
led the people back to the right direction and thus generated more revenue. That wasn't
so bad either. And also to cover up the bad links. So what brings me visitors,
but these visitors are all, rather, bad values, bad signals in relation to
values ​​such as jump rate and passing time or then of course in the e-commerce area, where I say
I track my goals and my conversions. There is also the which bad back links,
so to speak, never count on my whole things. Maybe just a note,
because it just flew around in the other project. Please pay more attention to what
Blogspot is doing right now. So they don't do it themselves, but they have a huge
band problem right now and we already have two or three large newspaper publishers who really had to
suffer. Yes, that's it from my side. As I said, here again my contact details.
Feel free to write to me via the various platforms if you have any questions.
Yes, and otherwise I hope that the lecture was good and despite the short interruption that you
could take a lot with you. Exactly, so if there are still questions now, I don't want to
discourage you. And I can turn on my camera here too. Then you also have a picture for the
face. If that now transfers a picture to the film. Exactly, so hello from me too.
Exactly, so if there are questions, please just put yourself through. Yes, I had already
initially, as you talked about the topic of jump rates, I wrote in the chat
that you can also set the heartbeat timer. Exactly, yes. That even on a single page,
I have a blog and there I have a very high jump rate on one page,
that's why I discovered the heartbeat timer, at least to measure a stay time.
That might be an important note. Exactly, maybe also here at this point, there are a lot of
ideas from Google Analytics to switch over to Matomo. There it is also the case that, for example,
in Google Analytics, the events, when I set them, for example, something like button clicks
or downloads and so on, that they then also completely, so to speak, the jump rate
or also the stay time, then also send. That means there is simply a different
way of doing things than we do at Matomo. That's why at this point, really a very good tip,
also with the heartbeat timer. However, it is not used that often,
because I also have the problem very, very often that it sends every 15 seconds,
I can configure that. First of all, it sends every 15 seconds back home,
which for many is similar to a page impression, leads to great loads. And the second
is that many already have historical data, which of course no longer work properly,
because you then compare before heartbeat timer to the right times. I definitely recommend heartbeat timer
in any case. Especially, of course, when you have single page applications,
you know that very often in the meantime. There is only one page and there are
perhaps different anchor jumps on the website and then I have no
values ​​to pass by. And that's why, as I said, at this point a lot of good
use of this heartbeat timer.
Oh, one more note, especially for those who have joined the WordPress plugin in Matomo,
the heartbeat timer can be activated very easily with a little hook.
Exactly, you have to say that didn't work at the beginning, you still repaired something,
because the heartbeat timer was a bit destroyed with version 4 and couldn't be set up properly
via the tech manager. That should now also work, as I said, from WordPress.
I also know it, most of the net users really use WordPress and that's where it works.
Should you just be aware that it is always sent home every 15 seconds,
for example, it will be said, I'm still there, I'm still there, I'm still there.
Yes, so if there are no more questions, I'm also on Facebook, I'm on Xing,
you should also find me relatively easily on the Internet. If there are still questions,
go to the workshop or maybe just topics where you want to discuss it or say,
yes, I might see it differently, I'm very open, as I said, as far as the whole topic is concerned.
Yes, otherwise I thank you, I hope, as I said, it was an interesting lecture,
the slides and so on, the recording and all that, I hope that it will also be distributed
by Matomo himself or by the organizers here and shared.
And yes, then I thank you for your attention and I look forward to seeing you again.