Hi, everybody. So the talk is now recorded, so I think that we can start this talk. So
my name is Romain Biard, and I'd like to introduce you to the development of plugins for Matomo.
And we will take the approach to have a technical introduction for plugin development, not only
what can we do with plugins, but also how do we do it from a technical standpoint. So
what will we talk about during this talk? So I present myself, and we will ask ourselves
what we can do with a plugin, which is the very start of plugin development. What's the
point of developing a plugin? Also, we will see how to be ready for plugin developments
for Matomo, and then we will dig deeper into the technical considerations of plugin development
for Matomo. So what are the basics of a plugin? How to add settings to Matomo if you need
specific settings for your plugin. How to store content in the database. How to use
an external API if you want to gather external data to cross with the data stored in Matomo.
Also how to localize your plugin, because obviously you will want to distribute it and
have users everywhere in the world. How to publish your plugin onto Matomo marketplace.
How to maintain it. And if you have any questions, we will have some room for discussion at the
end of the presentation, but also feel free to stop me during this presentation so I can
answer your questions along the way. So let's start with a short bio of myself. So my name
is Romain Biard. I'm the CTO for a company called Mascot, which is providing a learning
management software called Taktileo. I'm in charge of the product and development teams.
I've recently worked as a lead engineer in the DevOps company, and before that I had
a web development and digital strategy company for 10 years and also had experiences as sales
representative for US tech companies. I have a double degree, bachelor in computer sciences
and master in management. And from a more personal side, I have a personal attachment
for Chile where I lived for two years in the suburbs of Valparaiso. I like poetry, short
novels, and I am an occasional open source contributor. So here are a couple of projects
that I used to contribute to, obviously Matomo plugins, but also PHP FFmpeg, which is a package
to convert videos using FFmpeg. And if you look at my GitHub profile, you'll see that
it happened to me to contribute to other plugins, other open source projects on an occasional
basis. So a plugin for what? This may be a very trivial question, but I think it's absolutely
critical to ask it first to make sure that if you begin developing a plugin, you already
exactly know how to tackle the different aspects of the development in order to reach your
goal. So there are some important questions to answer first. So what is Matomo made for?
Matomo is made for collecting data on visitors of your website. So who is visiting your website?
How long do they stay on your website? Which pages are visited? Where do they come from?
Where are they clicking on your website? All this data is collected by Matomo. So this
is important to have that in mind in order to figure out what we can do with this data.
So you can ask yourself, are there additional data that could be useful for my business
or other businesses or other people? Like you may want to combine data from Matomo or from
external sources to make new information arise. So if you consider additional data, it could
be either data coming from external sources like APIs, or it could be also data that you
will collect by enriching the tracking API with your own tracking data. Also, ask yourself
who you are targeting because you very likely will not provide the same type of reports
and the same type of data if you're working with individuals or if you're working with
companies. There are specific information that each public, each type of people will
want to access, and depending on who is your target with this plugin, you will very likely
not provide the same type of data. Also, if this plugin is made for your company's need,
for instance, ask yourself who will use this plugin in your team. Is it the marketing?
Is it the sales team, the support team? How confident are they on data manipulation? What
is their ability to understand tables of numbers, understand charts, to understand very different
type of reports? And this will help you design the plugins that you want to develop. And
so, finally, do I need to gather data from additional sources to achieve my goal of developing
a plugin from Atomo? You will have to ask this to yourself as well. So, examples of
what could be done. You could, for instance, create a plugin that will generate a report
to display the weather in the city of your visitors. So, this could help you figure out
if the weather has an impact on your sales. You could compare political obedience of mayors
of the cities of your visitors to figure out if they are more likely to be in favor of
a political party or not. And it's very likely that these data are open data that you can
find on public sources on the internet. You could also create a report comparing the size
of the cities of your visitors if you want to figure out if your visitors or clients
are more urban or more from rurality. You could also create a report with a list of
countries from where your visitors are, the percentage of traffic that these countries
drive to your website, and how they rank in the PISA survey, which would answer the question,
what's the level of education of my clients or visitors? And these are just ideas that
I gathered for this talk, but there are a lot more ideas that you can come up with,
because all of these ideas are based on visitors' sources and does not work with, for instance,
the behavior of your visitors on your website, like which pages they visit, how long do they
stay on your website, et cetera, which are also important information that you could
cross with other information to make new intelligence arise.
So let's take the different types of reports that already exist in Matomo. You have already
in the application a lot of reports that you could generate. You can have charts, bar charts,
line charts, pie charts, et cetera. You can have tables of data. You can have maps. But
if you don't find the type of report that fits your need, you have the ability to create
your own one. The screenshot on the right is a report generated by a plugin called TreeMap,
which demonstrates that you can create any type of graphical representation that fits
your need with the development of a custom plugin. And this is particularly interesting
if you want to present your information in a specific way and not stay in what Matomo
offers to you.
So know that you've defined what you want to do. You need to ask yourself, what type
of data do I need to generate these reports? And where will I find this data, either in
Matomo database or externally? So to make this presentation simple, I'll base my demonstration
on the plugins that I developed, which is called IP2Company, and which is available
on Matomo Marketplace. And the point of this plugin is to try to get the name of the company
of your visitors for a sales development perspective. So if you know that visitors are from, I don't
know, AT&T or in Europe could be arranged, could be a bank, I don't know, Societe Generale,
whatever it is, you can have a prescription actions afterwards and try to call them if
it's not already a client or follow up with an estimate that you've sent to them because
you see that they come on your website after a specific action towards them.
So in order to develop a plugin, you need to prepare your development. So what do you
need to prepare your developments? You need an IDE, obviously. It sounds basic, but still
we're talking about development. You need a fresh setup of Matomo, a good knowledge
of PHP, ideally Docker, because it's easier to get a fresh setup of Matomo and deploy
your Matomo instance afterwards. And you need Git, which is something needed if you want
to publish your plugin on the marketplace. So why a fresh setup on Matomo? Why not working
on the instance of Matomo that you already have? Because it will help you to avoid conflicts
with other plugins when starting your developments. And I think it's very important to be sure
that your plugin is working as it should in the most simple environment that you can imagine.
So let's start from scratch when developing a new plugin to make sure that nothing is
interfering with our developments. Also, it will help you to generate random data to work
on. So Matomo has this neat feature, which allows you to get some dummy data in the database
when you set up the software to be able to test the software and test your developments.
Also make sure that you have enough data for your tests to be relevant. So when generating
new data, you can choose for how many days you want to generate data and share screen
with you afterwards. Be at least compatible with the latest version of Matomo. This is
really important and one of the reasons to have a fresh setup of Matomo because the latest
version of Matomo ensures that you're at the state of the art in terms of features, in
terms of security, and you need to be at least compatible with this version. If you're also
compatible with previous version, it's even better. But you should consider that this
is the very minimum requirement for your plugin.
So how do we do that? The easiest way is to use Docker and create a new instance of Matomo
using the already packaged Docker configuration files. Once you've done that, you can use
the CLI of your Docker instance to enable development. And to do that, you just have
to run this command at the root of the project. This will add a new tab in the administration
menu, which is called development. And this tab will allow you to generate dummy data
for your website. So here you can see that you can define how many days you want to compute
and to add to your database. Just be careful to not create too much data because it generates
really a lot of data and it can take quite some time to generate too much data.
So once you've done that, let's begin the development of our plugin. So what are the
basics of a plugin? The first thing to do is to understand how Matomo works in general.
So you need to know that Matomo is made entirely of plugins. The core of Matomo only contains
tools for those plugins, so a small collection of functions that are used by the plugins.
But everything in Matomo is made of plugins, even Matomo itself, even what you use when
you are having the basic setup of Matomo. So if you want to create your own plugin,
you just have to run this command again at the root of the project with the name of your
plugin. This will generate a new folder in the plugin directory using this name with
a couple of files in it, and eventually you will reach to a tree of files that looks to
something like this. This is more or less a standard tree of files for a Matomo plugin.
So the two key files that are generated during plugin creation are plugin.json, which is
a description of your plugin, which includes metadata for the marketplace, and this file,
this PHP file, which is a root file of your plugin. And this root file listens to events
and hooks such as install, such as activation or uninstallation. The rest is not needed,
but without the rest, your plugin won't do much. So you will very likely have a part
of the rest or almost everything in this list. So getting a no need for me to describe what
it does, a license to describe the type of license that applies to your work, a readme
also to describe your project, and then we reach to more interesting stuff. API.php is
almost at the core of your plugin because it defines API methods for your plugin that
will be reachable by other plugins if needed, but more than that, that will be reachable
by the components of your plugin, like the reports. And this is absolutely critical to
have this file at the root of the project because it will contain an important part
of the logic of your plugin. You can also have some config files to change the way Matomo
use the dependency injection, some documentation that will be used in the marketplace. You
can have localization with languages files in this long folder. Don't forget to include
screenshots when publishing your plugin into Matomo marketplace. If you want to have specific
styles that apply to the UI, you can have stylesheets here. And then these two are important.
So this folder will contain the reports that you will create for your plugin. So you have
one PHP file for each report you want to be generated by your plugin. And you will have
in the updates the files that will contain the migration that will be run by your plugin.
So if at some point you want to add new data to the database, you will need to create a
migration and it will come here in the updates folder.
So let's start with the basis. So two files are important. I mentioned that, plugin.json
and the root PHP file. So let's have a look at plugin.json. What do we have in it? We
have a basic description of what your plugin is. So you have here the name of your plugin,
you have the description of your plugin, the version, the actual version of your plugin.
You have the root stylesheet to use, the version of Matomo that your plugin supports. You have
a description of your source and everything needed to contact you. If there is an issue
with your plugin or if people want to contribute, you can describe everything in this section.
You can also provide a URL to the home page of your plugin if you have a public repo or
a specific website for your plugin. The type of license that you use and some keywords
that will allow people to look for your plugin in Matomo Marketplace. So you can see that
this plugin.json file is very basic and does not require any technical skills. You just
have to provide all the information that will properly describe your plugin.
The next one, the PHP file, which is at the root of the project, is more interesting.
So we've seen that this root file allows you to listen to different events that occur during
the life of your plugin, like what should we do when we install the plugin, when we
activate the plugin, or when we install the plugin. We can also listen to events and register
actions corresponding to each type of event. Let's have a closer look at the different
events and methods that we can define.
If you want, for instance, which is what I did for this IP2Company plugin, create a table
to store data in the database. You can use this install hook to actually create the table
that you need. This way, when people will install the plugin, it will automatically
create the required table inside the database. Or if you prefer, you can do it during activation.
That's your decision. You decide what fits best for you. But these functions, these hooks
are made for that. They are made to perform automatic actions at different stages of the
life of your plugin.
On the other side, when installing your plugin, it's a good practice to drop the tables that
you previously created to not overload the database of your users. You generally want
to keep a clean database. When removing the plugin, it's a nice behavior to also remove
your tables.
Well, now just send me a message asking if there is a hook for update actions. Yes, there
is one. If you look at the screen in the left, oh, good question. I have activate and install
and register. I do not mention update in my presentation. To be truly honest, I don't
know, but you can find this information in the documentation of the Matamor developer
section. I'll post the link here. If there is something that you want to know and I don't
have the answer for, you can always refer to this documentation, which is really, really
complete. I advise you to have a look at it because there are a lot of endpoints, a lot
of classes that you can discover and that will also help you define what your plugin
can do. I don't have an exhaustive knowledge of this documentation and of what Matamor
offers, but you should always refer to this documentation and to the ability of Matamor
to be sure that you exploit all the abilities offered by this software. Thanks for your
question.
We've got our new plugin, but what does it do actually? So far, nothing. We've just set
up the very basic files of our plugin. Let's add some logic to our plugin. What we very
likely want to do is to add a report to the plugin. Reports are at the core of Matamor
and this is something that comes with almost every plugin. You need to decide how you want
your data to be displayed and the type of report you want to generate. So to create
a new report, you just have to run this command at the root of the project again. The difference
with the previous commands is that this command is an interactive one. So you will be asked
for the name of your report and some other additional information that will allow Matamor
to generate these files. Let's have a look at them.
So the base.php is like a base class that will allow you to define how users will access
to your plugin. In my case, I decided to use the main visitors tab in the main menu and
to put my feature in the sub menu of the visitors item. So I just have to set the category ID
in which I want to integrate, which is provided by Matamor to never underscore visitors. And
then I can extend this class with new classes like this one, GetCompanies, which will allow
me to provide additional information. So what do we find in this GetCompanies class? We
can set the name of the report. We can set the description, the subcategory of the report,
the order in which it appears, and also the metrics that we need and the columns that
we want to display in the reports. This one is important and you will see that we will
come back to it in a moment because these elements that you find in the columns table
are also used by translation functions to display nice text to the users.
So let's follow up and have a closer look at this report. So GetCompanies. What are
the methods that we can find in this GetCompanies besides the construct? So we have an important
one, which is ConfigureView, and I'll give you a closer look to this method afterwards.
You can also have GetReacted reports to display other reports at the same time than yours.
I don't use it for my plugin, but you can. And you can also add specific configuration
for the widget if you want to create one. But the real logic will stand here in the
ConfigureView. So let's have a look at ConfigureView. Here you are with the ConfigureView, and it's
pretty straightforward. So let's have a look at the different parameters that are set there.
If we look at it, we can see that if there is a dimension set, we can define the translation
to use for the label. So remember what I've said before, no dimension is set in my case,
but still the logic is to handle this scenario. Then I define some configuration settings.
So yes, I want to have a search bar in my report. Yes, I want to have pagination to
be able to navigate through the different pages of results. Yes, I also want to have
a limit of results per page. I want to show periods of time, but I'm not using a bar chart
nor a pie chart or tag clue report. I want to have a basic table of data which will display
raw data to my users. This is a very simplest scenario that you can imagine, but these settings
will allow you to create very different scenarios and very different types of reports. And as
you can see, they are very simple to change. You can also add configuration like sorting,
etc. And then what do I do? I just take the keys that I defined just before, these keys,
my columns, to replace them with actual understandable text. And I use translations for that. So we'll
see afterwards how to translate your plugin, but think about using these translation functions
each time you need to display text because this will allow you to have a localized plugin.
And then one important thing is to enrich your API.php file because your report needs
to be supported by specific functions in the API.php. The command that you've run to create
the report automatically added a getCompanies function to this file, but you need to define
the logic of this function. And in this method, what do I do? First, I check for user rights
to make sure that he can access to the report. Then I collect data that I want to process
on some parameters like the ID of the site I'm actually visiting or a specific period
of time. And then I process the data and we'll see afterwards what I mean by processing the
data. And once the data is processed, I just return an array with the same keys than the
ones defined in my report file and the corresponding value. This is as simple as that.
So do we have a functional plugin now? Yes, we do. And you could stop there if you want,
but obviously you will want to do many more things. So let's move a bit forward and see
what we can do with Matomos plugin. One thing that you will want to do is configure your
plugin with some settings. I'll try to move a bit to talk a bit faster because I have
very little time and still a lot of things to say. So there are two different types of
settings that you can configure. System settings, which are global to your plugin and website.
And user settings that you can see here that are specific to each user. So if you look
at system settings, in my scenario, I've defined two settings that are important for me, like
an access token to an external API to be able to send requests to this API and the lifetime
of the cache that I created with the table that I created at the installation of the
plugin. So adding these settings are as easy as creating two methods that will define which
type of data you're collecting in the access token scenario. This is a text field. And
in this cache lifetime, this is also a text field. Same for the user settings. You can
define methods to create and get the values. And in this scenario, I want to see if my
users want to receive my report by email on a regular basis. And it's just a Boolean that
I will collect. So a checkbox is fine for that. And here is the logic to get the data
from the database. So now that I have collected these settings from my users, how do I use
them? So back to the logic of our plugin. What do we want to do? We want to compare
the visits that we received on our website with an external API to see if we can get
the name of the company to which our visitors belong. So we collect the visits. We loop
through them. And for each visit, we get the details of the IP address. And here is the
get IP details method. We check in the database if we have already collected information for
this IP. So we use the cache that we created. And if there is no result in the database,
we will send a request to the external API. So it has nothing to do with our settings.
That's correct. But we're going to it. To be able to communicate with the external
API, I created a specific class called IP info, which is the name of the external service
that I'm using, which will handle the relation with this API. And if you look at the construct
method of this class, I'm calling the system settings class that I created with a specific
method called get value, which will allow me to get the value of the access token that
has been set by the user. So afterwards, I can perform some tests on this value to make
sure that it's not empty, et cetera. But here is a way to get the value of the settings
and use them. It's pretty straightforward. Two lines.
So other things that might interest you in the development of a plugin is how to store
data in the database. So back again to the logic of our plugin. So here in this get IP
details method that we've just seen, remember that we're checking the database to see if
there is an entry for this IP. And if there is one, we update the details of the entry.
If not, we create a new one. So how do we exactly communicate with the database? Here
are methods that I created to have a more readable code. But if you look at it, get
stored companies, it's just a call using the DB class provided by Matomo with a specific
method called fetch hold. And then you can pass the SQL request that you want to be performed
on your database. Same with insert companies. It's just a DB method from the DB class that
will allow you to execute some SQL that you created. So you can perform any SQL request
that you want. Be careful with this SQL request to sanitize your content if you're using data
coming from the user. Same with update. It's a DB exec again. So manipulating data in the
database is pretty straightforward and simple. And Matomo provides all the classes that you
need to do that in an easy way. You can also use an external API. We've seen that before.
So here is my IP info class. And in this IP info class, I have other methods that actually
perform requests towards this IP info API. And what does this request look like? It's
described here with the get request details method. And as you can see, it's a very simple
curl request. So you can insert in your Matomo plugin any type of logic, the same ones that
you used to within your PHP applications. It's just a place for you to implement what
really interests you and compare data stored inside Matomo with any other type of data,
be it from Matomo again or from external sources. So yeah, coding an external API is just a
basic curl request as you would do within any PHP application. Localizing your plugin
is something important if you want to distribute it globally. Three things are needed. A list
of localized files that you will very likely get from Weblight, which is a website used
by Matomo's team to host translations, either from the core of Matomo or from the plugins.
And this method to translate content based on a key, the keys that you will find in your
languages files. So now that you have a functional plugin, you will want to publish it in Matomo
Marketplace. So make sure that you're done with the development of your plugin. You've
seriously tested it and you're ready to offer it to the rest of the world. Sometimes you
also want to keep this work for yourself. But if you're ready to distribute it, Matomo's
Marketplace is the right place to do it. Some things are important to check before publishing
the plugin. Make sure that it has a unique name and does not contain some protected keywords
like Matomo, Puwek Analytics, et cetera. Make sure that you have a readme markdown file
with a description of your plugin and a plugin.json file to describe your plugin. Verify that
the versions of Matomo and PHP that you declare in your plugin.json file are actually compatible
with your plugin. Make some screenshots of your plugin and put them in the corresponding
folder. Put your plugin on GitHub. This is mandatory. And add a webhook to your GitHub
repo because each time that you will create a new tag and push it to GitHub, this webhook
will be called and it will automatically publish the new version of your plugin onto Matomo's
Marketplace. This is a very handy, easy process that Matomo's team has set up. And you just
have to create a tag and push it to GitHub to deploy a new version of your plugin to
Matomo. And then the last thing to do is to maintain
your plugin. So stay updated with the latest developments of Matomo to make sure that your
plugin is still compatible with them. Test your plugin with new versions of Matomo. Also
maintain a change log at the root of your project to keep track of the different changes
that you perform on your plugin. So this way, other developers can easily have a look at
what has been done and if the changes are critical or not. Ideally, you would accept
contributions from other developers and answer to issues. And it's very human to say that
you don't have time enough to maintain your plugin, but try to say it so it's clear for
other people where you are with this plugin. And use it for your own purposes to make sure
that it still fits at least your needs and ideally others' needs as well.
Well, that's it for this presentation. Thank you very much for your attention. And I've
got an interesting question for Tasman about testing. So Matomo has this test management
lead in its core. So you can write PHP tests using PHP unit. And you can run these tests
pretty easily with some commands that you will execute at the root of your project.
So like the rest of the content in your plugin, you can use a command to generate new tests.
I paste it in the chat. So here is the basic command to generate a unit test. And then
you can also, this will create a class with tests in it. And then you can run this test
by also running a simple command. So here is an example in the chat again. And more
globally, if you want to have more details about testing your plugin, you can refer to
this documentation, which is pretty complete. Not sure if it answers your question, Tasman,
but that's the way to do it. Any other questions? Well, it looks like everything has been asked.
So thank you very much for your attention. If you have questions that arise after this
presentation, you can still ping me on the different networks. And I think that this
presentation will be available on Matomo's website or Matomo's website since it has been
recorded. So I hope it will be useful for other people afterwards. Thank you very much
for your time and attention. Bye-bye.