So hello, everyone, and welcome in this talk.
Today, we are going to talk about how
to configure Matamow for SAS and get
relevant data for your business.
So I'm your speaker for the next minutes.
I'm presenting myself.
My name is Ronan Hélot.
I'm an independent web developer in France.
I'm also a web development teacher in several schools.
And two years ago, I built up a MOOC website
called ronan-hellot.fr, and will
contain many courses about digital analytics
and development techniques.
And I'm also a Matamow contributor.
I made many contributions, like TEMs or plugins.
The one, it's a dark TEM to turn your Matamow interface
into dark.
Google TEM to prevent incoming users to Matamow
from Google Analytics to the Matamow interface.
They will love the Google TEM applying
to the Matamow interface.
And KPI widget plugin, which provides you many widgets
that you can put on your dashboard
and will generate tiny widgets with a single KPI on it.
The purpose of this talk, we are talking
about Matamow advanced configuration
and how to collect specific data.
We are adding more context to the data we are collecting
and how to create awesome reports in your SAS.
And then we are going further with premium plugins.
We are not talking about infrastructure
because there are many people at Matamow Camp
already did it better than I can.
And it's not the purpose of my talk.
We are assuming that you already are GDPR compliant.
So you already have the cookie wall or cookie banner
because we are going to use the visitor log, the user
ID, and user profile.
And those functionality require user consent
being GDPR compliant.
So I imagine that you are in a basic Matamow configuration.
So you already have deployed the default tracking
code on every single page you want to track.
And this default tracking code will provide you
some data, such as pages and sessions, unique and new
visitors, some default events, the hardware and software
configuration visitors have to walk through your website.
And sometimes, if you have an internal search,
the terms, basically tracking, some real-time action,
downloads as default events, and IP-based location.
So that's all the data or a part of the data
that Matamow already collects for you.
And you need a bit more.
You need user segmentation.
You need a well-synced user profile to your SAS.
We need, again, to add more context to the data we collect.
And we will be able to create custom events, custom goals.
And we will see in the second part
how to create a report of JavaScript error
that the user will find on your SAS platform.
The first part of this talk is about collecting driven data.
And in a second time, we will see
how to apply them in a properly reports
or directly in your SAS platform.
One of the first things you have to do
is to switch between the basic Matamow configuration
to the Matamow Tag Manager configuration.
To do this, you just have to switch between the tracking
code that provides by Matamow and placing this Matamow Tag
Manager code on every single page you want to track.
Don't forget to place the default Matamow statistic
tag, which allows you to recreate the default Matamow
configuration.
Matamow Tag Manager provides you a cool interface
to create tags or configuring some cool stuff
like custom events on many, many things
that we will see in this talk.
The things that will very, very help
us to configure Matamow for your SAS
is building up custom events.
During a long visit, your user will perform key actions
on your software or your website.
And you have to track all the journey of your users
to trigger those custom events and collect them
into your Matamow interface.
This event will be sent back to Matamow
and collected and displayed in the events report right
in your Matamow instance.
To start, regularly, I create two basics events
based on the form submission.
There is the login and the register form submission
on your SAS.
And we just have to create this kind of event.
So look, you go just in your back office,
create a Matamow Analytics tag.
You switch then the tag to the tracking type of events.
And then you have to configure your events.
I set the event category to health
to keep login and register events under the same name
and define an event name as a login.
We then have to create a trigger, the form submit.
And we just plug that trigger to the form ID
and listen for a form submission.
So we have to find the form ID.
Just have to inspect your website
and search for the ID of your login or register form.
Here is a login.form ID.
And then your trigger will be created and assigned
to the Matamow event tag.
Don't forget to publish a new container on your website
or it won't work.
And then you just, in this few steps,
have the ability to collect every single time a user is
just logged in in your SAS platform.
Don't worry about that.
You can create the same thing for register events
and for many, many things.
I'm talking here about some entities
that you manage on your SAS platform.
Let's imagine for a CRM platform that you have a contact
that the user can create.
Every single time they create a contact
or another kind of entity.
They can make stuff like, in development,
we say it's a CRUD, CRUD for create, read, update, and delete.
There are the four main actions that you
can do to almost any entity on your platform.
And it will be interesting of collecting those actions
and placing them in the visitor journey on your website.
One of the four actions of the CRUD, the red action,
is already tracked by Matomo only if the entity has
their own page.
Like, for example, if you see Airbnb,
when you create a new house, the house
will be available for everyone directly from Google.
So Matomo can collect the view of this entity.
But for the create, update, and delete,
there is no custom events by default.
So you have to set them up just as we
saw with the form submission event.
Another application that I already
made for several platforms is like when
you have a SAS platform with many workspace and many teams.
A user can create one or many teams.
And then you can add a member, remove a member,
or delete a team.
This is a factual example of how you
can manage your different custom events
and how you can name them to finally visualize them right
in your Matomo instance.
Don't forget to package all the different events of the CRUD
under the same event category name.
This category name will be team event, probably.
Then now you have your custom events
deployed on your platform.
And you have the ability in Matomo
to create custom goals based on those events.
So Matomo provides you an easy interface to configure a goal
and mark all the sessions that achieve one or many goals
to consider that the visit has converted your user
into a lead or a customer.
So for this part, you just have to create a new goal,
like one of the three you can see there.
For the login, as you see, my goal name is login.
The description is for a user connected to his account.
And the goal is triggered when a user sends an event.
And the event name is exactly a login, so exactly what
we set up at the previous slide.
Another huge part that will be really interesting
to add context to Matomo is using custom dimensions.
Because the data that Matomo collects, basically,
is very lacking context.
And for some reason, we are using
Matomo to add this context to the data.
Custom dimensions are not really hard to set up.
But you have to follow some rules.
And here, in our configuration, we
are using Matomo Tag Manager.
And in Matomo Tag Manager, we have to set up a data layer,
like the piece of code you can see from the code snippet
you just see on the screen.
This code snippet is a data layer
that I filled with two custom values, the logged in,
actually set to true, and the user plan,
actually set to premium.
And then in your Matomo Tag Manager,
you just have to go back to your main Matomo statistic tag
and change the configuration of your Matomo variable.
In this Matomo variable, if you scroll down,
you will find this section about custom dimension.
Then you can add an automatic tracking
of your custom dimensions.
Here, the first index is for user plan.
And the second index is for logged in or not user.
So about the two custom dimensions,
I already tell you, as you can see, when you are logged in,
we just display true in the data layer.
And when you are anonymous people,
or not just not logged in, we set false in the data layer.
Those two kinds of data will be uploaded to Matomo
every time you change the page.
And we will have a full vision of the status of the user.
The second dimensions I already set up many times
is the user plan.
Based on the business of many SaaS platforms,
will be a premium to premium strategy.
In the first time, we have many and several people
using a free plan.
That's what you can see in the first data
layer displayed on the slide.
And then the user will try the soft using a trial
period, as long as one or many weeks,
depending of your solution.
And then during this period, I send specific code
as a trial for the value of the user plan variable
in data layer.
And then when the trial period has ended, my user
just switched to the premium plan.
And I just send that value into the data layer of Matomo.
Now we know how to create custom events, custom goals,
and custom dimensions.
But we have to attach all of those data to our user.
Because we are in a SaaS configuration,
and we have a log in, and our user is our main entity.
And we have to attach all of the data.
So we are going to know how to pass a visitor to a user.
Matomo has a complete functionality about user ID.
And two ways of deploying it into your code.
Here, the first line, as you can see, is pack.push.
Set user ID is for the default Matomo tracking code.
Or if you are using Matomo Tag Manager,
you can continue to use your data layer
and just add a custom variable as user ID,
and then as value, the unique identifier
you just choose between data of your database.
The user ID will act as a bridge between your database
and the Matomo database.
It will allow you to track user across different devices
they use at home, like a smartphone, or a laptop,
or a business computer.
You will be able to track them.
And then, as you will see in the next slide,
you are able to see every single visit on action and event
triggered right on the profile generated in the Matomo site.
So here is my own profile.
As you can see, I'm at 100 visits.
In reality, I'm very, very far of 100 visits, very more.
But the profile is limited to the last 100
visits at the display.
I'm sure that you can expand this value.
But actually, it's locked to the 100.
And you will find on this profile every action
and every event that the user trigger
on the Matomo interface.
You will see in the next slide that we won't use directly
this profile right on Matomo, but we prefer asking the API
to create a custom profile right on your SaaS.
And then, because you're a company,
you have to gain some money.
And we have to configure Matomo Enhanced E-Commerce
for your SaaS.
It's a functionality that is built in Matomo.
You can enable it just by turning on the switch
to E-Commerce enabled and set up the currency you use.
To have a fully implementation of Matomo Enhanced E-Commerce,
you have to configure your data layer
and add some code on the product page or in the funeral
different page.
The Matomo E-Commerce will trigger some events.
And those events will be readable in the events report
right in Matomo.
All the events you will trigger will be under the event
category of subscription.
And as you can see on the screen that I just
picked on the Matomo documentation because of my website
is not an E-Commerce website.
And I can't take a screenshot of my customers.
So thanks to Matomo for this screen.
And as you can see, all the event actions
are signed up, cancellation, and upgrade
about the subscription plan for all of your users.
So it will be pretty cool.
And as usual, you can add a value to events.
And this value will be used to calculate a minimum value
or an average value of your revenue.
Then Matomo will provide you for 200 rupee a year a funeral
E-Commerce plugin that will allow you to put a beacon
in your funeral to define where your users are leaving
this pattern and why the user are leaving their cart.
So they trigger at every step a custom event.
And this event will be will be catched by Matomo
and generate some cool stuff and cool event-based report.
But this is on a premium feature.
So now we are able to collect data.
But the most important part is to retrieve those data
and create some cool reports and analyze
them to take a good decision in the next time.
For this second part, we will talk about segments
because your Matomo instance is now filled by useful data.
And we are now going to visualize them
in the proper reports using segments.
The first category of segments that I will create
will be goal segments based on achievements or not of a goal.
And here, as you can see, we just
create cool segments which allow you
to filter the visits using the achievements of a goal.
And here I set the goal to subscribe,
which is if a user have triggered an event subscribe
which convert the goal subscribe,
it will be filtered in this segment.
It's pretty cool to activate a segment
and continue to visualize all the reports in Matomo
with a filtered view.
Then the second type of segment I
will allow you to create is about dimensions segments.
Earlier in this talk, we already create two custom dimensions,
one for the logged in user and the second one
for the user plan.
And we can have five types of results, visitor only,
logged in user, premium user, in trial period users,
and premium users.
All of those configurations will be, for me, a custom segment.
So here, for the example, I just created
a segment for premium users.
So you can select in the first dropdown the user plan.
This is obviously your custom dimension.
And then the operator is is and the value is about premium.
So you will be able to store as many segments
as you want in your selector and then switch between them.
And it will be easier for you to track and to visualize
the journey of your user right on the Matomo interface.
This second part will be better for a technical or developer
person.
I invite you to enable JavaScript Tracking Error
right in your Matomo configuration.
For a Matomo Tag Manager user, it
will be in the Matomo statistics variable.
And you will just have a checkbox to enable,
and it will collect for you JavaScript Tracking Error.
This report will allow you to recreate the session
of the user who encountered an error in an attempt
to reproduce it.
And it will be very, very important for SAS owner.
The functionality will catch error displayed in the console
and trigger an event, which are all grouped into the event
category of JavaScript error.
Here, as you can see, I have four JavaScript errors
triggered from the beginning of the month.
So we have the five, so I have to fix it.
And as you can see in the second part, in Event Action,
you will have the URL of the HTML page or the JavaScript
file, which contains the error.
And then if you switch to the event name,
you will have the message write display in this table.
It's a copy of the message, which
is normally displayed in the console of your web browser.
So it will help you to view a difference error.
To exploit those information, you have to create a segment.
This segment will be an event category
based on JavaScript error.
Event category is JavaScript error.
This segment will be applied to all of your information.
And then you can switch to the visitor log.
And as you can see, this is the fourth visits
that have encountered a JavaScript error
since the beginning of the month.
There is a kind of problem with this, because as you can see,
every visitor that you can see on the screen
has just made a one-page view and have three actions.
Because of JavaScript tracking trigger an event,
an event in Matomo counts into the actions.
As you can see, a user who just walked through one page
has three actions counted.
So it will break the ratio of the actions per page or actions
per session.
And it will not let you have clear information.
So maybe it will be fun to find a solution
to not merge those events into the action counter.
And then we enter in my favorite section of this talk.
It's about the reporting API.
So Matomo is now full of data.
And Matomo have a great and powerful API.
So why are you not using it in your back office
to generate contextual charts?
This is a screenshot of my own website
where I provide some contents, mainly textual content.
And here are some blog posts.
As you can see, in my homemade back office, I have a chart.
And this chart is generated directly from Matomo.
In clear, Matomo API provides me the data I need.
And those data are organized page per page.
So I ask the Matomo API, providing the post URL
and the Matomo API, let me find their data.
I just configured the Matomo API to answer me in JSON format.
And then I took those data and use
them to build homemade charts using the HTML library chart
GS.
And as you can see, it's pretty nice.
And I have the information right in my back office.
And I don't have to connect to my Matomo instance
to visualize them.
Just in the right of the charts, you
can see my visit KPI information and the bounce
rate of every single episode.
As a real user, I prefer looking at those charts
right in my back office than switching to the Matomo
interface and searching in the page reports
to get those informations.
And then we can do exactly the same thing
with user AI-based data.
So here is my own profile, because I
don't want to show you other profiles.
But here, as you can see, I have a user ID set up on my website
and the user ID.
Let me asking the API of Matomo to get every page view
and sessions from a specific user.
So here, the JSON data are visualized in a custom chart
to grant a clear vision of the user visits.
As you can see, I'm pretty active on my website.
And the first November, I had a long work
to reorganize contents on my website.
So I made almost 450 visits.
But I can see if a user is still active or not on the website.
An idea of a CMS integration of that Matomo API
is because of the changements about Google Search Engine
and integrating the Core Web Vitals.
So here, it's an idea that we can build a plugin for CMS,
like WordPress, to show up just on the line of the table
that display all the page or all the posts
are published on your website, a clear indicator,
red to green indicator, to determine if the page load
faster or not.
I'm not a graphist, but I just make
that little visualization based on the screen
from the documentation of WordPress.
And I just add page speed and a green light.
But as you can see, it will be a better way
to have this kind of information.
And then to go further, you can also create custom alerts.
But you can create custom alerts for almost every support,
not only a SaaS platform.
But I create all the time custom alerts about drop in visit,
drop in revenue.
If you are a SaaS platform, drop in subscriptions.
It will be very important for you to keep an eye on it.
And you can do it simply by installing the custom alerts
plugin, who is already available on the marketplace of MetaMo.
And then to continue and go further and furthermore,
there is a premium bundle of plugin,
which is specifically interesting for your SaaS
as a heat map and session recording,
which generates an amount and amount of data,
but will allow you to recreate the session of your user.
Just imagine that this plugin mixed with the GS tracking
error, and you will be able to recreate
exactly the session of the user to try
to reproduce the GS error that he encountered in her visits.
It will be pretty, pretty useful for your SaaS.
And especially if you have a platform that
shares content for many users as a content editor and visitors,
you will be really interested in the Media Analytics
plugin, which allows you to track video and audio
and give you information such as the length of the video
that users really watch or the level of the volume
when they hear some audio or video.
And the next one that I didn't found on the base
is the User Flow plugin that allows you to track,
to visualize, not to track, to visualize all of your users
on the platform.
But it is very more specific to certain kind of SaaS.
So thank you for watching.
I will look for the different questions you have to ask to me.
And thank you for all the people who are still there
until this presentation.
So as I can see, I have one question.
Can you disclose the name of the SaaS platform
you applied those implementation?
Actually, for the demonstration, you saw mine.
And the other one are startups at Nantes in the city
where I live, actually.
And I think, no, I can't say those names.
According to you, Renan, what is missing within Matomo?
What is missing in Matomo?
I don't think if it's missing, but for me,
it's about the data storage.
So if you are interested in Google Analytics 3 and 4,
as you can see, they break the change
that they are breaking the data storage to another one
based on event.
And Matomo is a mix of this.
And as you can see, for GS tracking or e-commerce tracking,
they are all based on event, which is pretty cool.
And I think the way of the future for analytics software.
But it breaks many reports simply
because all the events are mixed on the same place.
So to get a clearer vision, we almost every time
have to create custom segments to see only specific events.
Maybe the event reports could be better.
Is there any other question?
I don't think.
Let's wait just a few more seconds
to make sure that nobody else is making questions in the chat.
OK.
OK, I have another question.
Why API did you find a solution to have last five minutes,
10 minutes hit on a specific page?
My API code are based on the timestamp selector.
And I guess it's about day, not five or 10 minutes.
It's a specific.
I'm not sure if it's five or 10 minutes.
I guess it's about day, not five or 10 minutes.
I don't remember because all of my time selector
are based on day, weeks, and months selector, not
about minutes.
But maybe I'm sure you will find your answer right
in the documentation.
And how hard is it to extract data out
of the reporting API of Matahomo and show it on a web page
like you did?
It really depends on the skills you already had.
So the Matahomo API is pretty cool and pretty easy to use.
It respects the standard of many, many APIs.
So if you are a web developer, you're
already familiar with the use of API.
So the Matahomo part is not the harder for me.
I think the harder is to recreate the interface
in your back office.
But asking Matahomo via the API to get the data you need
is just about 20 minutes if you have to read the documentation.
And I think I spend most of my time about headers
and requesting to the API, but that is pretty simple to set up.
Maybe I will make a video to explain
how Matahomo API will work and publish it.
But actually, it's not so hard.
And Valentin asks, API is powerful,
but what are the limits?
The limits of the API, especially,
I saw that when I tried to create a list.
So on my own back office, I have a list of all my posts
with pagination and stuff like that.
And I will use the API to display information
right in this list, but it will very, very
be heavy to carry on and will make many, many requests
to Matahomo if the API were set on this main page.
But I think the Matahomo API is powerful to send data
to Matahomo and to ask them, but only in a main entity page.
So as you can see, I just use the Matahomo API
on a view page of a single entity
as a single post entity or single user entity,
but not in a page with several entity
because of the amount of requests
we have to create if it's a data table visualization page.
And what are the limits?
The limits is like all the API.
So if you follow the REST documentation,
which is a kind of a guide for you who build an API,
if you follow those guidelines, you maybe
have to create many requests to get just one information
if you want to create some custom reports.
But it's not about Matahomo API.
It's most about generic API guidelines.
I hope that I answered your question,
which was a bit large.
If there are any other questions?
Apparently, there are no further questions in the chat.
So I'd like to thank you, Ronan, for joining Matahomo Camp
and for this very interesting session.
Thank you.
Thank you, too.
And thank you, all of you, for being there today.
And thank you for the organization
of this wonderful event.
Thank you.
So we finished a little bit earlier with this session,
but I'd like to invite everyone to join us at 5 PM
for the closing notes.
Thank you.