Okay. So, hi everyone. Thank you for being here and joining us for this presentation
about how to improve your SEO with Matomo. We're going to be two people here today. There
is Thomas Zeithamel from Germany. Hi Thomas. Hi, thank you. And myself, Jean-Marc Courtiard
from France. And we are very happy to be here and share with you how we use Matomo to improve
our SEO strategies and tactics. And as you can see, we've been working in SEO for a few
years now, for something like 20 years, and very happy to use Matomo for this as well.
And so now what we're going to do during this session is to first introduce why SEO can
be used with Matomo, how you can use Matomo for your SEO, and this, and go through the
different tools and tactics that you can use to improve your SEO with Matomo. And the way
we see it is that Matomo is some kind of a new tool for most of SEO practitioners most
of the time. And so this presentation is addressed to them, I mean, to SEO professionals who've
been working with Google Analytics for a long time and want to move to Matomo to increase
their potential or also to, they have to move to it because the clients are using now Matomo
and they have to get their hands into it. And I also, we both use Matomo for SEO, and
we know many people in this arena, and now everybody's switching a lot to Matomo, which
is grant. And so this presentation is for them, but it's also for Matomo consultants
who are maybe interested in SEO like this, and as well for curious people, if you want
to know more how to use Matomo and SEO altogether. And yeah, and one of the things which is very
important is that we will see how to use Matomo for your SEO. And in the case of SEO tactics
and how you can do some recurring follow up, how you can measure technical content or net
linking fields and tasks with Matomo. And it's also intended to work with SEO audits
consultants who need very deep technical information to carry on their audits. And so this presentation
is shared in three parts. The first one being the new data points in Matomo. The second
is how to use plugins with Matomo to improve your SEO. And the last one is about reporting.
Now let's move on to the first point, which is the new data points in Matomo. And Thomas
is going to take this point now.
Thank you, Jean-Marc. I hope you'll see my screen now. Yes, new data points for SEO.
Why is it important? So the first is that we have some metrics for SEO, for example,
the keywords, the visitor sources, and also many metrics we measure with the Matomo systems
and it's important for SEO. For example, the bounce rate or the time on site, it's depends
or is a factor in the, for example, in the Panda updates in Google. So we will pay attention
to this metrics, but it would be better when you can combine Matomo with your data-driven
SEO. I think we have many, many tasks we will think about it. For example, Google is taken
to a mobile first approach in 2018. So I think it's very interesting to check up how is the
behavior of your mobile users and so on to dedicate the duplicate content or think content
is very interesting for SEO because you want to indicate the poor quality sites and also
the user behavior in time on site, bounce rate, page impressions, all this are factors
for Google, which you can also measure with the Google Chrome browser. So what I want
you to tell why we don't, why we do need more data points in this is that we can make a
better data-driven SEO with Matomo. So you have the slides after this presentation, you
can download it and see it. I think it's the entry point. It's not so important what I
talk about, but what I think is very important that you must use data points or they're using
no data points because you want to see something in Matomo, which you can help to improve your
SEO. For example, look for mobile-friendly issues. So we have content tracking in this
case, so we can decide if a viewport is seeing this content log or not and so on. Ability
the usability backs, for example, also in some differences about the mobile version
or the desktop version. So we can measure this data in Matomo and you can build segments
to switch and compare this information. Find important blogs, which are seen very often
or identify the operation errors on something else. And the most part of finding the most
part of SEO in my SEO audits by using Matomo is to find thin content. So that's the reason
I want to do data points in Matomo. So we have three sources which are very underrated
and it's in the Matomo standard. You don't need any new plugins or something else. It's
in the standard. You can use it anymore, but you will setting up this information. So the
first is the custom dimension. You must switch the plugin on and you can use it. You have
five custom dimensions per visit or per action on the sites. You have events. You can tracking
some click events, scrolling and so on. Or for example, the content viewing. In the content
tracking, you can measure the views and the interactions on specific elements, for example,
the footer or something else. So these three are very important and underrated factors
to improve your SEO. First, the custom dimension. With the custom dimension, you can give some
information from your content management system to Matomo. And it's very useful to give more
data to Matomo, which you can split and make in the reports and you can segment this data
and so on. And for example, I have many helpful SEO metrics I can transport to Matomo. And
this information, you can read it out of your page or something else. For example, the helpful
dimensions are the release date. Why it's important. With the release date, you can
see when you have a new article on your blog, for example, you can see, oh, in the first
three, two, three months, it's very valuable. It's very high traffic site or something,
but the interest goes going down. And you can think about it. If it maybe you have duplicate
content problems or something, you can switch it to a no index page or the site type. You
can say, for example, this is a product page and what the bounce rate on all the product
pages in the in comparison of the category pages or something else. Also structures,
data, departments, page regions. So I think it's very useful that you use the dimensions.
So you can add the dimension in the admin interface in Matomo and you should give the
information over, for example, a push to Matomo in the tech manager, for example. So, and
there are some other information you can give to Matomo or can transport it. The SEO metrics,
which are very helpful for a better understanding of the problem of issues of something else,
which can help you to make a good SEO audit for your site. So, for example, the count
of headlines when you see, oh, I have 20 headlines on a site. You can think about it or the content
length. I mean, not the content length with all the HTML, but I think about the word counts.
I have an example for you. By using the tech manager, you can create a variable and you
can parse the complete HTML source. And I have to write a little script. Maybe you can
do it better, but it can be a help that we can count the words in the content. So in
the first step, I extract only the content in the main content. And this in a HTML, I
remove the HTML and count the words. For better reading in Matomo, I make a range of about
50 to make an arrangement that I can read it better. That's quite a little script, which
I use in the tech manager that I can transport the information, how many words on my content
site to Matomo. How does it look like? This is an example. You see, I have many sites
with 350 words or 500 words or 450 words. And in the dimensions, you can drill down
and see, for example, the information about the bounce rate. And when I use the plus symbol,
I can switch and see every URL and I see every bounce rate or the double times on a time
on site on every URL. And in this case, I see, oh, I have only three or five words in
this case, but I see the double times on this site are 50 minutes or 30 minutes or 20 minutes.
So many content, 450 words, it's not so, but maybe some images there and also, but I have
one, which is a breaker. It's only seven seconds on the site. And I can see, oh, it's maybe
there are some potential problems with the site. And that's the reason I use it for example,
to find thin contents, to find a site with low content or with not so many content that
Google can build a relevance to some search phrases.
And if I can add a few things, a few words about what you're doing here with this script,
it's very interesting because in this case, it means that you can do this directly in
Matomo instead of having to crawl the website and to cross the data with your Matomo or
former Google Analytics instance information.
Yes. And you see it only for the sites which are also visited. So it's one of a big part
in SEO audits is when you use a crawler and you have a 1 million page crawl, 1 million
are not visited at any time. So you have only 2,000, 3,000 sites which are visited and disinformations
about bounce rate or time on site are only measured in some analytics systems.
So the next part is that also underrated are the events. So GR4 is moving to track all
with events. But also in Matomo, it's not so very often, but we have it. We have events
and we can split it into, I think, two sections. For the first time, the technical issues.
Maybe you have a 404 site. Please don't forget to move when you have raised the error or
see it on the page. Maybe you have a 404 page that you also triggered an event that he said,
oh, there's a 404 error occurred. Or 500 mistakes and so on. Or no results pages if you have
no values for the search, for the internal search. And we have events on the page side.
So it's, for example, if your content is read. Yeah. So you also can events and events, for
example, the scroll def or something else. You can also measure this points. Or if when
we can read in the RTML source, for example, if a product is sold out, so it's not available,
for example, you can send it also to as an event to Matomo and see how often does it
appear. Yeah. And also click events. And also in this, I have a tip for you to build a big
measuring plan because it's very important that you use, in this case, you use for SEO
so many events you want to see. For example, when you want some arguments which you want
to improve your SEO and you will say, it's not needed to have this read more button.
We only need the first link. It's the title link with some relevant info for the target
page and read more is not a very good anchor text. So you can remove it because you have
to data and say, oh, just the title clicked a thousand times and read more button is clicked
only 10 times. So you have more or the better SEO argument for your presentation, for your
information, for your, for your better argument for your implementation of your SEO tactics
or SEO improvement. Yeah. So I think it's very important. Also similar products. Yeah.
If there is clicks on the similar products in a product page, you can see, oh, we have
thousand product page insights and we have some, some similar products on the side, but
nobody click it. Maybe it's not relevant enough. Maybe we should change the strategy. Maybe
the, the, the, the, yeah, the, the, the output is not so really good. Maybe the place is
not the right place and so on and so on. And so you can say, let us test us if it is better
in this form or this, and you can take many of this data to improve your SEO arguments.
So this I have for, for example, we have a carrier portal and we want to see how people
are switching from carrier section to the normal company side. And also I can see how
many people are switching from one point to another point and have measured this with
the events. Yeah. And to see how the people are interacting and can say, did we need a
normal site or did we follow the siloing navigation, for example. So it can be very helpful. The
next part also is like the event tracking is the content tracking. Yeah. So for it's,
for me, it's very important that I see how the headline structure is, is in the document
and the headline structure can be good to see, or if you can use this to find non-use
elements or for a better understanding how the site is, the navigation is on the site,
the scroll teeth or something else. And it's in the content tracking, it's very hard for
me and many times with my customers to implement the section. So, and this is also a good point
that we can use the tech manager at the moment. So the tech manager also, I have the custom
HTML and can use a script and the script does nothing else. I only get all the H2 or headline
two format. And on this headline two format, I give the information. What is the headline
in text? So I see every headline and I give the URL also as the content piece to Matomo.
And when you use this script, all your headlines with the headline two format will report to
Matomo which blog is seen or not seen. And it's very interesting because you can see,
you have to write order on the site and you can see, for example, we have 900 page impressions
and the navigation is seen 880 times and part of the website analysis are seen only 500
times and so on and so on. And you can drill down and see what is, which element is all
also seen or in the viewport. It's very interesting to see this information for a special landing
page, for example, and help you to make your SEO better. And the next in the content tracking
is also the footer, measure the footer. It's the best tip, I think, because everybody who
read the content, when he read it to the end, then the footer is displayed in the viewport.
And you can say it's not really the 100% but much part of all the users which see the content
footer, see the footer, are reading the content to the end. And you can say I have 100 page
impressions but only 10 users see the footer and it gives you a little bit of understanding
how many users read this content until the end. And don't forget segments. So segments
are a very useful part in Matomo and you can say, for example, dividing the devices, the
goals, the channels, the user type, if new user or a queuing user. You can with the comparison
of this, you can find more issues which can help you to make your site better. For example,
if your site is mobile-friendly, you build a segment with the mobile users and you use
a segment with the desktop users and make a comparison of this. And when you see all
the usability values in the time on site or the bounce rate is very different, then you
can see maybe it's some mobile-friendly issues or usability issues or maybe on many sites
we have hidden content. And in the Google search essentials, it's the new declaration
of the Google Webmaster guidelines. It's also a part in it that you say we have read the
hidden content, yes, but we also make some relevance to it, but how many we don't know.
But it's very interesting to see if there are difference about the mobile section and
the desktop section. And you can see how the site will be navigation and so on parts in
your site. So a little summary for this section, dimensions, events, and the content measurement
can help you for your SEO decisions because you have the data and can say this is the
reason why you have SEO arguments for your decisions or you can make things. You can
find also potential. You can find the content. You can find something else here. You can
find problems with the usability and so on. You have better argumentation for the implementation
of SEO tests or something else because you have the data then you can measure these values
in Matomo. And at last, you can also monitor your SEO measurements. So another trick, dimensions
you use, for example, you can import. John Mark is telling you about this plugin, but
you can take your search engine keywords to resolve the not provided solution. But on
this you can see how many people are, for example, using the CTR. And you can change
your title. You can change your description and see it how it works on the high traffic
sites. And high traffic sites means that you have many page impressions. And you can see
also if the bounce rate is going up or down where you take some changes. So I think I
hope this was very helpful for you. It's a part of mine. And now go back to John Mark.
Yeah, thank you, Thomas. This is indeed very interesting. When we built this presentation,
there are many things we were discussing. And this was, yeah, all these parts are very
interesting as it's most of the time we undervalue the Matomo or the, I mean, the analytic solution
to proceed with SEO. And in this case, we can see that there are so many, many features
in Matomo that can help you so much. And yeah, it was a pleasure to discuss this. By the
way, is my sound okay? Or is there still a problem with it? Because we had a problem
with it.
Yes, I think it's perfect. Yes.
Okay, cool. Thanks. And by the way, one small digression. I would like to thank Ronan Chardonnay
because he's the one who introduced us together and said, maybe you could do some presentation
altogether with this SEO theme. So yeah, that's great. Now let's share my screen and let's
move on to this second part of this presentation, which is plugins.
These plugins in Matomo are a very powerful way to get even in-depth information about
your SEO and about many, many things. They really extend the functionalities of Matomo.
If you take, for instance, WordPress, you can take WordPress.org and you get plugins
on your WordPress.org, I mean, on your self-hosted WordPress. And it's the same in here. You
can get even more functionalities with these plugins, which is something that doesn't exist
in the Google Analytics one.
So now let's start with custom reports. And one catch about this, the custom reports is
a functionality which at first was already present in Google Analytics. In this case,
in Matomo, it depends on the instance that you take. Whether it's on-premise, you have
to pay for it, or whether it's Matomo Cloud. And in this case, it's included in your Matomo
instance. So the custom reports are just like what you already know. I mean, they help you
to get to cross dimensions, I mean, several dimensions and several metrics altogether
so that you can get even more complete, comprehensive information regarding what you want to do.
So this is what we can do here with SEO. For instance, you can try to figure out which
page URL and page title have altogether. You can check traffic or engagement figures, KPIs
altogether with all this stuff. And we can check this out just like quickly. I mean,
I won't share this now because I guess it's going to shut down. You won't see my screen
anymore. But we will, I guess, let this link here. And by the way, the link is basically
the Matomo demo site. And if you go on Matomo demo, just search this on your favorite search
engine and you will find the demo site of Matomo. And just go to custom reports, which
is at the bottom of the interface. And as I said, there is a price for it. I mean, it's
included in the cloud, but you have to pay for it if you want to get it on-premise or
for WordPress. And one trick about that is that this custom reports, it's a small digression
by the way, this custom reports plugin helps you get information, but it takes the data
from the moment you have created your custom report. So if you want to get data back from
an historical point of view, you have to use another plugin, which is called Invalid Reports.
Here it is. And in this case, Matomo will calculate again all these reports regarding
your historical data. The other plugin that we mentioned here is the User Flow. As practitioners
of analytics, you obviously know this kind of plugin, I mean, this kind of functionality.
In this case, it's a plugin. And the way we use it with SEO is that when we use it with
a segment, it's very important to use it with a segment obviously. If you want to get your
organic search information, you will see where people come from, and you see here in red
the drop of people from one part of your website to another part, another part, another part.
And this is where you can think about, okay, there is a problem with this part, and this
is where people come from, etc. I mean, this is something that you already know if you've
been doing analytics for a while, so I won't talk too much about it, but I would say it's
pretty obvious. And there is another plugin that looks a bit like this. We will talk about
this later. It's called Transition, and it looks pretty similar to it, but it goes even
more deeper. It goes deeper into this. And the User Flow is, again, included in the Matomo
Cloud instance, and you have to pay for it if you want, as it's a plugin, if you want
to use it on-premise. And as I said, you have to use it with SEO organic search segments.
And one thing we'll catch about the segments is that they are not created out of the box,
not available out of the box when you're using Matomo. What happens is that you have to create
them. So when you create your instance in Matomo, and here in this case, I'm talking
to people who don't know Matomo yet and want to use it for their SEO, you have to create
this segment, your organic segment, directly, very quickly, so that you can get information
about your organic search traffic. Now, let's move on to another plugin, which is called
Search Engine Keywords Performance. So this one looks like this. You have many, many tables
and graphics and graphs, et cetera. It's a very, again, powerful tool. Thomas, you mentioned
it before, and the point of this tool is that you will connect your Google Search Console
or Bing Webmaster Tools or Yahoo or Yandex to Matomo. And Matomo will grab the data from
those tools through their respective APIs and get them into your Matomo. And what is
interesting about that is that you will get the same information than those you get into,
for instance, Search Console, the keywords, CTR, et cetera, et cetera, given that not
every information is available in those tools. We know that, for instance, Search Console
doesn't show you every keyword which are used by people to access your website. But anyway,
this is what you're going to get. And you're going to get also information about images,
you know, on Google Images or Google Videos, for instance, as well, and also the information
that you would get in Google Search Console regarding the Googlebot crawling accesses,
et cetera, the errors and everything. And what is good to know is that what is good
about this plugin is that you will keep an historical data recording of your Search Console
directly into your Matomo instance, which is great because in this case, you can get
like many years of a Search Console information if needed, given that you won't maybe need
something like two years of information for two years ago. But I guess that's okay. And
yeah, I think that's okay. But just one thing is just one catch, again, is that it does
not allow to match visitors to request. So in this case, Matomo doesn't do that, which
is a bit tricky somehow. But that's the way it works. So you don't get sometimes all the
information to get everything but visits with the visitors, right? And yeah, again, it's
included in the Matomo cloud. And it's a yeah, you have to pay for it if you want to get
it into your instance. But it's great. In this case, the third plugin we will talk about
is as your Web Vitals. Okay, so I'm rushing a bit in this case. So this but I think it's
important if we if we have Q&A. So this third plugin is about to get information regarding
your performance. You know, we talked about Web Vitals about Google putting this up to
the front. And in this case, this is how you can measure your performance with with Matomo.
What this plugin will do is that it will connect to your Google page speed insight API and
gather data regarding the five top traffic relevant pages on your website. Otherwise,
we take a lot of data regarding the API. And if you don't want this to be too heavy, you
have to focus on the five top pages. Anyway, you can also add more pages manually to your
instance. This is written here. It's possible to choose specific pages. And yeah, that's
great tool. And it's a bit like what we find in screaming fraud when we want to get data
from screaming fraud and cross cross them with Google page speed insight. And this is
how then you that you can measure your your performances, you will get every information
regarding your the API, etc. And all the other everything that makes your website slow and
then you can improve the best the best pages and the top traffic driven pages. Okay. I
don't know if somebody's got questions about this, by the way. Okay. Oh, it's fine. Yeah.
Okay. And now let's move on to the reporting. Okay. The Matomo you have many functionalities
to get reportings. One thing, though, it's that Matomo is not probably the yet the best
solution to get data visualization. We have to be fair about this, I guess. But there
are still many, many things you can do within it. And the point of this, of this part of
the presentation is to show you the native reports, data visualization tools that you
get and also the the other functionalities and plug in data visualization functionalities
as well. Okay, bye. At first, we can mention the segments. We talked about this many times.
These slides just to show you how to create a segment with the organic search in Matomo.
You have to choose the channel type and go to search. And this is how you're going to
get your organic search like you used to do in previous in previous analytic tools. Then
there is the acquisition channels. In this case, you can get just like you used to do
in all the solutions, the acquisition channels being spread around and taken apart. I mean,
breaking, sorry, broken down in depending if it's search engine, direct traffic, etc.
referrals, etc. And which is it's something that is obviously important when you want
to measure your SEO performances compared to the other channels, which are driving traffic
to your website. There's also what I mentioned before, the transitions, the transitions are
a way to get information regarding where people come from, where people come from on your
website. I mean, the incoming traffic regarding the different channels. And you can see where
how many people have stayed on the website and where they went and how many have went.
I've quit your website on certain pages. And this is it's very malleable. I mean, you can
change the page URL, the URL, the titles, etc. and see where people come from, from
certain search engines and then go to certain pages, etc. All right. I'm hurrying up. It's
almost done. We also get, just like in Google Analytics, the site search. It's a relevant
tool to get information about what people are interested in and are looking for on your
website. And again, you can get all this information here, like all the terms they've been looking
for and on which page. And there are also other tools that you can use to see your data.
In this case, you have the landing page report. It's something that I use a lot when I do
SEO audit, because in this case, you can get the landing pages where people arrive on which
page they arrive on your website. And it's something you can find again in Matomo. There
is duplicate title. Again, you can see this and see if you have any problems with the
titles. And this goes, again, with the parts that Tomas mentioned before and about the
H1, 2, etc. It's everything in here is complimentary to get your technical SEO proper. There are
also Google Search Console information, as we mentioned before in the search engine keywords
performance plugin and SEO Web Vitals, again, in this. You can get as well to make something
very practical, broken links or 404 or 500 errors on your website using exactly the search
engine keywords performance plugin in the crawl errors. And in this case, we have the
screenshot of the demo site of Matomo, where you can see that you can get all these 404
errors on the website. And that's great, because in this case, you can quickly wear there.
And finally, the data export. And it's very important to mention that Matomo has extensive
or comprehensive data export features. In this case, you can export your information
with as CSV files or CSV for Excel, XML, but also JSON, HTML, RSS. Yeah, RSS looks pretty
cool because you can get information on the web page. I mean, using a plugin on RSS client,
for instance. And you can do many, many things. And obviously, it's very important to do that.
I mean, to export your data into your own tools. And in this case, if you export data
on your own in a spreadsheet, it's obvious that you have to manage them a bit. It's like
what you get from other tools. And you have to make sure that you have to change a bit
the layout of the information to make them more relevant, to change the colors, delete
certain columns, just like you would do in Screaming Frog or maybe with Google Analytics.
And you also have to change the average time spent. Because, for instance, in this case,
this time is measured in seconds. So you have to do some calculations to get it in minutes
by the time. You can also export your data to Data Studio, which is very important. We
have customers who are very data-driven. I mean, they use Data Studio a lot. By the way,
the name has changed a few days ago. And now, OK, anyway, there is a plugin for that. You
have to pay for it every month. And you can give them your data from Matomo into Data
Studio. It's important. You can also use spreadsheets like Google Sheets, for instance, or LibreOffice
Calc to get data. But I will mention this here directly with the API. And there are
also dedicated dashboards in Matomo. It's a very important feature. And in this case,
you can get all the data you want to measure, especially for your SEO, and compare the bounce
rates, et cetera, the evolution, where people are coming from, through widgets that you
can get into your Matomo. And I'm hurrying up again about this stuff. Yeah, a few insights
to create your dashboards here. Well, you have to create general dashboards and also
data-driven SEO dashboards in this case. And yeah, that's pretty obvious. And more functionalities.
Well, here, in this case, we have covered only a few functionalities of Matomo regarding
your SEO. And what's important to know is that you have no sampling in Matomo unless
you need it in very specific situations. But by default, you have all the data you need
to carry in your calculations. You also get your own data. It's your own data, which is
very, very important to me, so that you can get them, and keep them, and do whatever you
want with it. And you can also draw information from Universal
Analytics. You can get them from Universal Analytics into Matomo to get your historical
data. You won't get everything, but it's good to mention that you can do that. And the last
thing is that you can also use the log import feature. I will give a presentation in 15
minutes on this same channel. And it's also something that is interesting from an SEO
perspective. OK, so sorry. Thank you. Any question? After we are a bit late, but that's
OK. OK. Thank you very much, Thomas and Hedger
Ma. Can you hear me? Yes, yes, yes.
OK, great. I'm currently looking at the chat to see if there's any questions from the audience.
I wrote nine of them, so I'm just going to ask them to you quickly, even though on the
chat it's true that we already think about potential. And so I really would like to thank
what's more the Matomo community for playing the game and answering to the questions of
the different people. So the first question is, but you somehow answered it within the
conferences. Are you using metadata such as the word numbers per page by using custom
dimension to analyze SEO? So you already answered to it, so to say. But sorry for this question.
Do you do it for real with your client? OK, that's that's my question, because from what
we could see from the outside, it's like it means in terms of database, it means a new
call, every new page which is loaded. So let's imagine that we collect metadata, the number
of words on the page and so on and so on. We may have actually too much data collected
to Matomo that we were not collecting before, or even some additional scripts which are
running in the background and making the pages slow to load. I just like to know your position
about this. I can answer. I think it's my part. No, it's I think it's not a hard load
because the whole dimensional thing is tracked before. You set the track page view to Matomo.
So you can collect the data and send it with a stack to Matomo at one time. And I think,
for example, to get the main content words, it's a millisecond procedure which are taken.
But it maybe makes sense that when you use the tech manage, you can also switching this
and can say I only sent this tracker for partial size or partial size or for a side region
or something else when the load is too heavy. So you can decide to change in the trigger,
for example, only on Wednesday or something else. So you can reduce the, but it's important
that you measure this data to see you make zero tests because why it's important. In
many cases, it's my problem. I have so many feelings in my stomach and say, oh, no, that's
a bad side or that's a bad idea to make this. And with the data you measure with Matomo,
you can say, okay, we can test it. We change the title, we change the headlines, we replace
this part of site and so on. And for me, it's very, I lost the screaming frog, but it's
only a problem because Google can only measure these values for my site when the sites are
also with it. So when you say cross and say this page is very low, but it's no value site,
nobody with it decides, I think it's not a really bad, really, really great problem for
your site. When you have 5 million sites and you have only 2000, it's more important that
you get, for example, the web hotels for this with the sites to bring it up. Yeah. And not
for the thin content sites or structure sites, which you have on the site.
Okay. Perfect. Thank you, Romain. Sure. I still have eight questions left. Next question
is about, do you have any solutions when it comes to measure the number of backlinks pointing
to a specific domain in order to store this value within Matomo? So I get that you get
the sense of the question is that we can get the number of referrals, but when it comes
to backlinks, so to say, adding a link pointing to a website, those are collected by third
party services such as Google Search Console or SEMrush or whatever. And have you ever
heard of a solution or have you ever thought about the solution in order to store this
data within the database as a plugin or whatever? Yes. I also, another baby, I learned in 20
years of SEO that the best backlinks are backlinks with real users. So my tip on this is build
a segment with the entry page of which site you will see. And you can say entry page contains,
for example, the site or is the site and then go onto referrals and we'll see all this referral
information about which sites. The problem is that the Chrome browser, for example, didn't
give you the information for the detailed site, which the backlink is stored. So the
problem is that we can, many times we get only the domain name. That's the problem.
So I think Matomo and also Google Analytics or other tools has a problem that the browsers
are not sharing this information anymore in this detailed data. So I think the best alternatives
are majestic SEO, Aharef and so on. And you can combine the sites and see which sites
are visited and which backlinks are bringing you no visitors. Yeah, I totally agree. These
aren't dedicated tools for that purpose. And they have a lot of financial means and technical
means to gather that. So yeah, obviously, you have to use those external tools. I haven't
found anything yet that can match this. Okay, sorry. Just a silly, loud talk, but couldn't
we imagine a custom dimension at the referral level? I mean, the fact that so as the action
level or visit level, we would have it at the referral level on which we could send
different values, just the authority of the link, such as the trust level or that kind
of thing. Sounds actually interesting. That was just a silly thought, but I was thinking
that, okay, maybe, maybe, okay. Next question is about, in your presentation, you showed
it was possible to measure 500 error messages, which are several ones. And I wanted to know
if the way you measure it is by log import, or do you use another method? And if it's
another method, how do you do so? Because it seems like super complicated to implement
compared to measuring another front page. Yes, the easiest way is on a pepcheap world.
When you have a pepcheap web server, you can say the hearty access, you can say, for example,
error document 500, and you can give error site to the CMS. And on this CMS site, it
can play in heart email, and you can integrate the source, the tracking code into it. That's
the easiest way to measure the 500 sites. Wow, super clear. Thank you. Next question
is, is there any improvement you wish Matomo to have in order to analyze better SEO? So
you show us SEO Web Vitals, which is like the last plugin that the Matomo team developed.
But are there any room for improvement that you can see for SEO?
Well, yes, but maybe not directly into Matomo. What I wish could be done is that we can have
access, I mean, tools like SEMrush or Screaming Frog could get you an access to Matomo, so
that you can cross your Matomo instance data with SEMrush, just like you do with Google
Analytics right now, or with Screaming Frog, by the way. I've sent them a few tweets about
that. And yeah, they said they're interested, but yeah, I guess it takes time to develop
this kind of feature. And no worries, guys, by the way. And yeah, this is what I think
could be great, that we can get all the kind of access we had before with these kind of
tools. Yeah, directly into Matomo.
Okay, so it will be more like an API discussing with SEMrush, for example, just exporting
some configuration we made in SEMrush in order to get the less data for competitors or the
list of the backlinks, that kind of thing.
It goes in both directions. I mean, to get the first thing is that when you connect to
your SEMrush account and create a project that you can get, you can connect your SEMrush
project to your Matomo instance, so that your traffic data goes into SEMrush and you can
compare things. And also that you can get all as well data from SEMrush into Matomo.
But this is about developing plugins. And yeah, it takes time and money.
Okay. Next question is more linked to what you just said, Jean-Marc. Do you identify
potential bridges between bots such as Screaming Frog and Matomo in order to populate Matomo
with some data? I'm mostly thinking of the number of pages listed in Matomo might be
different for the number of pages that we really have on the website. And yeah, do you
identify possibility here? Maybe you can tell us a bit more about what you discussed with
Screaming Frog though.
Yeah. Okay. So in five minutes, I'm going to do the other section. But yeah, but I see
yes, about the Screaming Frog. Not too sure. Yeah, not too sure about that actually.
Yeah. No, no, no worries.
That's how good bots are. Matomo is actual is a bot tracking prevention. It's also there
you can spam reference and you have all those functions also plug in for the port tracker,
which only working. But if JavaScript is disabled, for example, many bots have no JavaScript,
but this bots which have JavaScript and very good implemented, you cannot see if it is
a bot or not. You can see it on your actions in the, in the, in the visitor log, for example,
that the bot is really plump calling every new file every second, for example, and you
can whistle segments, you can say, okay, this information, then.
Okay. Yes. Yeah. What I wanted to say, sorry, I was focusing on the other position just
before that. So I didn't say anyway. And yeah, that's a that's one part. But the other thing
you can do is again to import data from your logs, and you can get this information you
want.
Okay.
A quick one for Thomas is knowing Matomo is a key success factor when it comes to sell
SEO services in Germany.
Sorry, I understand it. Let's let's say that you are providing SEO services in Germany
is having some knowledge in terms of analyzing data with Matomo is a key success factor to
win a contract. Or do most of companies in Germany, they don't care. Either you use Matomo
or Google Analytics. And if you are not a Matomo expert, it doesn't really matter.
That's a difficult question, because we see that more and more shops, for example, switching
to Matomo I have in Germany, I have, for example, Siemens, VB, it's big, big brands, which are
switching to Matomo. And so also e commerce shops, and Red Bull is also moving to Matomo
and so on. And when you know Google Analytics, you find very easily some statistics in Matomo
also.
And I think for reporting, it's very interesting, because GR4 is standing out next year. And
we don't have a bounce rate, for example, in GRV at the moment, maybe they implemented,
but say they plan to organize all those events. But you have a bounce rate, you have to page
overview, what you see is every URL in Google Analytics and see how many side impressions
I have. And this is removing in Google Analytics fall. And so you have with Matomo alternatives
that you can see your old reports, which you can give it more. And I think it's, it's more
and more agencies in Germany are setting up a Matomo and also work with this. In Germany,
it's also some good, some big seminar, one to one, but it's also from Alexander Hollis,
it's a very big training courses, which is also Google Analytics. And they set up with
me a Matomo solution for this.
Okay, guys, I have been pinged many times on the chat in order to close the discussion.
I really hope, first of all, thank you very much. Thank you very much for suggesting this
presentation to do it in duo. So the different nationalities coming together, sharing expertise,
that's really great. And also maybe next year, we could find you for the V2 of this conference
or maybe addressing the search engine dotizing part, because it's true that could be as well
subject to another big talk. We would like to thank you on small and all the best remark
for your next talk. Close the room now. All the best. I invite you to answer the remaining
questions on the chat. Have a great afternoon. Bye.
Thank you. Bye. See you. Good luck, Mark.