Hi there, everybody. How are you? I hope you're doing well. So my name is Boris, and today
we're going to go over how we can have our own Matomo instance. I'm sure we have heard
a lot of positive things about it during MatomoCam. And so I wanted to host a workshop on how
everyone can install their own Matomo instance. Now, when we want to have a Matomo instance
up and running, the first thing we will need will be to have a computer to run it. So we'll
also go over where you can find different providers, and I'll try to make it as easy
to follow. But in case anybody has questions during the workshop, please feel free to write
in the chat, and I'll do my best to explain everything to you.
So before we dive into Matomo, first I would like to introduce myself. So as I mentioned,
my name is Boris. I am based in Albania, which is located in Europe, and I have been contributing
to different open source projects for around six years now. I am a member of the local
hackerspace, open the apps hackerspace, and I also am part of cloud68.co, where what we
do is we maintain different open source instances like Matomo, for example, where we not only
install them, but we make sure there are backups, monitoring for the health of the service,
and provide support. So I think that's a pretty good beginning introduction about myself.
So without further ado, I would like to get into how you can have your own Matomo instance.
So for the guide, I have estimated that our Matomo instance should be able to handle around
100,000 visits, and that is based off the official documentation from the Matomo website.
Of course, as you scale up, you might need a different setup to accommodate for all the
traffic that you're going to be having. So as I was mentioning, the first thing we're
going to need is a computer, or more specifically, what we need is a server. That way, when somebody
goes to the URL for our Matomo site, they will be able to see the website. And there
are a couple of different providers. One of the first things you need to keep in mind
is, if you're doing a setup similar to what we're going to do, you need to be aware of
where most of your user visits are going to be from, because the closer the server is
to your users, the faster it will load. If I am in Europe and I try to access a server,
for example, in Asia, it might be much slower to load compared to a server that's in Germany.
So one of the providers I highly recommend usually is Hetzner. They offer dedicated servers,
but they also offer virtual private servers. And the difference in that explained very
briefly is that with a VPS or a virtual private server, you essentially get a small chunk
of a physical machine. And you can install whatever you want on it. It has its own operating
system, and it's quite easy to add more hardware to it. Whereas compared with a dedicated server,
you have a lot more hardware and computing power allocated to it, but it does require
more maintenance because you have to look out for stuff like hard drive failures or
RAM corruption, and you have to constantly monitor it. So in Hetzner, the virtual private
server section, they call it Hetzner Cloud, and they have pretty good beginning prices.
So for a Matomo instance of about 100,000 users, something like the CX11 tier, which
has one CPU core and two gigabytes of RAM is a good start. And if you essentially use
all of that computing power, you can just upgrade to the next plan and downgrade later
on down the line. Another popular provider is DigitalOcean. The good thing about DigitalOcean
is that it has a lot more data centers compared to Hetzner. So Hetzner only has data centers
in Europe. And yesterday or the day before that, they launched a new data center in the
US, but DigitalOcean has data centers in a couple of US cities in Europe, as well as
in Asia. So if you're outside of Europe, I will highly recommend checking out DigitalOcean.
Another popular provider is also Linode, which is fairly similar to DigitalOcean. You can
of course use Amazon Web Services and Google Cloud Platform. I personally don't use them
because I don't agree with essentially their ethics. Google, Amazon, and other big tech
companies have been known to not be the most privacy respecting companies out there. So
I try to stay away from them, but of course you are free to host them wherever you want.
Okay, so in preparation for today's workshop, I have already created a server on Hetzner.
And the domain for that, I am going to paste it in the chat really quickly, will be matamotest.cloud68.co.
If you go to that URL, you will not see anything load. And that's because nothing has been
set up yet. So give me a bit of time to share my screen. And I think you should be able
to see it now. Let me just make it a bit bigger so that you can see. If the screen size, the
font size is too small, please let me know and I'll increase it. Okay, so first thing
you are going to want to do is to connect to that server. And for that, we use SSH.
So this is a command that lets you connect to the server as root, which is a user that
can perform, can execute all the commands on the server, which will be very helpful
during installation, but it's usually recommended to not run commands as root. So now we are
inside the server. And you can see that because here it says root at matamotest, whereas before
it was saying Boris at whatever my computer name is. Okay, first thing you do after connecting
to a new server will be to make sure that it's up to date with the latest version because
packages come out all the time. So new software comes out all the time. And since this computer
will be publicly accessed, we want to make sure it's up to date so that it's more secure.
So this is running Ubuntu 18. And to update the packages, we have to run two commands.
The first one will be apt update. And this essentially just refreshes the list of new
software, but it doesn't actually install them. So if we let it finish real quick, there
we go. It says that three packages can be upgraded. And to upgrade them, what we have
to do is we will have to run apt upgrade in this case. So let's just confirm that we indeed
want to update. Okay, there we go. So now what we have to do is we are going to have
to install some other software to make sure that, you know, if you go to that URL that
I shared in the chat, Matomo shows up and your browser knows how to interact with this
computer. So the different components that we need installed are mainly a web server,
which is a program installed on the server so that your browser knows how to talk to
it. We'll need a database. So this is where Matomo will store all the data that it collects.
And for this guide, we will be using something called MySQL. Of course, you are free to use
whatever you want, as long as the program is compatible with it. And the last thing
we're going to need to install will be the PHP softwares into the server. So Matomo is
written in PHP. And for that reason, we need to make sure that the server itself can run
this program and then serve that on your browser. Okay, so to install the web server, it's really,
really easy. Using the apt command from before, we're going to tell it to install, and then
we're going to say the name of the program that we want to install. In the case of the
web server, we're going to be using something called Nginx. Another very popular option
is Apache 2. But there are a couple more you might want to dive into at your own leisure.
And other than Nginx, we are also going to install MySQL server. So this is the web server,
and this is the database server. Let's just run that really quickly.
Now when it comes to PHP installation, you can use different versions of PHP. Matomo
itself recommends using PHP 7.2 or up. For this guide, we'll be using PHP 7.4. So the
problem then becomes that PHP 7.4 is not available by default, I think, in Ubuntu 18.04. So we
have to add something called a repository, which is like a list of other packages or
other programs that you can install on your computer that are not available by default.
So to do that, what we first have to run is this command, which installs some, it's essentially
the apt command again, but it installs some background applications needed to follow the
other steps. And we can see in this case, because it didn't say installing anything
new, it was already present in my installation. Okay. Now we are going to run another command,
which is add apt repository. So essentially add a new list of possible programs that you
can install. And then the repository that we're going to be installing is Andre slash
PHP. So if we press enter on that, it will warn us with things that we need to keep in
mind of, and then it will ask us to press enter to continue. So we're going to do that.
And here you can see that it's updating the list of programs. So these are what it had
by default. And then you can see here what we just added. Okay. Now we can run the step
to install PHP 7.4. So let's go ahead and do that. I am going to be installing a version
of PHP 7.4 called FPM. So let's press enter on that. And let's just give it a little bit
of time to configure everything. Okay. So now we are pretty much almost ready to continue
with a Matomo installation, but PHP in Ubuntu 18 comes with what are called modules. So
these are optional softwares that you install on your computer and they provide more functions
to PHP. If you head over to the Matomo user installation guide, so let me get that link
and paste it in the chat really quickly. So in here you will see that the recommendation
is to install a bunch of packages. I have written them down beforehand. And what we're
going to do is we're going to install them, but we want to make sure that we install the
same version for the module as we did for PHP when we initially installed it here. So
I said 7.4 and I have to make sure that in here it also says 7.4. So let's go ahead and
press enter on that. And let's give it a bit of time. There we go. Now we are ready to
download the Matomo code from Matomo's website. So let me reshare my screen really quickly.
I think it's this one. Yeah. Okay. So let's open that in fuller view. What we're going
to want to do is we're going to want to go to the download Matomo section and we can
see that the latest release is version 4.5.0. And we're going to want to right click this
button over here. And we're going to want to copy the link. Now let's jump back into
the server. So let me share my screen one more time. Okay. And let's make it a bit easier
to read by removing all of these things. If you also want to clear screen in case you're
following along, you can type clear. And once you press enter, it will essentially free
up your view so that it's easier to read what's going on. Okay. First we're going to want
to download the URL we just copied. So to do that in Ubuntu, you can use curl or you
can use something called wget. I personally prefer wget. So let's go with that. And the
syntax for that will be wget and the URL that we just copied. So once we press enter, we
can see that it has downloaded it. We can verify this by running another command called
ls, which is something like list structure. And we can see here that matomo.zip does indeed
exist in my current directory. So you can see that it's a.zip file. So it's an archive
and it has a bunch of folders inside. What we're going to want to do is we're going to
want to unpack that. So first let's create a directory called matomo. To create a directory,
I use the command called mkdir, then a space, and then the name of the directory I want
to create. Then we're going to type mv, which moves a file or a folder to another location.
And we're going to move matomo.zip to the matomo folder. So if you run ls one more time,
we can see that now we have this folder. And inside that folder, we have the zip file that
we downloaded. Okay. Then we are going to want to enter that folder and all the commands
that we're going to be executing now will take place from there. So to change the directory,
you have to use a command called cd. And then after the space, you enter the directory that
you want to go in. So in that case, cd matomo. And we are going to want to unzip this. So
we say unzip and then the file name matomo.zip. And we can see it's printing out a bunch of
stuff. So if we run ls, we will see there is a how to install matomo.html. There is
a matomo folder and then there is the matomo.zip file that we downloaded. Now for the next
step, what we're going to want to do is we are going to want to move this matomo folder
that we just extracted. And we're going to want to move that to a place where our web
server, so in a place where the program in our computer, which makes sure that the site
loads from the browser, has the option of reading those files. So to do that, let's
use the mv command again and say matomo. And the place where we want to move this in Ubuntu
is slash bar slash www. So this is a default directory that is created when we install
our web server. So if we go over there now, we will see that we have HTML and matomo.
And if we go to, let me share my screen again. But essentially, if we go to our URL, so that
is matomotest.cloud6a.co, we will see a welcome to nginx page, which to me doesn't look a
lot like the software we want to install. But the good thing is we can change that.
So to do that, let's jump back into our terminal window, where we are typing the commands.
And first, if we run ls, so the same command to show the structure, but this time we add
a dash l, it will show us a bit more information on the contents of the slash bar slash www
folder. And what we're going to want to do is that for the matomo user, currently its
owner is the root user, which is the user I am logged in as, but it's generally recommended
that you change the permissions of this folder. So to change the permission, or more exactly
to change the owner, we have to type chown, and then we're going to type a option which
says don't change the owner of just this folder, but change the owner of all folders and files
inside this folder. So that is dash r, capital R. And then we define the user that we are
going to grant ownership of this folder to. So in the case of nginx on ubuntu, this user
is called www dash data. And then we have to do the same thing, but this time what we're
defining here is the group. So we essentially set an owner, which is a user on our system
and a group that have ownership to this folder. So let's go ahead and complete the command
by specifying the directory that we want, which is matomo, and press enter. Now for
the next step, we're going to want to change the configuration of our web server. So to
do that, we are going to be using a text editor. I'm sure a lot of people have strong opinions
about which text editor you should use. In my opinion, you should just use a text editor
that you know how to use and can easily navigate around. So in my case, I use nano and the
file we are going to want to edit is located inside the etc folder, which is where most
of the configuration for different softwares is located in Linux. And we're going to say
nginx and we can see that there are a bunch of files and folders here, but the one we're
interested in is sites enabled. So let's go ahead and type that. And in here we can see
that there is a file called default. So let's go ahead and change that. I will mute just
for a minute for the ambulance to drive by. Okay, now it must be a bit easier to hear.
So I'm going to cheat a little bit. I'm going to be using an nginx template, which I had
already prepared beforehand, but you can find pretty much the same configuration online.
And I'm going to want to change a couple of things. So before I change them, let me first
explain what we're doing. When you visit a website and you go to HTTP, what essentially
you say is, hey, I want to access this server, but think of the server as a building. Sure,
you might want to enter a building, but you have to choose a door in which you enter from.
And in computers, we use port to describe this behavior. So you want to specify a port
for that. Luckily for us or unluckily, depends on how you look at it, some ports are standards.
So for HTTP, we use port 80. And for HTTPS, so that's when the site has a green lock next
to it and says that the site is secure. We use port 443. We're not quite ready for port
443. So let's change the configuration a bit by essentially commenting out some of these
functions, but we can uncomment them later. To comment them, we just use this icon in front
of what we want to comment. So let's go ahead and do that for a few lines here. What we're
doing mostly is we're removing the SSL configuration. So we're removing the HTTPS config. Now this
is not permanent because it's highly recommended that you do run HTTPS on your site because
you don't only protect your own systems, but most importantly, you protect your users.
And then we're going to want to change this option right here. It's actually located in
two different places called inventory hostname. This is a template for the automating tool
that we use at cloud68. But what we're going to want to type instead of that will be the
URL for our website. So let's say matomotest.cloud68.co and confirm everything. Okay. Another thing
we are going to want to have to change is the PHP version because this template uses
version 7.2 of PHP, which you can see here, whereas we installed PHP 4. So let's make
that change as well. And we are now essentially ready to save the file. So in nano to save
a file, you are going to... Yeah, I did comment the server section. So in nginx, the way you
define things is you define server blocks and in there you enter your configuration.
As you can see here, we have two server blocks. And the reason for that is we have one that
listens on port 80 and all it does, it just redirects you to HTTPS. And we have another
one for HTTPS. Now I haven't commented this section here, and that is so that we are essentially
just using a single server running on port 80, which will be serving the Matomo website.
But we are going to uncomment that later on. So let's go ahead and save by typing control
and then O. It will ask us where to save. Let's just say the default file we opened.
And then we're going to want to close the editor. So for that, we type control and then
X. Now we can go ahead and restart our web server, but it's usually recommended we test
if the syntax for what we just did is correct. So to do that, we are going to type nginx
and then space dash T. This tells nginx, hey, can you test my current configuration and
make sure I haven't forgotten semicolon somewhere or forgotten to close a server block. So we
can see that the configuration file is syntax is okay. And we are now ready to restart our
program. To do this in Ubuntu, Ubuntu uses a system called systemd. So to restart our
web server application without restarting our entire server, which is a bit ineffective,
we have to type systemctl, then the operation that we want to perform. So in this case,
restart and then the name of the program we want to restart. So there we go. And if we
refresh our site now, let me just change my screen. We now see a new page, which is the
Matomo installation wizard. And this page, in my opinion, is really, really cool because
first thing it does is it performs a system check and it sees if what you have is all
correct and if there is anything you need to change. So we can see the PHP version is
fine. All of these extensions and configurations are fine. And then there are some optional
suggestions. So you can see force SSL connection. We're not using SSL and that's a problem.
It also gives us a bunch of information. Now I do want to continue to the next step, which
is database setup. But when we go to database setup, we can see that we are going to have
to enter a username, a password, a name for our database. So it's probably good to configure
HTTPS before we move on. Okay. Now to configure HTTPS, you usually have to have something
called an SSL certificate. And SSL certificates, there are a couple of different ways to get
them. You can buy one, which lasts for a year, or you can use Let's Encrypt. Let me mute
really quickly just for the ambulance to go by. So as I was saying, you can also use something
called Let's Encrypt, which gives you a free certificate available for 90 days. So we're
going to say that our website is running nginx, and we're going to use upuntu 18.04. It will
show us some commands that we can run. And those commands first, we have to install something
called snapd, which allows us to install other packets not available by APT. And let me just
copy this command beforehand. This command essentially refreshes the list of available
programs for snapd to install. It's very similar to APT update that we performed. And then
we're going to run snap install certbot. So this is a program developed by the Electronic
Frontier Foundation, which essentially makes it very, very easy for you to get a Let's
Encrypt certificate and authenticate yourself and then be able to use it. Last thing we're
going to do is run this command, which I can't go into details about what it does due to
time constraint, but it makes it possible for us to run certbot in our system and for
it to respond to us. So let's cancel this. To get the SSL certificate, we're going to
run certbot cert only. So only give us a certificate, don't do anything else to our system, and
then dash dash nginx, which is the web server we have installed. We are going to want to
type a email address to get security notices and renewal info. For now, let's just use
no reply at cloud68.co. You need to agree to their terms of service. And if you want,
you can sign up for their newsletter. After you do all that, it will ask you what names
you will want the certificate for. So it has already gotten Matomo test from our nginx
configuration. So let's just press enter. And certbot will do everything that's needed
for us. We won't have to take care of verifying who we are and verifying that we have access
to this domain when we own it. So now we can head back to our nginx configuration and uncomment
everything that we had commented. So in here, we define the location for our certificate.
And these are some other configuration options just to increase general security on the site.
So let's go ahead and save. We run nginx dash t again to verify everything is running correctly.
And we restart our web server again. Now, if we go back to our site, let me close my
screen share so I can show you my browser. We can see that now this website is running
on HTTPS. And we are now ready to do our database configuration. So to do our database configuration,
we are going to have to talk to our database server, which is installed in the same server
that we were using. Let's go there. And let me share this. Okay. So we're going to want
to type MySQL to talk to the server. And we can see that the view has changed a bit. First,
we're going to say create database Matomo. You can name this anything you want. Then
we're going to say create user Matomo user at localhost. So create that user in this
system identified by, I might be confusing it a bit with another syntax or another database
server. But let's use a really, really bad password for now. And next, we're going to
run grant all privileges on Matomo. So grant all accesses to the Matomo database to the
Matomo user at localhost. Okay. So everything's done now. We can now close that and go back
to the webpage we were viewing before. And for logging, we're going to say Matomo user
for the password, the password redefined and the database name. And we're going to click
on next. There we go. So Matomo has successfully talked to the database and created the structure
needed for us to continue. Now we create a super user. So this is our username for the
administrative account. Let me generate a quick password for this. There we go. And
we're going to want to type our email address and we can click on the configurations options
that we want and click next. And we can see that database access denied. So what I'm
assuming is happening here is somebody might have done this configuration before we have.
So let's go ahead and check the logs really quickly. And just give me a little bit.
Oh, I can see that my screen share is not working. Let me check really quickly what's
going on. Give me just a second. Okay. So I just redid the configuration again. Apologies
for not seeing, but I was essentially just going over the website again. And now we can
set up a website that we want to monitor. So let's say cloud68.co, which is located
at this URL. We select a time zone for our website. So let's try to find Tirana or we
can just say UTC plus one. And we click on next. And it will now give us the Matomo JavaScript
code, which we can add to our website and start having analytics. And that is pretty
much it. We now have a beginning installation of Matomo. There are a couple of things we
can further do. We can add a geo database that will show us, you know, we can see that
there is a database upgrade required. So to do that, let's copy this command and run that
on our server. And I can see that you're not seeing my terminal. So let's change that.
There we go. Now, it's generally a bad idea to do this without backups, but this is a
test instance. So I guess you only live once in this case. But please don't just execute
commands on a production system without making sure you have good backups. And let's fix
the permission. And let's upgrade Matomo. Let me change my screen again. And in here
we say admin. Let me take my password again. And there you go. You now have a Matomo instance
running. As I was saying, there are more things to configure your instance. You have to set
up automatic backups. You have to set up monitoring to make sure the instance is healthy. You
do have to set up something called cron jobs, which are essentially background jobs that
perform different operations on the data and make sure that your instance loads quicker
because it doesn't have to compute everything at the same time. It can just show you the
data it has processed ahead of time. I want to show you a few configurations really quickly
that are just to optimize the instance. If we have time, if not, please feel free to
stop me. But essentially we can see here that it says we should set force SSL to one in
the general section of our configuration of Matomo. And we need to increase the max allowed
packet in our SQL database to at least 64 megabytes. So there are different configuration
and tweaks that you can do to your instance to make it behave more responsive. So in case
there are any questions, please feel free to let me know. Now's the time and I'll look
forward to answering them. So Melanie asks how often should the archive cron job be scheduled
for? Every hour or something else? It really depends on how much data you have really.
Usually I set a configuration where it runs once every day, but this is for installations
that track a hundred visits a day max. You can set this to run more often. Something
like an hour might be a good idea if the traffic you're getting is around a hundred thousand
visits, because that's essentially going to process all the data. And when Matomo has
to calculate all of that, when you load the page, it's quite intensive for it. No problem.
Marianne, sorry if I'm mispronouncing your name, asks any reason for using nginx? To
be honest, there's no strong reason why you should use nginx or apache 2 in my opinion.
They are optimized for different loads. Yes. But the main criteria you have to keep in
mind is you have to use a software that you're comfortable for. In my case, I really like
nginx syntax. It's really easy for me to read. So that's what I use, but you can use any
web server there is on the planet as long as you can configure it to run. And it seems
like my pronunciation was correct. So yay. Lukas is sharing in the chat, if you are using
nginx, you might want to look into this link, which is a GitHub repository. Let me open
that with screen share so we can take a look at it together. There we go. Lukas, thank
you for sharing this. I did not share it beforehand. So we can see that the Matomo organization
on GitHub has a nginx configuration for Matomo. So I will highly recommend checking this out
to have essentially the same configuration that I copied over from our template. You
can find that one in here. And this is frequently updated. So you might want to check into it
when there are new versions of Matomo coming out. Awesome.
Okay. So Lukas is sharing that the reason is that the HD access files, so these are
some files that configure a part of how the web server operates, and they're usually used
when you use Apache 2. Lukas points out that these files won't work in nginx, which is
correct because it's an Apache 2 only setup. So those configurations won't work in nginx.
And they have had to write the config rules manually. And it's very, very important for
you to copy the correct config because otherwise your Matomo instance might not be protected.
Some files in the Matomo instance might not be protected. And that's not a very good idea
if your Matomo installation is public. So if I share my screen again, one such configuration,
for example, is this one. And it says, disable access to the following directories, config,
KMP, core, and length. And it says, deny all requests to these locations and show a 403
error code. Yeah, I think you should really use this config because if somebody can access
your configuration folder remotely, then it's pretty much game over. So you want to protect
that. Is there any other question that you want answered? Of course, you can ask me at
any time even later on. My username almost everywhere is this one. I am also in the metrics
chat where you can find me with this username instead. Awesome. It looks like we have answered
all questions. So thank you again, everyone, for joining. And I hope you have fun during
Matomo camp. And we'll see you around.