the okay so i guess so we
are good to go and so on
the festival as thank you very much
although choosing the sir these conferences thank
you very much already for being reverse
her to death
i have to say that already has
been that the first the speaker that
they asked her to come to metal
boot camp were directly accepted so i
would like to thank you once more
for being sore lets out reactive so
positive and to have the will of
being reversed today and this conference to
be
no different than the different one that
we got over the last hours because
this conference is an interview so it's
probably the only one in addition to
the one table that we other yesterday
we've had a different matter more expert
saw the concept of an interview of
course is to ask some questions
already prepare some question that i will
ask her to or already to there
so those question will be shown on
the screen as you cannot see it
right now those slides are done mai
mai sorrowful cared those are not done
by valeri so that's why you will
see the diary not lead that mature
beauty fall is just that i'm not
i'm not an artist when they designed
the slides and if you like care
to ask any questions to her on
a leash please use a shut that
mathml camp that olga and you will
have the possibility to act as a
reply your questions toilet is why we
look at them pick them up and
ask them to oily on safe finish
to present the different questions that they
that they prepare
an small thank you thank you for
having me first of all as well
ananta and i'm excited about all the
conversations also taking place around gd pr
compliance pii personal data and privacy i
think it's an important topic and so
i want
the two shared it's visions of the
future as well discussions about risk so
let's look at going let's go
a soul the topic name is how
does risk for the or differ from
classical risk of perception and the first
question i would like to ask you
already is the following one could you
please introduce your search your audience and
explain what your job position consist of
shock
i so i introducing myself he asked
me the question why i came from
i am dutch french speaking have lived
a long time in brussels where i
did my economics and economic studies and
then moved to spain
i have been in the digital analytics
sphere since around two thousand where a
web trends log analyzer six landed on
my desk and i was asked to
well find insights with that tool with
a lot of flash websites and at
the time and it was also the
time of service and google analytics came
a lot later at least for my
career i it was partially a game
changer on different levels but it also
worried me in terms of privacy and
how much data we were collecting and
also integrating a stitching
together and and so i started looking
also at some at privacy certainly after
we sold our startup in belgium called
like two two lps digital lp i
digitized in the uk
and so once my children were small
i created a family and started looking
at this thing called td pr and
following the progression of that legislation it
took five years and started also to
understand how the lawyers who are talking
because
i didn't have a legal background at
all i am now very happy that
i can actually quote certain articles of
the gd pr
out of my mind hurricane because i
use it so much and today i
have my own consultancy and i have
basically three pillars in there on the
one hand side i am a g
p o official data protection officer for
a customer data platform called and particle
based out of new york
on the other hand i also teach
dpl courses for different university of which
the university of massachusetts
are they also created the european centre
for privacy and cybersecurity so it's not
just me it's a bunch of very
smart people that all come with different
angles and we talk about digitization of
our societies we teach in those courses
and some of my colleagues from maastricht
university are this weekend
senegal to teach about gd pr so
it's it's about making sure that this
idea of privacy legislation enshrined within the
gp are also in it influences global
thinking and this is what we're seeing
gdp as a blueprint and my last
pillar is i was
work for european institutions and i worked
on ethics for the european data protection
supervisor their ethical advisory boards back in
two thousand and sixteen so when basically
the ink was dry on the gdp
our european institutions were asking themselves what's
next
and this is what we're seeing today
with initiatives by for example terrible dawn
with
the different acronyms that are coming out
of the digital services act and and
and other governance acts are currently being
discussed on on top of discussions about
artificial intelligence and this while the supervisory
resources are ramping up to make sure
that they can enforce the gd pr
we're also seeing more complains so these
are basically the three pillars where i
sit about my official job position as
such that we're going to talk about
here is as data protection officer for
a sas platform based out of the
us
okay thanks very much i'm sorry there
is one question that i didn't have
a plan but just by the lets
at the end so that you gift
this question make me sink about so
feel free of cost to himself or
twitter or not you mention web trance
i just would like to know back
in the days
is what happened in in the the
way analytic solution evolve where you really
realize that's the privacy concerns started i
mean at which point did the solution
evolved that much that it started to
be a privacy concern
amen i'm sorry i have to rephrase
it but according to you when all
the years at which led to citizens
all is a good omen started to
to start to care about privacy because
i guess the back in the day
webtrends people were not sinking as much
as the let's a cell ready
an saw analytic system or anything anything
this was just for them nika a
software for the eighty guys that sir
but not for marketers and that may
be used in terms of raising what
citizens are doing and and and at
what point did you realize the day
is clearly a privacy concern which is
raising that that's my question
well i i think generally speaking there's
a difference between me and and then
you know the public in general and
i remember back in two thousand reading
a newspaper articles i think was a
new york times that talked about this
idea that cookies could be shared between
websites
and so that profiles could be built
and the fact that you know advertisers
could target people that are interested in
i think it was the n b
a but also read financial reports
and so this idea of profiling was
started starting to to kind of arise
for those who are paying attention the
thing is market share in advertising for
digital took a long time to evolve
and so if we're talking about the
early two thousands were also we had
the dot com bust and we're not
talking about you know a broad range
of surveillance mechanisms because basically not a
lot of people were were actually online
so that that's one part so these
these issues have arisen
certainty from for the last twenty years
this is not new the thing the
biggest and how should i say er
alarm bell that was was really i
think something important that was not noticed
a lot but is refer to very
often and more recently in the last
three years is the acquisition of doubleclick
by google
i think this really hot
an important consequence that we see today
because it's it's not just about privacy
it's certainly about while the market share
it's about antitrust legislation it's about competition
and there was actually in dissenting opinion
for the acquisition of doubleclick by google
by somebody called pamela harbour which you
can still find online today and when
you read that document from two thousand
and seven so almost fifteen years ago
you realize that basic issues describing what
we are witnessing today
so privacy is one part of this
the gdp rs one part of this
accountability but antitrust and competition are going
to play increasing roles and last week
i was also at the university of
toulouse because i worked for the european
institutions and the observatory of the platform
economy and
that's what we are witnessing today is
platform ization of services where certain of
the actors have very important market share
and influence other actors and the question
is okay what are we going to
do about that because these are going
to be the next challenges so they're
not new questions
it's the gdp doesn't solve for everything
but it's it's it's a milestone in
her goals towards trying to balance out
the use of data the digitization of
our societies together with the opportunities that
are there for the businesses but also
making sure sure that for
fundamental rights are respected and whether that
fundamental rights is privacy the right did
freedom of expression there are different rights
also battling in in this changing our
societies so it's it's a journey we
we are not done yet and we'll
see where we go okay saying
sure much i repeated for audiences but
if for some of you guys who
like to ask some question too early
please feel free to go and shut
that matter will come the oxalic the
womb which correspond to this conference and
asked the director your questions to unleash
and they would pick them up
the next question is said to one
of the earth of the question of
the topic today could you please explain
to our audience what the dp also
i'm not going to give the definition
and purpose here what the dpr is
about
yeah so so a dpl is on
a roll that has been brought to
life through the judy pr
and is actually describes between articles thirty
seven and thirty nine of the gd
pr where article thirty seven talks about
when a company needs to designate a
data protection officer and then what their
position is and what the tasks of
the data protection officer
r and so in that sense our
privacy questions inside companies and can emanate
from the technical teams the legal teams
and the customer support teams and what
is really interesting with with a duty
pr is that they create
this obligation of a centralizing role that
basically takes on i call it the
hot potatoes so i am a hot
potato take her for anything where we
have questions about does this make sense
does it support a fundamental right to
privacy or or is this a problem
so the gdp are basically defines this
companies have a choice to decide whether
they appoint one or not and it's
finding itself also incite more legislations i
was reading about singapore last nights and
singapore also on talks about data protection
officers and so these people are basically
b
bridges between different departments to make sure
that's the way data is being treated
is as balanced as possible between you
know opportunities for business and and fundamental
rights to privacy that the specific and
i think position also have a dpr
is that you give rec
tremendous patience but it doesn't always mean
that the company follows it's you're not
a decision maker you are
you represents the fundamental rights of data
subjects and looking at the systems the
data flaws the processes you make recommendations
with respect to how the system should
work after that add depending on who
the dpr reports to it's a it's
a risk bay
based analysis from the company to say
i agree or i don't or don't
agree or i come with something else
in order to mitigate the potential issue
that was raised by the dpl
thank you
okay i sink and the the next
question is authority as well occurs the
question it's like what when we when
he when we hear you we would
have the feeling that the data protection
officer is like the sheep we have
a five six legs
could you please tell us a bit
more about the background that's most of
sure
colleagues let's sales people that you are
seeing on the field who are the
people like you of all could you
as well explain you expand us
how did you succeed to come to
to take this position as well what
motivated you in the king disposition are
you like learning every dash are you
are you sometimes scared of trust of
in a new techie stuff to learn
which are a brand-new which of course
could raise more complexities maybe you may
realize that okay i have those new
information system coming within my risk assessment
and i don't know them and i
don't have the time to enjoy
instigate them because i just have one
we can free an overdose question and
just coming to my head and the
gen one that i succeeded to graph
this could you please tell us a
bit more about the background that's the
appeal must of to embrace this position
yeah and i see there's there's also
a question about that
in the chats
i
that was basically the next question and
yeah so it it's interesting to note
that for example there's an association called
the aipp international association of privacy professionals
and they do surveys to see who
their members are and and i remember
early on because they weren't like the
first lawyer
or started talking to us just like
they were there thought it sounded like
the best way that the best place
to go
when they serve as surveys and their
members do and not all of them
had been appointed dpl but the majority
had the legal backgrounds and so there
are also recommendations certainly in the early
days of the gg pr by different
authorities
s to consider that dps should have
a legal background
now i do understand that but i
tend not to agree
i because i think that's as you
said the whole nights it's a mouton
sank bats it's a it's a it's
a sheep with five legs we used
to say that about a weapon the
olympics as well many years ago so
that's that's always funny to those parallels
that actually come back and buds as
as your
a bridge builder between certainty the technical
teams and certainly for as a dpr
for for a data platform and you
need to have some understanding also of
of cell technology of data and also
be able to interpret the law and
so my background is econometrics institute
six i know digital because i've basically
been in there for the last twenty
years and and curious about it and
i learned the the legal path and
keep talking to the lawyers about the
interpretation what does certain words mean and
i inside certain court decisions and
this is where i think it's also
important to have like a network of
individuals that can bring their thoughts and
reflections about the interpretation of legislation and
so most dps i would say either
they have been appointed as as an
additional
how should a task to their job
by bigger companies because somebody had to
beat the dpl because of the gdp
are as of the enforcement i've seen
different types of dps i've seen really
legal legal people who are going to
touch upon digital at all and don't
understand how it works and dsp
people even work at facebook sites it's
sometimes a bit scary and i've seen
people who are very technical and very
pragmatic and talk about processes as i've
seen more jack junior people what worries
me the most i have to confess
but it's it's maturing
is that the pills searching in the
beginning were very young so it's like
oh we have to appoint somebody you
know to take the hot potato and
to be honest you get pushed rounds
you get pushed around by the sea
teal by you know you you have
to ask questions to understand how the
systems work and if you're not like
your persistence and i typically use my
gray hair and say you know i
am really silly i'm really stupid but
i don't understand what you guys are
talking about and then i i'm not
sure you're very effective as a dps
so it's it's the maturity and and
i think you're also the experience of
difference and specialization that makes for a
good dpl but it's it's a new
type of title so it still needs
to evolve but there's less lawyers in
there jpp did another show
survey survey i realized that this percentage
of lawyers up about eighty percent went
back to forty so other types of
profiles are also starting to to to
apply to data protection officer jobs and
often they come from privacy home sourcing
so
or they just went through certain trainings
and and this is what they want
to do
okay thank you i i often those
accused that your question was just came
from and which links back to something
that you that you said some minutes
ago about okay you provide recommendation and
then the ceo of the company on
let's just take coral bells deciding to
go
this way is up to go and
those away always up to nuts have
loads of recommendation at all and we've
injured the pr what is already famous
for this whole depress us spread the
world about his his those four per
cent of turnover on it said penalties
if someone is not respect
acting or let's say gdps i would
like to say that does it work
for wheel on the shield i mean
this threat of a guys if you
don't follow my recommendation
you may be subject to four percent
off of penalty of ton about your
company always it in fact some something
that the company does not even care
about because they're saying that that it
will never happen because they'll sell too
powerful on the market and of course
they will use some as a let's
say a way
as of single cat you cannot put
me for boston because if so i
will decide to outsource all my company
somewhere and finally know one of the
goodness four percent let's say
penalty so i would probably go to
maybe five or six warnings before the
plates and i would probably actor under
celled wanting something like this and feel
free to insult to this question that's
ok this is confidential i prefer nothing
sober i'm just curious about this point
does it does does it work
ok this four-person the threat of of
affinity
i think as we are
beyond a couple of years of enforcement
of the gd pr and i think
initially it did it did scare a
lot of people because you have to
understand that prior to the gdp are
the data protection directive only allowed two
countries to fine around half a million
euros and that was
uk and spain
i so i remember talking to somebody
in digital and that it takes a
couple of years back before the gd
pr and i think that person was
in the czech republic and that person
said you know if if anybody gets
fined under the data protection directive is
like what is it five hundred euros
who cares
it's it's it doesn't matter it's just
you know doing business and as i'm
based in spain i know that you
know companies like telefonica they basically had
a budget for data protection finds under
the directive
so initially i think it was really
a good you know wake up call
to say hey guys two to four
percent of global turnover or twenty million
euros whichever is higher is your financial
risk and and it did serve as
a wake up call it it's why
you know all these data protection offer
series have been appointed and things like
that i i today think this is
starting to backfire why am i saying
that's well because what basically happened to
the larger players who is a business
model depends on personal data so they
hired a lot of very
smart privacy professionals before the enforcement of
the gd pr and clearly had a
strategy of what i call lawyering up
if i get fined let's imagine fifty
million euros by camille
i dunno go to the courts and
fight it and ideally that i find
will disappear which which is what happened
to the fifty million euros trump camille
so in that sense it's a good
thing because it woke up the markets
it's not ideal because it doesn't align
all the players into making sure that
they do the right thing because they're
using the legal system to basically escalate
now this has a certain time and
what we're seeing is that more and
more of these questions are actually now
coming to the european court of justice
so it's a matter of maturity where
the market needs to evolve in a
certain direction where certain new ways of
thinking around data needs to take root
and be accepted and that takes time
we used to be in a time
of let's collect everything and see what
happens
we are now in a time of
let's use the data that may be
nuts at start deleting and not use
everything and data minimization and things like
that so we're becoming more prudent with
what we're using and and asking more
questions and as i mentioned there are
other acronyms after the gdp are they
the data governance act the digital digital
services act we're not done yet in
terms of making short in the right
direction so that the risk of these
finds is there it's not ideal and
certain supervisory authorities have started to play
enough
very smart way with that in the
sense that their fines are not huge
but their requirements for compliance do have
a significant cost effects and this means
that there's for example a ruling in
belgium where a
bank needs to pay around two hundred
euros in fines just nothing but they
need to change their systems behind and
this is the iceberg nobody seems to
see are all the powers that the
supervisory authority have to for example stop
data flows and say you're not allowed
how to pass that data from here
to there or you need to delete
everything that's dare in a surgical manner
and this is the real risk of
the gdp are are these inherent costs
because we have been used to collecting
everything and that if something goes wrong
we will have to
start cleaning up and that is going
to be like the biggest challenge in
the longer term other challenges are also
arising if we're thinking about it from
a global perspective class actions are typically
not things that exist in europe so
class actions is when people come to
you
gather and they go up against accompanied
the biggest the best example i've found
so far as the movie erin brockovich
where she goes after a chemical company
but these are rising there are class
actions that are against salesforce and oracle
and the netherlands there's a lot of
discussions in in australia in two
terms of evolutions of the cas actions
so this is another risk that is
not directly it's it's enshrined within gdp
arts testing things out it will take
time but potentially it will come that
risk will come from other countries maybe
even the us
okay so here we can start to
make a link with analytics like someone
alone who claim that someone is not
choosing that solution properly as no that's
a real power but if you can
find an online service who easily does
a the list in one piece
people who find this an unconventional and
would like to think the company could
easily gazelle all around and just knew
a couple of clicks quoted to do
a class action that that's typically what
you're thinking of them right yeah yeah
absolutely i think that's that's the direction
this might take and what's interesting also
is that
search of venture capitalists certainly in france
are backing that up okay i saw
him on the screen we probably have
the ugliest the slide of the metal
camp that they did myself the question
is is just the following that's the
topic submission that you make for maximum
accompanies or does it
risk for dps differ from classic called
risk of perception and i just would
like to know why did you decided
to submit this topic i mean what
what was the main message that you
would like to to to give us
because i guess that's when you choose
it you have something in mind and
i really would like to leave you
the flaw here
and to have the possibility to express
everything that that odin mindful for this
given topic or so so i talked
a bit about risk before this notion
of finds and what is underneath the
iceberg of the finds that we don't
see those hidden costs that will certainly
influence
the way we treat data whether it's
personal or or not
but what i also realized working certainly
was compliance teams that go through certifications
and talk about okay our our requirements
in terms of compliance is that when
these compliance teams talk about risk they
talk about risk specifically for the compa
any
and as i mentioned before a data
protection officer typically is an independent and
an external adviser to a company and
if you enshrine this within the logic
of the gd pr but the dpr
does is they represents the fundamental right
to privacy of of the
data subjects so when a dpr talks
about risk and when you say hey
you know mister company this is not
good you should not be doing that
because because because then the company will
take a risk assessment of their own
to decide whether yes or no they
will they're going to
will do something else but the risk
perception when a dpr flags something is
this external vision of risk to data
subjects compliance people talk about risk for
the company so these visions align
to a certain point but not totally
and so this is something that is
i think important to understand also from
a semantic perspective because as she said
see that so many times i use
same words as the security people but
we don't mean the same thing when
i talk about risk i talk about
risk to society to people outside of
the company that can
blind people talk about risk to the
company our financial consequences of the choices
we make and i think this will
continue to evolve but what surprises me
is that first of all the understanding
of what a dps is or is
supposed to be a dp oh is
not the same thing as privacy
council because of privacy council works for
a company and if for example a
supervisory authority knocks on the door of
accompany and talks to the privacy council
the privacy council has obligations of confidentiality
a d p o's role as defined
within also article
thirty nine of the gd pr is
actually to talk to supervisory authorities
so this once once companies also understand
this it also means that this row
of deep yo is challenging because it
it basically if you bring in the
risk of having somebody external looking at
what you're doing and being able to
talk to supervisory authorities
so it's it's it's a challenging position
to build trust and i think after
three and a half years at m
particle we are this is what what
is existing this is what's there i
i typically spy on the teams and
give my comments but it took time
for this trust to be built and
and as as you mentioned beef
oregon on yeah i have sleepless nights
because i'm worried about the system or
because there is a a team that's
you know building something that i don't
singles in the right direction
but i think it's it's in the
interest long term interest of companies to
bring in deep peels and build this
trust to make sure that what they
build today and for the future goals
in line with how privacy legislation evolves
and so
oh and i'm always a bit worried
as i mentioned before young the pills
they get pushed round and things like
that but that the presence of mind
is always i look at society what
are the consequences of what you're doing
and where could this go nobody thoughts
about the issues that bigger players
day to day bring about for the
democracies of our societies or or the
stability and this is what all these
deep yields need to do is to
make sure that this goals basically in
right direction and so this is why
i wanted to bring this to the
table because it's it's you know the
euro
happiness and institutions like to talk about
risk and gdp are being a risk
based assessment and i agree but risk
for who and for what is often
the first starting point of any kind
of privacy engineering discussion say okay what
what are we talking about what is
the context and
how do i see harm and how
can we find balance within the data
flows to make sure that everybody that
is impacted by this not only actors
like michael moore and and and the
company using them but also old data
subjects behind
okay thank you that that's perfect
it's currently two thirty six i'm going
to enter within the topic
which is about
link between the pure and matter more
so i really would like to know
if web analytics tracking tools like metromile
so let's add web analytics in general
okay could say google analytics eighteenth on
that though what what the rules are
out the console you see by the
peel
so i would say like information system
who could contain personal data or as
a consider those optional information system to
look up at precisely the moment my
question is that's within the scope of
the pure you probably got a new
ceo him which contain far more
personal data then the web analytics system
newsletter that the basis you probably have
ozone ozone information system out there or
just emails for example and just would
like to know where in the scope
of the deep your mind the location
of
of women that he took system
okay so so typically when we talk
about the obligations of a deep heel
and it sits within the roles of
the company so what kind of role
does that company played paid it it
is a data controller for its own
marketing operations
and then it might be a data
processor for other things it depends on
what the company does
so in that sense typically i think
systems but i might be wrong like
like matter more digital analytics and the
m p c d p's play a
role
for marketing operations ideally more honestly i
would i would like to see a
bit more but apparently this is still
like the big game here
and unfortunately there are a plethora of
tools being used by marketing departments
i and these tools also change every
year to three years
and in that sense i think i'll
certainly dps that are are are not
technically technical minded and have issues understanding
how all these systems interact what is
clear is that sin certainly needs a
gd pr as he systems
act as data processors for marketing i
think the minimal requirements are typically around
this idea of having a contract or
data protection agreements and and making sure
that these international data flows work well
and it also depends i mean matter
moyes have very specific to
cool in the sense that it's not
a sas solution and in in that
sense it also you know it depends
whether there's an appetite from the company
to actually invest resources and making sure
that they can set this up and
have this up and running inside their
systems
so i think for dps if i
had to answer this question from that
specific angle do they care if they
understand what's going on in marketing and
start digging a bit probably yes and
does it facilitate do certain stances with
respect to privacy facilitates
and the the the the audit and
the audit passing by a privacy office
of a tool like moto moto mo
certainly but it's not the only aspect
so how much does this way in
the risk exercise of the company is
a big question
that answer your question kind of yeah
yeah absolutely of sergei of menus else
in mind i'm just trying to look
at the time and think about the
number of slide that they have left
and as we're leaving some space for
an audience to ask some questions
but yeah that's that's answering a question
bits raising so many in my head
that it's a well it's a it's
a challenge the next question is about
this one and i think it's very
linked to do and so little would
you provided us which is a do
the dp will make a difference between
proprietary software and free software because us
up then it's within the tamil community
make clearly a difference between the two
that i would've affected swimming with what
you just said with data flows but
i really would like you to insult
this one does it make a difference
between appropriate
software and free software well i i
think our last interaction on twitter clearly
shows that certain dps like me think
in terms of sass and then it's
like alright free software that's that's totally
different ballgame
because what i mentioned before it was
like what would your dpl ask for
from any sass tool is i want
a data protection agreements and i want
to make sure that their standard contractual
clauses to make sure that my international
data transfer are as local as possible
comes in free software that
self-hosted where you want so as standard
contractual clause doesn't make sense and a
dp eight doesn't really make sense anymore
either because there's no intermediary the question
i think that will start to rise
however here and it's it's it's also
the case for sas but to
privacy by design functionalities what is needed
and this is also what what i've
done most over the last certainty eighteen
months
complex systems is as this is a
system that helps a data controller what
does that system need to do to
assure that it supports the compliance obligations
of the data controller so the matter
more customers a typical example would be
we are certainly also following apple's eighty
ti consent status does it actually applaud
the lawful basis for processing and the
fact that yes or no we agreed
we didn't agree those terrible banners for
a privacy and things like that does
it defined purpose do we know what's
that
specific data point is about and certainly
if you want to do more with
that data can we use these fields
to pass a month
by seeing these are kind of conversations
that need to happen today i'm focusing
on privacy by design because also i
mean matter more doesn't exist in a
vacuum it is part of something that
is them doing something else and so
these conversations about what do i need
inside my tool to make
sure that i interface correctly with how
data subjects exercise their choices and also
making sure that through the pipeline of
the data these choices are respected and
if at the same time data subjects
exercise their rights which is kind of
the big one in the gdp
yds not new but it's bigger i
also have the capabilities of doing that
but i think this is like the
big challenge for most companies and sites
or free software is to start looking
at what does privacy by design mean
and what do i need to do
for my customers you
he mentioned other tools out there while
the french tools they take different stances
than others
so you could imagine for example a
tool saying and i do not forward
this data if there's no consent is
that the choice of the tool to
say that or is it up to
the customer
so these kind of discussions and stances
are taking place depending on you know
the the the risk appetite of the
company how their contracts are being set
up and things like that but these
are kind of the conversations that a
tool also needs to decide to say
okay where do i position myself do
i
i want to be extremely strict in
terms of privacy or do i prefer
not to cut myself off from other
business opportunities leaving more responsibility to my
customers these are more ethical discussions to
be had but they need to take
place
okay
thank you very much and i'm looking
at how many quit okay i just
have one question left which is great
because we have five minutes left
i was on the risk of personal
data infringements fallen into dish did i
write this question i cannot even understand
it myself without the risk of go
for an entity
do you understand this question because i
don't understand it myself than i should
have preferred it without the risk of
personal finance
okay we talked a bit about the
notion of risk and and the underlying
bits of the iceberg with respect to
search data subject rights
i
yeah i think i have something in
mind when i write that i didn't
proofread this question just would like to
be sure that the audiences got the
opportunity to ask questions so i will
let the chuck goes on for the
next those thirty seconds
so i can see that we of
different people in the church we have
macros we have seen evolve we have
many other people if you have any
questions please feel free to ask one
or either already do you have any
any question that you expected me to
ask you or that you would like
the audience to
ask you about specific sing
no not not specifically i think we
we ran through our
oh
we got trois yeah people are willing
to pursue a career as as peel
and it depends a bit on your
and your background i think
there are more and more jumper offers
out there but they often require some
form of either a certification or experience
and so there are certifications out there
the i e p p has a
couple of them and they often font
find themselves and insights and the job
offers that i read as i mentioned
also i teach at maastricht university they
do dps
certifications
i'm i'm hiring as well so i'm
looking for people so if you're interested
i'm happy to have a chat
i do i think yeah more more
job offers for dps
but it's it's about you know getting
your your foot in the door and
start building some form of of of
knowledge around the the topic as well
if your lawyer actually helps but i'm
happy to help as well
okay
i cannot see any any questions left
on small officers another one actually personal
responsibility oh yeah absolutely it's a very
good question that was often debated and
and actually if you look at the
gd pr
and there is another role which has
the raw representative
and a representative you have to look
it up in the gdp i don't
remember the the article but is the
person that's going to represent to accompany
if they don't have
a foothold basically inside a certain country
there's more discussions about legal responsibility for
representatives than for dps and i think
it would be also counter productive to
talk about potential responsibility for for dps
because
i i i've seen the the conversations
about representatives and people are just walking
away to say i don't want that
liability i don't want it but i
don't think that as such a dps
have some form of a responsibility or
liability but on the other hand they
are responsible for it in front of
the supervisory authorities to answer any kinds
of
questions and this is still in discussion
and in in making do
i think if we're talking about some
form of a responsibility or a certain
liability there is conversations about more civil
liability for decision makers so seals and
things like that or criminal liability i
think the conversation will go there not
dps because that would be kind of
shooting the subjected in the foot
but we'll see
perfect and on small thank you very
much for being with us today to
spend some time just retina the room
with all the different questions we'd be
on until the end of the events
on his head this evening so if
you have some free time left of
feel free to have a look at
it maybe some new questions will come
if you will have time which was
totally understand of course
should free tuf
to to leave it and i will
send you the the questions mate you
made if i got them and for
the audience i remembered that the speaker
was all hindi poets and that you
can easily find her on a very
famous options zine because she's kind of
the expert in the world dealing with
privacy a privacy concern
since i thank you very much orange
thank you for everything thank you for
having me thank you for listening and
if there are any any questions this
is also how we all learn please
feel free keep in touch and have
a good conference went on thank you
for having me thank you
the next conference would be in nine
minutes from now cause there is only
one on the schedule that i can
see this one will be made by
continue you by and myself even if
i will have just the minor roles
in it it's about using that mode
to collect data on intervention engagement within
the results
triodos food so use case from a
a client of mine so the clients
will talk about this project and i
will come within the conference and explain
how we did with the project management
but we have met so useful