Welcome to the first day of the MatomoCamp,
or rather one of the first two days.
But here we are in a German-speaking day.
So the moderator here is Joachim Nickel,
who has been using Matomo and Piwik for over 10 years
and also engages in various open-source projects,
such as, for example, especially the CMS Contao,
which you may have already heard of,
and of which the funding association is the president.
And he will now tell you a little more about
how to get a little more data experience in Matomo
with background tracking
and, in general, also with which alternatives
there are for classic Matomo JavaScript tracking,
which everyone knows.
With that, Joachim, you can start.
Thank you, Lukas.
Yes, hello.
Let's start with the second slide with me.
In the end, Lukas has already said a large part.
I am an OMT ambassador.
I will come to the OMT topic a little later.
President of the Contao Association
and Matomo for at least 2010,
probably even a little longer.
Today it's about the question, first of all,
can I trust the numbers at all
that we track in Matomo or anywhere else
in this type of tracking?
And a little teaser at this point,
I would say a very clear no.
That has several reasons.
Because if we take a look at how standard tracking works,
what we have in Matomo,
either via the Tag Manager
or via normal JavaScript tracking,
then the visitor comes to our website,
gets the data, in the end,
and in the website there is this little code
that just says, you browser,
give me the data back there to our Matomo
and track the whole thing.
And that's where we really have
this huge problem with the data pass-on.
Because on the one hand there are these
tracking protection stories,
ETP and ETP, as they are not all so nice.
On the other hand, we have the big problem
of the user consent,
which we have to use often
in connection with the Do Not Track headers.
But, and very specifically,
the problem of the ad blocker.
For 2021 I found a statistic
that suggests that in Germany
around 40% of users
who are on the website
use ad blockers.
Over 42% worldwide.
These values always differ
differently from the manufacturers
who give these statistics out.
Some of them go up to 50%
and it is very, very different
with the individual websites,
but we'll get to that in a moment.
This fact was, in the end,
the reason why I said
that this path ahead
is perhaps not necessarily the best,
because too much data is lost.
And that's why I say, okay,
let's draw the path and go directly
from the application to Matomo.
Because Matomo has something very nice
that other systems do not offer in this form,
namely the Tracking API.
The disadvantage with the whole thing
is that the implementation
has to take place in the application
and we really have to collect
all the parameters we need
and we don't have the nice case
like in JavaScript Tracking,
that everything is already
more or less out of the box
and then we just have to collect
these data and send it to Matomo.
The tasks that arise with it
are, on the one hand, clear.
We have to clarify the topic of session handling,
that is, how do we get the individual
visitor sessions together?
Matomo cannot take on this task
for us at this point.
We just have to take on this task
and take care of the bot recognition
for the most part, because everything
that we throw directly against Matomo
is ultimately evaluated there.
Bot recognition at this point is
difficult, because it is switched off.
And we always have to take into account
that we have a certain latency.
That means that the application itself
should send the request to Matomo
only when the output is
delivered to the web browser
of the customer.
But even then it's stupid
if the process just takes too long,
because the way to Matomo API
is just too long.
And so you could think about
just getting the whole thing
somewhere locally yourself
and then first hand it over to Matomo.
We have to work with a corresponding
API key in the Matomo instance
that has a writing access
to, for example,
hand over the IP address,
either shortened or
in plain text, to
do the geo-IP resolution,
or we do the geo-IP resolution
directly in the application.
And of course everyone agrees
that the topic is data protection.
That means we have a lot of data
in the application.
We can possibly identify the customer
one-to-one directly
and then have to think about
which data will be handed over.
It's up to Matomo not to get
problems there in terms of
data protection.
Let's take a look at the comparison.
On the one hand, I have a
regional provider that I have
equipped with standard tracking
and in the background.
And when I look at the whole thing,
then I have a difference of
about 60 percent,
60 percent more data that I can
identify in background tracking
for these customers.
We also see the deviation
of the mobile types down here.
That means whether it's a desktop system
or a mobile system.
In background tracking, we have
much more desktop systems,
which raises the probability
or the assumption
that the ad blocks are higher
on desktop browsers.
You have to say that was a time
when you couldn't change the standard
browser on iOS.
Now everything is a bit different.
Personally, I use both
on the desktop and on the phone
the browser Brave.
It makes the tracking
more difficult.
But at the same time, the information
with Matomo and in connection
with cookie-free tracking,
that the Matomo instance is on the same domain,
then the JavaScript tracking
comes through the Brave browser
while other things are kept
and decoupled.
Let's take a second look at
the KFZ online shop.
Here it looks like we have
about 30 percent more visits,
but already about 40 percent
more page views.
How does this come about?
From the situation,
in contrast to a regional provider,
where I very often only have
one-pager visits,
I have much longer visits.
And if a user
who goes through the online shop
has a blocker,
then the difference between
the number of visits and the page views
will be different.
I'll come back to that later.
Here I have the
short-term view of the telematics
of the mobile browser.
That means we had 74 percent
mobile browser in standard tracking
and 67 percent in background tracking.
That means the number of desktops
has also increased again.
You always have to consider
this distinction, because
there may be so much
different data in background tracking
that you have to consider
whether you actually wanted to choose
the right one.
Now we come to the OMT.
The OMT is
an online platform
that is the meeting point for
further education and networks
in online marketing.
The claim of the OMT is
to learn from each other all your life.
I am also the ambassador of the OMT
and had the chance
to evaluate this page.
Here we had an installation
of a Matomo standard.
There were
almost no deviations.
That's why I leave that
out here with Google Analytics
in comparison.
Then we had an uplift of
15 percent in the visits.
That was the big disappointment
because the difference is
relatively small.
Apparently, not so many people
use the system adblocker.
Then I looked at the data
and realized that I had
left out Google Analytics
because that did not give us
any further points.
We have 80 percent more
page views
compared to the visits.
That means 15 percent more visits
but 80 percent more page views.
I wanted to take a closer look
at that.
But first I looked at the statistics.
This is an online learning platform.
That means that people go
there every week.
That means that the weekend
dates are much lower
and that's why we have these
interruptions.
Here, too, we have a huge
share of desktop users.
That means that even in normal
tracking we have 73 percent
desktop users while in
the background we even
reach 84 percent.
We already remember the
73 to 84 percent because now
we have a big difference.
We have segmented the whole thing.
I have left out all the
individual page views to
see what happens there.
I have found out that
with the visits we have
no longer 15 percent but
already 35 percent more.
If we take a look at the
page views at that point we
even reach 140 percent.
Before we had 15 percent
to 35 percent
and 80 percent
to 180 percent.
The share of users
in the desktop area
goes up to 91 percent
by now.
The database
that we have here,
with the page views at least
two, looks like this.
In standard tracking we have
24 percent of visits that
generate about 53 percent of page views.
In background tracking
we only have 5 percent
more visits.
But we have 18 percent more
page views that are generated here.
We clearly see the difference.
The users, the app blockers
in this case,
bring a much higher number
of page views.
If we increase the whole thing to
the number of page views of at least
four, then this difference
is much higher.
Yes.
Let's take a quick look at the
technology from the front and from the back.
From the front is
clearly the normal standard
tracking variant.
The background tracking I have here in the middle
and at the very bottom
to compare the variant, if we
run log file analytics with Matomo,
so that you can see
what the differences are.
Events,
i.e. event tracking, are not a
topic at all.
About the Tag Manager, about the normal JavaScript integration
or the like,
we can do everything perfectly.
In background tracking, this is not possible
from home at first.
Because the tracking
comes directly from the application,
i.e. at the moment when the HTML
is generated.
So I don't know anything about the entire user interaction.
If I
wanted to bring that in,
I would have to build my own interface
with this data
in addition to the tracking API
within the application,
using Matomo.
This is a bit more complicated,
but theoretically understandable.
Within log file tracking, there is no chance
to do anything with events at all.
Internal elements tracking,
exactly the same.
Standard available in background tracking
only via an own interface
that we have to create.
The same applies to the downloads,
which are already available.
That means we don't have any problems there.
Also the outgoing links,
the same variant over background tracking.
I have to solve this on my own.
These are all interactions within the browser
that happen,
which I can't get right away.
In log file tracking, there is no chance
to manage the whole thing at all.
E-commerce tracking is not an issue at all
in the background,
because the data about e-commerce
is even much earlier available
than it would normally be.
Also here in log file tracking,
there is no chance to get there.
Of course, we can use cookies
to recognize the user again
in standard tracking,
in terms of how far you want to do it
in terms of the user consent-free variant
or whether you use hybrid tracking there.
That is up to everyone.
In the background, I have to think
about something else
how I can recognize the user again.
Of course, I can also set a lifelong cookie
with which I can identify the user
afterwards,
but I have to get the logic
into the application.
Adblockers are
exactly the problem
when it comes to standard tracking,
which is why I want to do this background tracking.
In background tracking,
it is not an issue at all.
All user data are coming in,
even far too many,
because all the normal bots
are being protocolized here,
but I'll get back to that in a moment.
The same is true for lockfile tracking.
I would like to briefly mention
the topic of caching here.
Standard caching,
that is, HTTP caching,
is not an issue with standard tracking at all.
If I activate it
or even use a CDN
and want to use background tracking,
I have problems there,
because the data for the tracking
no longer appears in the end application,
because the data comes directly
from the CDN,
and so I have the problems
to capture this data there.
In the case of lockfile tracking,
I would have to use
the CDN tracking
and not the individual server.
Session recognition,
of course, if I don't use cookies
in standard tracking,
it happens via fingerprinting.
In background tracking,
I have that via the system.
Most of the time,
I recognize the user
during the session,
and with that I have a much more accurate
session recognition than I would have
with fingerprinting or the like.
When it comes to lockfile analytics,
we don't have to think about it at all.
Someone tried to find out from the IP address
of the user agent
whether it could be
a coherent session or not.
Lockfile tracking is always
a nice parallel variant
to get a feeling
of what is going on
in standard tracking
in order to detect
a size and target size.
And that without the effort
to integrate the whole thing
within the system.
Integration, of course,
standard JavaScript code,
simply bind in, and that's it.
With background tracking,
it has to take place in the application.
I have developed a finished module
for the CMS Contao.
It's relatively wide.
A few more tests have to be done.
There are too many vulnerabilities
with extensions that come in
that could interfere with
the extensions I have developed.
We just have to do a few more tests.
If you are interested in these extensions,
feel free to contact me.
Then we can take a look
and do a little test.
And with lockfile importing,
of course, the whole thing has to be set up locally
so that the lockfiles are imported.
Let's get to the important point
of recognizing bots.
We basically have the situation
within the web,
just about 50 percent,
maybe even 60 percent of the traffic
that really follows by humans.
A large part of 22,
25 percent of such a thing
in the shoot comes from harmless bots.
Harmless bots are, for example,
the Google bot itself, the Bing bot,
Yandex and whatever they're called,
but also all the other services
like SysTrix, like Ksovi,
or other services that know
the websites, or even
we ourselves, for example,
Screaming Frog or something like that.
All the bots that identify themselves
based on the user agent string
that they are bots,
we can identify as harmless bots
or evaluate in the form
that we say, yes, we can
filter them out anyway
and we know what happens there
and everything is fine.
And the important thing
that we should know,
which is basically,
whether it's Google Analytics,
Matomo, Standard Tracking,
or something like that,
are these impersonator bots.
That's about 25, 26 percent
of the traffic goes to such bots.
They act as if they were real people
who search the websites.
That means the user agent is
falsely, logically,
as if it were a normal Windows
that accepts cookies, obsession cookies,
long-term cookies.
These cookies are sometimes
divided over the instances.
So I've seen things
where I said, I really want to get to know
these people who,
within just 15 minutes,
once from Asia, once from the USA
and once from Sweden,
access the website and every time
only one and the same page,
not the start page, but some sub-page.
And we clearly recognize that
these impersonator bots
act as if they were real people.
They also do scroll,
they also do scroll events,
they also solve reading time triggers
and stuff like that.
They actually click on buttons
and solve CTAs.
That means we recognize
based on the behavior of these bots
not whether they are real people
or whether they are bots.
They really do a damn good job
and they annoy us in the statistics.
I have an updated version
from 2020
from another provider.
It assumes that we also
have about 25% of web bots.
Here you assume about 60% of humans.
The values,
you have to say again and again,
such statistics are always colored.
Depending on what kind of access
the providers of the statistics have,
they are different.
That's why it always comes down to
what is identifiable on your own website
and can be tracked.
Then you just have to do the things.
I've brought you a little comparison
with regards to impersonator bots.
This comparison is a bit unfair.
This is my own website
that I had from August 31
to September 19
in parallel tracking
with an automo instance
where no bot recognition
was in the grip
and an instance
in which I had everything
that I could drive.
A manually managed IP address
list of bot networks
and the like.
The difference looks like this.
The curve is identical,
but not the number.
I have almost half
of real accesses
that I could identify
that they were really humans.
The rest are actually
such impersonator bots
and they also produce
completely different values
for me in terms of pages.
That means the data
that I have here,
reading time,
jump rate and the like,
are completely out of order
because I have so many
impersonator bots on it.
Why do I have so many?
That's almost twice
what I have on normal visitors.
This comparison is a bit mean
because I use my website www.job.de
at the same time
as a forwarding target
of over 100 other domains,
partly expired domains,
partly domains that I had
before projects myself,
but also certainly of the 30-40 domains
that have never appeared anywhere
that I have registered,
but that have never appeared anywhere
and still get these domains
in large numbers from bots.
That's why I use this website
a bit like my little honeypot
and can identify
IP address segments
that I then find out
about whois analysis and the like,
whether these data segments
or these IP address segments
serve network operators
or not.
Topic recognition of bots in general.
User Agent is a voluntary
application, that means it can
definitely be faked. I shouldn't
rely on that.
It's difficult to use
because only with the second
access this variant can
be tracked,
but also bots accept
these cookies and share
the cookies, distribute these cookies
over their entire network segment
and finally only the IP address
remains and we have to
build our own filter there.
The problem at this point is
we can't really identify
die-in and static IP address segments
and everything ends up
in the background tracking.
I have to go back
and forth to search for
manual pattern recognition
in order to handle the whole thing.
At this point I want to focus on
an expansion of Matomo
because when I look at the
downloads of the tracking spam
prevention, which was only
at 1,828 when I
made this screenshot,
then that's extremely little.
This expansion should
be installed by everyone
in their Matomo instance
because I don't only have
the possibility to say I want
to exclude IP address segments
which are for example
downloaded from well-known
cloud providers like
Oracle, Amazon,
Azure Cloud and the like.
Lists are automatically downloaded.
They are not complete.
I have to say that very clearly,
but it's a very good approach.
But here I have the
possibility to do something
about exclude countries
to improve the data quality.
For example, if I have a website
where I am not at all interested
in whether users from China,
the USA, Sweden or the like
should come,
then we should see
that this thing is
possibly recorded
in the exclude countries.
Alternatively, to turn the whole thing
around, if I say that I am really
only interested in users from
the German-speaking room, from the roof room,
then I might just add
Germany, Austria and Switzerland
to it, possibly also France
and England and similar things
that come in a little bit.
But these are the customers
that interest me in my logging
and I can eliminate
an enormous number of log-in entries
based on the fact that
this geo-IP database is relatively
up-to-date and works
quite well.
You have to say that this free
database of a geo-IP that is
installed or offered
as standard at Matomo
is not always 100%
up-to-date due to the fact
that it is a free variant.
There is a cost-effective variant,
which is much more up-to-date.
There is also the MaxMind service,
which is also much more up-to-date.
In my opinion, this free variant
is much more up-to-date.
And the second variant is
to take care of the list of
globally ignored IP addresses
by yourself.
At this point, I have a list
of over 1,400 IP address segments
that I have identified
and that I throw in here.
But you have to say,
if I have so much data in here,
the load of Matomo is of course
still quite a bit higher,
because every single call
is a bit higher.
Finally, the manual pattern recognition
is one of the most important things.
We then have to check the IP address
and carry out the cleaning of the log data.
Matomo helps us
by having this DSGVO
or GDPR segment cleaning
where I can say,
OK, I would like to delete
this IP address segment
and then all this data
will be taken out of Matomo
and I can continue with it.
I can also update it
and then record this IP segment
as an exclusion variant.
In this context,
I would like to briefly
talk about the anonymization
of IP addresses,
because we have to briefly
look at which settings
I would like to make
for this case,
that I would like to make
a manual pattern recognition
and clean the data
of the 254 IP addresses
together.
And I can say relatively precisely,
OK, this IP address segment
is most likely
only in the input area
of a service provider.
Especially with cloud providers,
they usually have at least
this class 10,
i.e. 254 IP addresses,
which I can identify
relatively well about,
even if I use the variant
in addition to that,
I can just look at how this entire IP address segment
belongs and then I can get a little bit
more information about it.
If I leave the standard variant,
which is recommended for Matomo,
i.e. this two-byte variant,
then I pack 65,000 IP addresses
into this cluster.
That's definitely too much.
So if I use this setting in Matomo,
I can bend it,
somehow trying to identify
whether this data
or whether this access
came from an IP address segment
which is a network provider service
or something like that, or whether it is
a dial-in network, then I can completely
forget about it. And if we go to 3-byte,
then we don't even need to talk about it,
that's rather 16 million IP addresses.
Then I can actually
completely ignore this lockfall analytics
related to the visitor variants.
The data protection history down here,
in this case for our
certification for bots and the like,
is rather not very interesting.
And what is it all about in the end?
In the end, you just have to go through
the visitor log in this manual recognition
and then just look at
these IP address segments
and take a look at
the whole thing
according to the UIS database.
Yes, that actually
brings me to the summary
of my lecture.
If we really want to have
complete visitor data,
we have to rely on the background tracking.
Alternatively, with a
lower entry threshold,
to first look at what is going on
with ad blockers, possibly lost,
is the lockfall analytics.
The problem at this point,
if I have too much anonymized
the lockfiles from the IP address,
that is, even more than this class C segment,
then I can not leave Matomo
the chance to filter out
certain data
in this tracking spam prevention
variant or
the own IP address filter
history.
If a class C net or a class B net
is only anonymized,
then I can forget about the lockfiles
to really clean up the data.
I will get insights
without question,
but I will not be able to
identify whether these were
normal user accesses
or rather accesses
from on-board networks.
By doing this,
I can deal with the background tracking
or lockfile stories with the ad blocker
and have to see how it is
with the application levels,
i.e. with the HTTP and user caching.
Application caching in general,
i.e. where can I use it?
Does it even help me to develop
this background tracking?
I just have to have a good strategy
in terms of onboard recognition,
which, as I said,
has an IP address filter,
and my recommendation at this point
is always to carry out
parallel tracking from the front,
i.e. normal tracking by JavaScript,
and the tracking from the back
in parallel, because from the front
I get insights that I only get
with considerable effort through
the background tracking.
Here in the background tracking,
I really want to find out
what kind of loss
we have in normal tracking
i.e. the normal tracking
with the corresponding factor x
to calculate us a little nicely
and to get better insights
at this point.
We have to say that
when I looked at the OMT thing,
there is no way to say
I'll just take the factor 1.5
to calculate
what I would have
on users.
I really lose a lot of
facts that, especially in the
convergence or performance marketing,
are relevant.
Because if I really lose
the user who generates
much more page views,
who generates revenue,
who makes the purchases,
if I don't have it in standard tracking,
but I can capture it in background tracking,
then that's a completely different topic
on which I could then
control my Google Ads
investments differently.
Because I really see
that the display A performs
much better than the display B,
how I could normally take it out of standard tracking.
So from there
look, what does it look like?
Then just clearly the topic
of privacy by design,
what about user consent
that we really completely
anonymize the data
and of course run our Matomo instance
on our own server.
And then the whole thing could,
depending on how we deal with our data protection
then also work well.
Yes, I would say
half an hour talk, half an hour
point landing and from there I say
thank you very much
and yes, I am now looking forward
to questions that may come in.
Exactly, now would be the time
for any questions,
comments, other things
about the topic.
There has already been a question discussion,
which I would have asked, otherwise
you could maybe start right away,
a little bit about data protection,
opt-out and so on.
The problem is with the normal
JavaScript tracking it is relatively
simple to make an opt-out,
because you put a cookie,
it just works with the Matomo function
and with that it is relatively
straightforward. With a
background tracking you have to more or less
implement it yourself.
In the background tracking everything
has to be integrated by itself,
but right there I can of course also
take back a JavaScript-based cookie
and interpret whether
I can use it,
want to use it. At this point
you have to say, of course, that
background tracking is a purely
technical approach,
which in principle first of all
makes the data available.
How we handle the whole data protection
is still a second question.
I just wanted the basic idea
that the background tracking
and the possibility of data
coming in and presenting,
but yes, if we really talk about an opt-out
and really need this
data or
have to implement it in the necessary way,
then it's right, then you can do it
with a cookie and I can use it
in the application.
If there are no further questions,
let's leave
the people a little bit of time,
there is a bit of delay between
what we are talking about here until
the people see it.
Either I have explained everything
so beautifully or no one
dares to. Oh, someone is typing.
Yes, perfect.
Otherwise, you are welcome to contact me
at LinkedIn and Facebook
and feel free to ask questions
at any time. I am happy to
be at your disposal.
Exactly, and if you come up with anything
in the next few hours, the chat room
will remain open, it is only for one talk,
you can just continue
during the whole MatomoCamps.
A question from the chat room.
Do you have any experience
with hybrid applications?
Yes, I have two
applications currently
in the pre-planning, where we
want to implement the normal tracking
of the user consent
and then also
set the appropriate user cookie
if the user consent is available,
is in the planning, but I don't have any
experience with it yet.
Tracking for the MP3 calls,
that would more or less
be more or less only a variant
that can be solved either via
lockfile analytics or
but you switch
the analysis or rather
the provision of the MP3
via, for example, a PHP
Redirector, which works
virtually as a virtual
directory and then
takes the data in reception,
takes the calls in reception, the requests
and then also sends it
to the Matomo API
as a corresponding request.
So it can be solved without any problems.
We can talk about it again.
Exactly, a proxy script, exactly.
Exactly, something like that I would have also
asked myself,
which was not asked in the chat
and the one problem
that I see a bit
with background tracking is,
for example, if we have a very normal,
very simple PHP page, then
that would mean that every time this PHP
page is called,
a beginner is sent to the Matomo server
and the problem
is, in contrast to JavaScript
tracking, if you program it wrong,
that the background
server waits until it gets the answer
from Matomo and only then
sends the request to the user
and thus actually the
side call becomes a bit slower.
Yes, that's the standard error
problem on the topic, but
you can do the whole thing in this respect,
at least I do, that I
collect the data
within the standard process for the
page generation, but only
after, in the end,
yes, if Flash works,
that is, the entire HTML output
delivered to the customer
is then, in the end,
the last task of the
API Connect to Matomo.
Variant 1, then I have, in the end,
the situation that the process
runs a little longer, but the
session to the browser is already
closed and, accordingly, the user
does not receive this request anymore.
The second variant is
to write all the tracking
information into the database
and then play it
through, and then
take the data
from the database
in a separate process and then
send it to Matomo.
Since I have to work with
a writing access anyway,
with the API Key, I can also
set the time of the access later.
Then I have a temporary delay,
but no real-time analysis at this point
in Matomo, but just 1-2 minutes
delayed, but that seems
to be a more elegant variant,
that I really log in, in the end,
only to a local MySQL database
or, as always, the database
just save and from there
get the whole thing out and
throw it to Matomo.
A solution that I then also
would have, which unfortunately goes
relatively badly in PHP, but in other
programming languages, for example,
it would also be a possibility
that the server has multiple processes
and then simply sending
the data to Matomo in a separate thread
and then really completely
independent of the application
of a user, because you don't have to wait,
because you need the information
not to be able to send the user
his data. But you can do the same
in PHP, I can also just
load a thread.
So, as I said, if there are more
questions, feel free to contact
me at any time, linked in Facebook
or my website itself,
also on my website, book an appointment
for a meeting, then we can
like to see your individual needs.
Otherwise, if there are no more questions,
then it comes to an end.
I can briefly announce
what happens at 11 o'clock.
At 11 o'clock we have two events again.
On the one hand, you can
change to live stream room 1,
where Jrg Paul will talk about it,
in a very, very large
Matomo instance,
from the point of view
of the Swedish tax agency
or something like that.
So really Matomo instances,
which get millions of pages a month,
how you can still handle it
on the server side,
that you can do the load.
Or you can change to
the interactive workshop
of Thomas Zeithammel
in the workshop room.
Then it goes on in German
and he can talk about how to use Matomo
properly for such engine optimization.
That would be the two possibilities
at 11 o'clock.
Otherwise, thank you, Joachim,
for the nice lecture.
My pleasure.
Have fun with Matomo.