Well then, it's about two o'clock and with that, it's time for the next session.
For this, I would like to introduce Sylvia Arapi.
She's a digital rights advocate with a special interest in the topics of privacy and intersect.
And she is also one of the co-founders of Cloud68.co, working to make the use of open
source digital infrastructure easy and convenient.
In her talk, How to Stay Compliant with Privacy Regulations with Matrimonial Analytics, she
will cover the importance of compliance with privacy regulations, especially from a business
perspective and how Matrimonial Analytics makes it easier for people to ensure the privacy
of their visitors.
For this, she will go over a comparison with Google Analytics.
And with that, take it away.
Many thanks for the introduction, Markus.
Hello, everyone.
I'm very excited to join this very first event of Matomo Camp.
Today, as Markus mentioned, I will be speaking about compliance with privacy regulations
by using a digital analytics tool such as Matomo Analytics.
A quick look into the agenda for today.
I will quickly go over the discussion about personal data, why are so many regulations
in place in order to safeguard this data from companies, let's say, who are hosting personal
data.
We will go through the alternatives that we have when it comes to using digital analytics
tools, such as Google Analytics, Matomo Analytics, which will be the main focus of this event.
But of course, there are also other tools out there which you can use.
And then we will go over the main requirements of GDPR and we will look into the tools that
Matomo provides us with, which support us to respond to the requests of data subjects
and as a consequence, that makes compliance easier.
So a few words about me, I am a free software and online privacy advocate, at least this
is what I do on a volunteer level.
I am a board member of Open Labs Hacker Space in Tirana, Albania, an NGO where I have contributed
for the last couple of years and where I had the opportunity to learn about the free software
movement and since then I've been engaged in various small open source projects software.
I've mainly been engaged with advocacy and with a special focus on the topic of online
privacy.
I'm also one of the co-founders of Cloud68, a company which supports other small teams
to make use of free and open source software.
I've been using Matomo in the last two years maybe, despite the fact that I haven't used
it in a setup where we would handle like a huge amount of data.
I've closely looked into it as an alternative of Google Analytics, which of course not only
makes compliance easier but has many other advantages compared to this proprietary tool
which I will try to go into more detail later during this presentation.
I'm sure that everyone who is hearing this session now couldn't have missed hearing the
expression that data is the new oil.
We hear this pretty often maybe in the last decade since 2013 with the Edward Snowden
revelations about how personal data was being mishandled not only from companies but also
from government bodies.
There has been a lot of discussion and many other cases of data breaches have been published
which created and increased this need for a public debate about how companies were storing
personal data, how they were processing it, how much data they were holding and how much
information does the public have about this.
This increase of the cases of abuse we can say increased also the need from public bodies
to create proper legislations on the ways how these companies should handle the data
and how they should also take measures to protect it and to not abuse with it.
The reason why companies are so eager to collect as much data as possible is because of course
as this expression says it, data is the new oil, it means that there are also lots of
profits about collecting and making use of the data.
This is why it's really important to have proper legislations in place and to help to
hold these companies accountable about their actions.
Privacy compliance, a very short definition of the term is that it is a company's accordance
with established personal information protection guidelines, specifications or legislations.
Depending on your country where you are operating or where your customer base is at, you might
fall into different regulations, so this is a case by case, this can be treated on a case
by case scenario but two of the most not only popular but also more strict regulations in
place are the European General Data Protection Regulation, GDPR, through which also during
this presentation we will look into more detail, but also the CCPA which is California's Consumer
Privacy Act, both are designed to protect and authorize access to what's called personally
identifiable information which we will also define in the upcoming slides.
So basically this presentation will mainly be designed for those companies who are gathering
personal data of individuals who are performing digital analytics but are also looking for
tools which will support them to stay compliant with these various regulations.
So despite the fact that there has been this long discussion and abuse about the misuse
of personal data, at the end companies also need to collect it because it's also a way
to serve their customers, to improve their experiences, to perform innovation.
So the main considerations here is that we should perform digital analytics actions in
this GDPR era by having ethics in mind and by complying and by using the right tools
which support our ethics.
So as I mentioned, while there are various regulations in place, one of the most strict
and most discussed ones is the European GDPR which requires all companies, despite the
fact that if they are based in the EU or not, if they are serving to EU-based citizens,
they will have to comply.
This is a regulation which strengthens and unifies data protection for all individuals
within the EU.
This regulation of course is quite complex and if we were to go and dig way much deeper,
of course we would need the support of law consultants to discuss everything related
to it, but if we were to explain it very easily, it is applicable to a company every time that
it is collecting personal data, if you are storing personal data of these individuals
then you have to comply with the data protection principles which are guided by the GDPR.
So of course, in order to collect this data, you should also have a legal basis for doing
so.
You should always communicate this legal basis to your users which are called data subjects.
So they should be always informed about the type of data that you are collecting about
them and why do you need this data.
And of course, they have various rights upon this data which again we will look into more
details.
An important aspect of the GDPR is that it also included some other identifiers in the
concept of personal data.
For example, IP addresses, if an IP address can be used to uniquely identify a person,
this under the GDPR, this is also considered personal information and personal data.
So it's not enough to have like very concrete information about the person which falls under
the PII such as their name, their home address, their email address, but if there are some
sort of third party identifiers which you can use to match and in another way to identify
a person's identity, that falls under the personal data and here we include IP addresses,
cookie identifiers, page URLs or page titles, user IDs, e-commerce order IDs, locations
and hit maps and session recordings.
So this was a major upgrade with the GDPR to also include this kind of identifiers as
part of the legislation.
So every time that you are collecting this information, you should make sure that you
are following all of the GDPR guidelines.
So especially in the case of small companies who do not have all of the resources to go
over a very careful check of their internal procedures, they should try to minimise as
much as possible the amount of personal data that they are saving about their individuals
and when possible, if they do not really need it, they should completely avoid doing so.
And of course there are ways, for example, if in your website you are hosting a digital
analytics solution but you are mainly interested in analysing the user behaviour but you don't
really need to know who these users are, then you should make sure to configure your tools
in the right way so that you just get the information that you need but without hosting
any type of personal information about your visitors.
So in this way you will save yourself a lot of time and resources which you otherwise
would have to communicate what kind of data you are hosting through your privacy policy
and also to comply with the data subjects request.
So in every scenario when you can avoid at all hosting personal data, you should consider
doing so.
Also another benefit, let's say, of not hosting personal data when that is possible, which
you can achieve by using a tool like Matomo, as we will see later, is that you can configure
it in a way so that you can also avoid the constant screens which are those annoying
screens that we see every time that we open a new website who asks, who informs us about
cookies and the data that they are storing because this has proved to also impact the
customer experience so if you can, in a way, avoid this at all, that can also be beneficial
for your business purposes as well.
Matomo actually provides a way for you to achieve this.
So in the case that you do not track personal data and you also need to have enabled cookie
last tracking, you can bypass this requirement which is quite usual by legislation such as
GDPR and the privacy to display this banner asking for cookie or tracking content.
The reason why with Matomo this is possible is that visitors aren't tracked across various
websites as it happens in the case of the Google Analytics.
Visitors can be tracked within different days, so in a time frame, Matomo does not perform
profiling of visitors and of course the data can be used for your own purposes and not
for other purposes such as in the case of Google Analytics with whom if you share the
data they can also use it for their own offerings.
An important consideration under the GDPR are the rights of the data subjects who are
the people to whom you are hosting this personal data.
Under the GDPR they have various rights which they can exercise any time and in order to
stay compliant you will need to have the necessary tools to respond and to perform this request
by your data subjects.
Some of these rights are the right to be informed.
You have to always communicate the kind of personal data that you are collecting through
a privacy policy, at least this is the most usual way to communicate this to your users.
They have the right to access this data so they can ask for you all of this information
and you will have to share it with them.
They have the right to ask for erasure of the data.
They have the right to ask for modifications of the data if they pretend that the data
that you are hosting is not correct or needs to be updated.
They have the right for data portability, which means that in some cases they might
ask for this data and you will have to send it to them in a machine readable format which
they can easily use afterwards.
They also have the right to object.
This mainly happens in the case where you are not asking for consent but you are performing
the data collection under the legal basis of legitimate interest and in this case your
users might have the right to object for the data collection.
And of course in the case that you are asking for consent they have the right to withdraw
consent and usually it's advisable to offer an opt out option which is easily accessible
by your data subjects.
All of these specifications under the GDPR put a lot of pressure on companies of all
sizes because no matter the size of the company they have to make sure that they are respecting
this personal data so they need to take all the appropriate measures to stay compliant.
This requires additional resources, more education within organisations to also train their internal
staff and to design all the organisational procedures with data protection principles
in mind.
So with this being said, when it comes to making the decision about your digital analytics
tool you might have to go through a decision making process when choosing the right and
appropriate tools.
As I mentioned during this presentation we will mainly go over the comparison of Google
Analytics and Matomo Analytics and why I believe that Matomo is better for privacy compliance
but of course there are plenty of tools out there.
The only thing that I would suggest is that when you make this decision we should also
try to look and to consider as a factor in the decision making process the tools that
this software provides in terms of privacy option.
So if usually in this decision making process we consider simply the features or the analytics,
how powerful this tool is in terms of analytics, I think it's really important to also add
in the decision making these other options.
I haven't used any other open source tools besides Matomo but when I looked into it as
an alternative to Google Analytics it really makes things easier and it does provide great
documentation in terms of how you should treat the GDPR cases.
So why you should consider Matomo as a replacement of Google Analytics?
The main reason here to mention is the fact that when you are using Google Analytics you
are sharing your data with Google, a big tech company which we can now say whose reputation
hasn't been that great in the last couple of years.
We also know that Google uses this data that you share with them of your visitors.
They use it to feed their databases for user profiling which has been considered a big
threat by many privacy advocates, a threat not only to people's data but also to democracy
we can dare to say.
With Google Analytics you also do not have ownership of the data, you are sharing the
data with Google, it belongs to them and you have to agree with their own terms any time.
With Matomo you have options such as the option to host the data on your own, being at your
home server if you have the technical skills to do so.
As we discussed earlier, with Matomo you also have this option to avoid this annoying tracking
concept screens for those businesses who might be able to configure Matomo in this way while
with Google you cannot do that because they are using every data that you share for their
own purposes as well.
And also with Matomo, as in the case of every other open source software, you have flexibility.
Since the software is open source you have the freedom to customize the software according
to your own needs, to develop plugins so that they can perform other actions, so if you
are a developer and you want to customize it based on your organizational needs you
can do so or you can allocate appropriate resources to customize Matomo.
And of course you have the option to host it on your own premises or you can go for
the Matomo cloud offering which in any case does not use the data that you host in their
cloud for other purposes as in the case of Google Analytics.
And of course you will have this option to be more independent because in a scenario
for example even if you are using the Matomo cloud and they change their pricing model
you can always have the option to self-host or look for other options available.
While with Google Analytics as it is a proprietary software this migration process might be a
little bit more complicated than simply moving your Matomo data from one server to another.
So these are some important considerations to take.
Usually when people just look for an analytic solution it's easier to go for Google Analytics
because it's free in the sense that you do not pay any money for it but you do pay with
the data that you are sharing be it your visitors data and of course also by using a more privacy
compliant tool you can also gain a competitive advantage because in the cases of data misuse
companies can also have like very negative impact in their reputation.
So if you do take these appropriate measures but your competitors don't then you automatically
in a way are gaining some competitive advantage over them.
So why Matomo?
Some of the main benefits of using Matomo as I mentioned is the fact that you have 100%
data ownership it provides so many privacy options which you can customize and will help
you stay compliant with various legislations and privacy laws depending on your scenario
where you are based or what kind of data you are hosting.
It's reliable and secure Matomo is open source and there is an active community behind it
who are like actively contributing to the source code reporting bugs and helping in
improving it and you have the option to host it on premise or on cloud.
Regarding the privacy options that Matomo has to offer it really makes compliance easier
by providing many features and to quickly go over these features Matomo provides you
with data anonymization because it is designed with privacy by default in mind so it implements
a range of data anonymization techniques for example you have the option to not record
the full IP address of your visitors here is a screenshot from the Matomo interface
where as you can see you have the option to select how many bytes of your visitors IP
addresses should be masked and this gives you more flexibility let's say in the way
that you are how you are hosting this personal data of your visitors it has a GDPR manager
tool which for which we will go in more detail later but it helps you which will support
you to respond in an easier way to your data subjects request Matomo can be configured
to not process any personal data or PII I've shared in the resources of this slide a link
which has a very detailed guide on how you can achieve this there's the option to configure
Matomo to automatically delete logs from the database which means that you can also automate
this process as well also according to GDPR you should have these these procedures in
place also about the timing on how about data retention which means how long do you need
to save your customers data so according to these procedures you can also configure Matomo
in the right way so that you comply with these regulations or Matomo supports that do not
track preference which is like a browser configuration of your users so that they notify automatically
Matomo so in the cases that they do not want their behavior to be tracked Matomo has other
options such as to disable the live features to disable tracking cookies you can customize
the way how your users opt out of all the trafficking you have you can delete visitors
data when requested through the GDPR tool which we will look into later I also mentioned
it previously that the data is not used for other person purposes compared to Google Analytics
you have the option to disable visitor logs and profiles and options in terms of where
you are storing this data so we also mentioned earlier all of the rights that the data subject
has under the GDPR legislation sorry for the background noises so the GDPR manager has
been developed to ensure that websites are fully compliant with this regulation and it
provides you with the right tools so that you can take appropriate steps to comply here
is a screenshot from the GDPR tool from the Matomo Analytics and as you can see it makes
it quite clear and it keeps you informed of all the options that you have when dealing
with a subject's data so the first thing in this menu would be to search for a data subject
and this is what it looks like in Matomo so you have the option to choose the data source
which can be from which website if you're hosting different websites you can choose
the website from where you want to filter this data out and here you can find data subjects
by performing different filtering options to find the matching data subjects and in
this way through these filtering tools there are various actions that you can perform such
as for example if a data subject will perform the right of access to this data after searching
the data by using this GDPR tool you can export the matching results and send it to data subjects
and this can very easily be done by this export selected visits button another option is to
delete the selected visits and you can apply this in the case when the data subjects are
applying their right of erasure and the procedure that you follow is the same you filter out
the data but in this case you will simply delete those visits and inform the data subject
for this action the data subjects also have the right of rectification so in some cases
you might need to update the data that you are storing in the Matomo you have to do this
by accessing the database or modifying the records but in some cases a workaround of
this like when in setup where that is possible might also be to simply delete the data if
you don't need it anymore your data subject also have the right of data portability and
in this case you will again exercise a similar similar steps as in the case of the right
to access and you will send in a machine readable format their data to your data subject so
that they can access it and they can use it for example if they are moving from your offering
to another service provider they have the access the right to ask for this data
and another right of your data subjects is the right to object this is applicable only
when processing personal data with legitimate interest as a lawful basis and in this case
you should offer an opt-out feature to your users Matomo again makes this easy through
the interface where you can customize the output iframe as you wish and then you can
embed this code on your website to make it as easy as possible for your data subjects
to opt out when they wish and the also visitors have the right to withdraw constant and this
is applicable only if you are using constant as a legitimate ground to collect this data
my greeting from Google Analytics to Matomo in my personal experience I have faced this
question a few times and the procedure has been like quite simple Matomo provides again
very good documentation that you could follow but again I've tested this scenario with not
like huge amount of data but in each case you should go over an evaluation process to
make sure that everything is working as it should for you so for this process as well
in the resources of this presentation I've shared a guide from Matomo which hopefully
will make the migration easier for you in case that you have already started Google
Analytics and you want to consider a switch and start using Matomo so many thanks for
hearing this was the presentation for today so if you have any question you can feel free
to write them in the chat or thank you Silva and there are already two questions or discussions
in the chat the first one is what do you mean with page titles and page URL or personal
data do you mean together with other data yes this because this kind of data in a sort
of way can be used to identify can be converted into a PII which means that if there is a
way that your data controller which is the person who is tracking this data can match
or can reach can after your identity after collecting this information that means that
if you are hosting this kind of like search queries that usual user might enter in your
website that means that you are hosting personal data and you should take appropriate steps
to safeguard it as GDPR guides us thank you we have another one even if I anonymize a
part of the IP address isn't the whole IP address stored in the database in the database
it's stored only the anonymized version of the IP address but of course I know anonymizing
IP addresses is not enough to say that you are not storing personal data you should also
make sure about what other type of information that you are hosting but this is like one
of the features that Matomo provides so that you can minimize the information so at least
this is like a step to more to more privacy okay and we have another question I think
it may relate to the first question because we have a bit of delay but it's what about
pixel tag well that also falls under the personal data because in some cases the cookies might
save some unique identifiers which can then be used again to identify a person's identity
and thank you about that I'm gonna wait for another minute to see if any more questions
pop up but that seems to have been the case if any other questions arise feel free to
keep using the chat for it it's gonna stay up and besides that once again thank you for
the presentation and yeah have a great day thank you everyone