Okay, so it's currently 9.00 CST time and we are ready to start this historical moment
which is the first MatomoCamp ever. Welcome to the MatomoCamp opening ceremony. My name
is Renan and I'm here with Lukas Winkler. Lukas, can you hear us? Yes, I can hear you fine
and welcome to everyone here. So this MatomoCamp opening ceremony will last about 30 minutes in
which we will explain to you what this MatomoCamp is about, how you can take part of it as well
as presenting the different organizers, so as the different speakers that we will have during
the next two days. So what this event is about, this event is about spreading the knowledge
about Matomo Analytics which is the number one free software web analytics platform which of course
that most of you guys know which gives you 100% data ownership. If you don't know yet
Matomo, please do not hesitate to scan the QR code which is on this slide which will make you
land on matomo.org and you can as well already have a look at the solution if you just type
within your URL bar demove.matomo.cloud. So what is the history of the event? Why are we
holding it today? So in fact it just started with a bunch of Matomo passionate talking,
Lukas, myself and other guys and that's not probably the best storytelling ever that we're
going to have here but it's just like people talking together and saying hey why don't we
create a MatomoCamp and here we are. So it's not about great ideas coming, it's just the fact that
we realized that it was probably the good time to organize one because we started to have a lot of
people from around the world asking a lot of questions, setting up businesses about Matomo
and then this is where we say okay we have a high interest of communicating together, of spreading
knowledge or helping our businesses, companies to grow, helping Matomo to develop and so on and so
forth and that's the reason why we decided to create an ambitious project which is a Matomo
camp which consists of spreading knowledge between all the people around the world.
We wanted when we created this event to keep the free software philosophy by saying that and mean
that we are excluding in organizing this event all the proprietary solution, all the proprietary
software in order to organize it and we decided to really challenge ourselves by using only
free software technology. So instead of taking just one technology which is gathering everything
that we needed, we take the bet that we could organize a quality event by just taking free
software pieces. So of course we would like to thank the community and of course the different
software editor of those free software platforms that we are using for this event. Of course by
starting by Matomo, Matomotics which is the number one free software web analytics platform,
then BigBlueButton which is the video conference software that we are using right now with Lukas
in order to make this conference. During all the event long you will have the possibility to chat
with all the communities through Element which is an instant chat messaging system. The different
files that we use for the organization of the events so as many different applications have
been used thanks to a solution which is named Nextcloud. Most of the servers which are running
the different apps that we have now are using an Nginx software platform. Lukas you can correct me
if I'm wrong but KDNLive is the software which is used in order to make the streaming part am I
right? And no it's a video editing software we will be using in the next weeks to edit together
all the recordings before we can publish them on the website. Oh great thanks. Before the event
we created a survey over the summer in order to know what were the expectations of the Matomo
community. We used for that a survey software named LimeSurvey. In order to organize the schedule,
gather all the different needs from the speakers, their presentation and so on and so forth.
We use a great software named Pretalks. In order to add the matomocamp.org website we use a famous
CMS named WordPress. In order to send the newsletter by which we collected the different
emails from matomocamp.org we used a software named PHPList. And as well in order to make people
interactive and more during the event we are using a software named WorkAdventure and I precise
that no free software were harmed during this organization. Maybe the logos when I try to
resize them for this given slide. And I apologize as well for all the other free software that we
may have used along the process but that I may have forgotten to add within these slides.
I would like to thank our partners for the event. This event is mostly relying on a very low budget
and as well on the best effort system which means that it's mostly relying on the time and energy
that each individual of the organizing team are putting on it. But I really would like to thank
in particular the Matomo team who accepted for us to use a logo which is similar to the one of
the Matomo. As well I would like to say huge thanks to Empreinte Digital who is the company
who is let's say running all the streaming infrastructure and who is putting a lot of human
resources and energy in holding this event. I would like as well to thank Mist Analytics who
invested some time and budget in order to create the logo. I would like as well to thank the Sonora
company who as well put some energy in it so as purchasing the domain name of matomocamp.org.
And as well I would like to thank Stairs for the investment that they make within the template of
the WordPress website. So to say we are really running this event with a very small budget
and I really would like to thank all the different individuals who are the organizers of the Matomo
Camp event because they gave a lot of their time. Mostly those are women and men business
and they really spent a lot of energies in this event on their working time.
About the organizing team, you will have the possibility to see all of them either as speakers
or as moderators. So I would like to thank Onsmore Lukas-Krinkler for all the involvement that he put
within the event, myself, so Renan Chardonneau. Silva Harapi, she's been the one in charge of
all the communication that you may have seen either on the website or either on the social network.
Peter Bolk who is the guy who deals with all the system administration part with the help of Lukas.
Frédéric Cain that you will have the chance to see as a moderator for the French speaking conferences
so as a speaker. Joachim Nichel as well who helped us in organizing the event.
Stefan Koning that you will have the chance to see during the Q&A session. Thomas Zeitnamer from
Germany, Thomas Pearson, Jorge Fabian and Mats from the Digitalist AB team in Sweden. Stefan
Gill from the Netherlands, Thomas Schoening from Germany and as well Guangri Li who helped us for the
sponsor part. I hope I did not forget anyone. Dealing with the speakers part, they are really
coming from all over the world and I really would like to thank them on small for taking part
of this event. So you will see Lukas, you will see myself. Joachim Richard-Stark will take the talk
in I think at 10 a.m. today who is from the InnoCraft team. So let's say the private entity
behind Matomo Analytics. You will get as well Nathan Freitas, you will get as well
the let's say I'm gonna call it like this the Italian team are represented by
Davide, Pierre Luigi and Claudio. We will have the chance as well to have Christian Alner,
Valentin Bares from Empreinte Digital, Bati Steven from Open Source Politics, Victor Vexjai
for a talk about privacy, Boris Boudini, Aurélie Pauls, Katie Newbay from the UK and Ronan Hello
from France. Once more I would like to thank all those speakers that we are going to have the
chance to have today from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. and as well tomorrow from 9 to 5 p.m. CST time. Lukas,
I can give you the floor now. Yes, so I will be talking a bit about how you can participate
in the event. So of course most of you have already seen our nice schedule where you have a
nice time overview when which talk or workshop will take place to day and tomorrow. You might
probably have also seen our live streaming page live.matomocamp.org where all of our
talks are streamed live into two rooms at the same time and there you can also join the workshops
and can you go to the next slide please. And so if you want to participate in the event you can
watch all of the talks on live.matomocamp.org you can see the live streams there. If you want to
ask questions to the speakers we have a chat room for every single talk on chat.matomocamp.org or
the chat room is also visible below the live stream. And you can also find on chat.matomocamp.org
you can find multiple chat rooms where you can talk to other participants about Matomo,
about Matomo business related things and other topics. And as a slight bonus in case you don't
really care that much about the talks themselves and are more interested in meeting up with other
Matomo users and want to know their experience, talk to them, we have a work adventure platform
on meet.matomocamp.org and there you can join and talk to other people in groups or together
in a voice or video chat. So if you're interested in talking to other people you can go to meet.matomocamp.org
and one more note at the end the whole event is planned in central european time so at the moment
that's central that's UTC plus one hour. So if you are not from central europe please stay keep
that in mind whenever you look at the schedule and other things just so you don't arrive at the wrong
hour. So thanks that's it for me back to Renat. Okay yeah I just would like to precise just one
tiny thing is that you don't need to register to anything in order to attend the event you just
need to go on live.matomocamp.org and from the time schedule which will start in 10 am so in 45
minutes from now you will have the possibility to pick up either room number one or either room
number two so you just need to go on live.matomocamp.org and make the choice in order to see the
conference that you want to attend to. If you would like during this conference to ask questions
to the speaker the only thing that you need to do is that you need to go and chat.matomocamp.org
and here you will need to register to this platform and once you register to the platform
you will have the possibility to ask as many questions as you want to any conference that
you are looking at and or interact with any other Matomo users let's say attendees to the events
by using this platform so of course that's a great place in order to connect. Let's imagine that
you are looking for someone in order to help you about some Matomo issues that you are facing on
a day-to-day basis that's typically the place where you cannot do it but if you would like to
have more interaction like seeing the person that you like to discuss with in face-to-face
you can use this platform which is meet.matomocamp.org which does not require much registration as you
just need to put a nickname and you are ready to go so just to let you know that live.matomocamp.org
won't allow you to interact with the speakers that's through chat.matomocamp.org that you
can do it and that you can interact with other either through chat.matomocamp.org by text message
or either by video cam system on meet.matomocamp.org. And one more thing related to this if you have any
questions to ask the organizers have any troubles or unsure about how something works correctly
on chat.matomocamp.org we also have an info desk chat room where you can write something and we
will see it immediately and in case if something is broken enough that you can't even connect to
the chat you can also find the contact form on the Matomocamp website where you can send us a message
and we will reply via email. So we are a bit ahead of this time schedule we planned this opening
ceremony to be 30 minutes long and we made it in 15 minutes that's great because it gives you some
time to go on chat.matomocamp.org to already test the platform to see if you can register to it
easily to already start to connect with other attendees. You can of course go as well on
meet.matomocamp.org and start to connect with other people. Just to let you know that the
first session of today will start in 45 minutes from now so let's say 10 a.m. There's no reason
why they won't start on time so I think that at 10 a.m. it will be good. Probably out of the main
questions that you're going to ask is will those talk will be recorded? The answer is yes of course
we have some moderators and moderators have the responsibility to record each session and when
the sessions will be available well we may need of course to make some cut some adjustment within
the recording but they will probably arrive just some days after the event. Just to let you know
that one month before we created a pre-matomocamp event which was for topic the matomo tag manager
so it was a 45 minutes conference and this recording has been put online probably like
two or three days just after it so you can expect just a one week delay in order to have the recording
online it's not going to take like like a month. Lukas do you have anything that you would like to
add or say to our attendees today? No nothing for my end apart from of course wishing everyone a
nice matomocamp today and tomorrow. Okay that's great so yes welcome everyone to a matomocamp
enjoy it as much as you can. Next session will start at 10 a.m so in the meantime you can relax
and just create an account on chat.matomocamp.org. See you in 45 minutes for the first talks.