Okay, so we are live now.
So once again, Marco, thank you for joining us today.
To everyone who is attending this session, Marco is one of the co-founders of Plausible
Analytics.
In this talk, he will talk more about the platform, which is a simple, lightweight, open-source
and privacy-first web analytics tool.
Marco will introduce Plausible, explain the differences from Matomo, and do a demo of
the dashboard.
Marco, I'm leaving the floor to you.
Thank you.
Great.
Well, thanks very much for the intro, and thanks for the invite.
You know, I got an email from one of your colleagues a few weeks ago, and he's like,
would you like to come and speak on a MatomoCam conference?
And I was like, but we're Plausible, we're not like even a fork of Matomo, we're completely
different, like we're an alternative, why would you want us?
And he was like, oh, we spoke with the Matomo people, and we really insist that you guys
should join.
We invited a few other alternatives as well, it would be nice to kind of expand the knowledge
kind of in the community and so on, and show some of the other people the other work they're
doing in kind of the same area.
So here I am.
Like mentioned, I'm the co-founder of Plausible Analytics.
Here's a website, Plausible.io, we started, so like in Matomo is, you know, like I have
known about Matomo for, you know, I don't know, two decades now.
I think it started a while ago, kind of like Google Analytics did, but we are pretty much
brand new.
The first line of code was written in 2018, we launched our product in 2019.
And here we are today, we have, we are fully open source, so you know, you can, our code
is out there on GitHub available, so you can inspect it, analyze it, you can download it.
We have a very easy self-hosted version as well, so people can install it on their own
servers.
We have the cloud version, which is kind of what makes it sustainable.
So you know, if we don't have any investors or anything like that, which means that Plausible
is basically funded by the subscriptions that our subscribers pay us, that the fees they
pay us for the subscriptions.
We have 8,000 plus subscribers at this stage, we are installed on more than 60,000 websites,
at least our cloud version, the self-hosted version, there's no telemetry or anything,
so we don't know, but 60,000 plus websites use us, about 2 billion page views per month,
we kind of count all across these websites.
And yeah, we're a team of eight, a few months ago, if you ask me, three months ago, we were
a team of three, so now we're a team of eight, we've grown very fast, kind of similar to
our growth in general on like how well-known we are, we've kind of grown our team as well
very fast over the last few months, so now we have six full-time developers and two non-developers,
one of them is me, and we're kind of trying to do our best and have a Google Analytics
alternative that's a bit, for some people, that's better and easier to use.
So basically, let's have a look on our website, let's have a look at the differences from
Matomo at least, with Matomo we're more similar than we are with Google Analytics, which we
pretty much have nothing with, so Matomo and I can see, this is the post I wrote a couple
years ago, I can see Matomo was founded in 2007, so that's very, very earlier than us
and it's installed on 1.9% of all the websites currently, but we're like, we just started
showing on those lists, like built with and so on, we're on 0.1 at this stage, so that's
one of the big differences, like we're tiny currently, but there are some similarities
as well, which we don't have with Google Analytics at least, but we have with Matomo, so basically
both teams, both tools are fully open source, us like Matomo, everything is a GitHub, you
can do whatever you want with it, self-host it and so on, we are also developing everything
in open, both of us, so all the code is in there, you can go similar to, like you can
go on Matomo, you can create issues, start discussions, ask us for like, would you guys
introduce this or even contribute to the products, everything is there in the open, you can see
how we make decisions, what people think we should build next, people voting and so on,
and the other one that a lot of people like is the complete control of all the data, so
similar to Matomo, we don't share your data with anyone, we don't sell it to anyone, we
don't, unlike Google Analytics, we don't use it for any other purposes, there's no ad business
here, we have nothing to do with surveillance, capitalism and so on, so basically your data
is your data, we don't really, we're just here to kind of help you make sense of it
and help you count it, and then what you do with it is not our business, so basically
if all these things are the same and similar to Matomo, what are the differences from the
two?
So one big one that a lot of people like is the simplicity aspect, so basically if you
look at Matomo, it's, for someone like me that's a marketer, it's pretty much like a
full-blown alternative to Google Analytics, you know, you have hundreds of reports, you
have all the, you can do, you can track pretty much everything in Matomo as you can do in
Google Analytics, which is not the case for Closable, we have one report, one page, everything
is there on that one page, there's nothing extra you can do, I will show you in a bit,
but basically they're built without simplicity and ease of view is in mind, which is something
that a lot of people were missing when looking at Google Analytics especially, it's like
a lot of people are like, you know, having to hire people to explain them or build custom
dashboards for them, having to go to training and so on, like there's no need for any without
the Closable, it's just one simple screen.
That also, the fact that we're so simple and we don't track many things also means that
our script is very lightweight, that's another difference from Matomo and for Google Analytics,
Google Analytics is much more heavier than Matomo, so there's a bigger difference there,
but at least from Matomo's perspective, last time I checked, the script was about 22 kilobytes
while our script is less than one kilobyte, so there's that little difference in terms
of how much, how fast your site can load or how much electricity you will have to use
with all the visitors and so on, and then the last one, the other one, the one that's
kind of become more important over the last few years with all these privacy regulations
in mind is that the Closable is built from scratch to be as privacy first as possible,
so the reason we don't have any of the stats and metrics that you can look at is because
we don't track many of those things, and why don't we track them?
Because of privacy first aspects, so there's no cookies, there's no long-term identifiers,
there's no way to track people across different websites, there's no way to track people across
different devices that they have, so all that is inbuilt in Closable by default, Matomo
has them as well, you can, you know, there's steps on the Matomos website which you can
kind of follow and kind of get something similar to what we have kind of out of the box, but
basically that's one big difference is like we do that for you immediately, and there's
no kind of less privacy version of Closable, you just get what you provide by default.
Okay, so what we can do right now is quickly run through the dashboard itself, we open
all of our own stats, so if you go to our website Closable.io and click on live demo,
you will be able to see the same stats that I can see as a co-founder of Closable, it's
all there all around, all visitors are on your app out there in the public, and this
is our dashboard, it's this one page that I mentioned before, this is pretty much it,
there's nothing else.
At the top, you have the current visitors, which you can click on to get to our like
a real-time report, which is pretty much the same as what you saw previously, but just
for the last 30 minutes, so let's go back to our main report here.
So basically, our normal dashboard is this one, and do you have the live, like a date
picker here, like what I was doing right now, and these numbers, these letters on the right
are our keyboard shortcuts, so say I do D, I will go to today, I do N month to date,
Y year to date, and so on.
We have these little arrows as well that you can use it then go back and forward depending
on where you were before, so if you're on today, you click on it, you go back to yesterday
and so on.
There is the custom range as well, which is you basically select whatever manual time
period that you want.
Filter as well, like everything that we do further down on the page is also filterable,
so you can get to it here if you prefer, kind of like a quicker way, some people prefer
it that way.
Then we get to our main chart, the only chart we have, the only graph is this one, we have
four metrics in it for now, unique visitors, total page use, bounce rate, visit duration,
you can actually click on them to get the different metrics displayed on the graph,
you can deselect it all and then you kind of get no graphs, so you get even smaller
dashboard then.
Here on the right is a little download icon, which means that whatever you're looking at
here in the report, you click on it, you get a CSV export with all those reports of your
current view, so right now I'm on today, if I click on it, I just get the today's view,
if I was on month to date or last month or whatever, I will just get those reports then.
So what do we have further down?
Further down on the left, we have top sources, everything that you expect, we use the referral
header to see where your traffic is coming from, you can click on the details button,
then that kind of expands and you can see the bounce rate and visit duration of the
different sources.
You can also even, you can click say GitHub, you can click and then you would, your dashboard
is then filtered by the source GitHub and your dashboard now only shows traffic, you
know, people that arrive to your website from GitHub itself, I'm pressing the escape key
right now to get back to the main view.
Next in the top sources, we also have campaigns, so that's basically all your UTMs, all of
them are there and they kind of support the same, you can click to filter your dashboard
by a specific UTM source and see all the traffic that came to your website from that specific
campaign you've been doing and whatever else they did on your site, again, clicking on
escape to go back to the main view.
On the right of top sources, we have top pages, that is all the pages on your website that
your visitors have viewed, again, even there you can click on details, then you can get
page views, bounce rate and time on page metrics as well for all the pages, you can click on
any specific page and then your dashboard is again filtered by that specific page and
now we are only showing the traffic that actually went to this specific slash settings page
on our website.
We also have entry pages reports, that's similar to what previously what we saw in top pages
but now we're just showing the entry pages, so basically the pages that people started
their session with, again, the same, you can click on details or you can then click on
and select a specific page and now your dashboard is filtered only by people that started their
session on this specific page on your website.
Same with exit pages pretty much, now we have the pages that people exit your site from,
if you click on details, you will now also see the exit rate and total number of exits
similar to what you can do in entry pages where clicking on details gives you total
entrances and visit duration too.
So those are the top sections, if we go further down, we have the location report, that gives
you a little chart by default, you can click on anything specific in the chart to visit
that specific country, so now the dashboard is filtered only by people that are based
in the U.S. and what happens then is that you can see regions or states in the case
of U.S. and if you go even further, you can see the cities, so people are visiting from,
so now I can go countries U.S., state is California and then cities Los Angeles and now I have
three filters up here, which means that what I'm looking at now is the dashboard for October
2022 and I'm only displaying people coming from U.S., California and the city of L.A.,
so now everything you see in the dashboard is just those people.
I can click on the escape button again to get back to the main view, the regions, countries
and cities work the same way, so when you press on the details button, you can see the
expanded list of everything else and depending on which you select, you can then see something
different or some different metrics, such as the percentage of visitors coming from
that location.
Next up on the right-hand side of countries is devices, we start with the desktop mobile
laptop tablet, but then you can click on the browser tab here, so now you can see actually
the browser that people are using, you can actually click on say Chrome and then we have
the different versions of Chrome and now I can click on Chrome 107, so now we are only
seeing the traffic on our website using Chrome version 107.
You can go to OS, which is the last tab on the devices report and that then shows operating
systems which works in the same way as we saw with the browser, so I can basically click
on Mac and say 1014 and now the dashboard is filtered by those people only and for example
I can say top source is Google, so now we are seeing people that arrive to our website
from Google search results that are using a Mac with a Mac version of 1014, that's basically
what we are seeing now in the whole dashboard.
Next up is the next section is pretty much different from website to website, by default
we don't track any goals, but so when you start using plausible, you can set up any
goals that you want and something that we have set up on our own website right now is
that you can visit, we are tracking people that are visiting our blog, so I can see when
I click on this and now the dashboard is visited by people that have visited the blog and I
can see now the top blog post that people have read during this time period that we
are looking at.
We are also tracking in the goals, we are also tracking the number of sign ups, so that
basically now shows you the number of trial sign ups on our own website, we are tracking
that as one of the goals and now my dashboard is only filtered by the people that actually
signed up for the product.
We are also tracking the number of upgrades, so again we are a SaaS startup and our subscribers
is basically what funds us because we have no investors, so we are now tracking how many
people are actually joining the platform and finding it interesting enough, valuable enough
to pay for it, so now we can see the number of sign ups in October 2022, which is 565,
so that we track too and the last one we track is newsletter sign ups, so on some of our
blog posts we have a newsletter link, so some people choose to subscribe to that and get
the latest blog post sent via email, but this like I mentioned will be empty when you sign
up and what happens is that you can create what you want from it.
So what we can do is go to our documentation and in the documentation section there is
the goal conversion section, which basically explains what that section does and what we
do have, we have page view goals, kind of similar to our goals for the blog visitors,
like you can combine different dynamically created pages, for example the e-commerce
check out pages and so on and create a page view goal for them, they have custom events
and that basically is everything such as what we do for trial sign ups and subscriptions,
you can track any individual element on your website using that and then after getting
a lot of feedback from people, we decided to create some very simple ones that you can
kind of automatically use, so basically we have very easy way to count outbound link
clicks, so any clicks on your external links, we do the same for file downloads, so we can
easily count the number of clicks on PDF file and so on, same for your 404 error pages,
so you can easily install it, so Plausible just automatically counts visits on 404 pages,
we can do the same for clogged and fielded links and people that use pretty links in
general, we can track those too.
This is pretty much the view of what Plausible does, it's in the filter, you can kind of
do a couple of different things that you cannot really do in the rest of the dashboard, so
say we go filter by page, you can actually select is not, so say I can go filter by page
is not slash sites, so now we're watching the dashboard, people that have not visited
the slash sites page, that's what we're seeing right now, this filter also has the contains,
so we can say okay, let's show everything that contains blog, and so we will go, and
now we're showing all the pages that contain the word blog in their URLs, this works the
same way for say locations and all the other metrics, so we can go country is not, and
then we can go say United States and say filter, and now we're showing the dashboard of everyone
except for visitors from the U.S., and then all the metrics that we discussed are now
showing only those that are not from the U.S., and you can go, again, you can add anything
else you want at the same time, so adding this trip means that we now are showing the
dashboard of people that are not from U.S., that are using Mac, and that arrived to our
website from GitHub as the referral source.
You can press the escape key again, and now we're back to the main view, press D, I'm
back on today, I can see today this is our traffic for the day, and that's pretty much
the demo of Plausible, like I mentioned, we really focus on simplicity, ease of use, so
you don't need to have any kind of training to use Plausible, and really on privacy aspects,
which means that we're kind of limited in what we can track, because that's how we want
to build the tool, if we want it to be privacy first, which also helps us being very lightweight,
so our goal is always to keep the script that you insert into your site at less than one
kilobyte, which we currently are at, and hopefully that can continue for a long time.
Yeah, so this is my brief overview of what Plausible does.
I don't know if there's any questions from the audience, or anything else I can answer,
that we can do now.
So there have been some questions in the chat, which I'm also pasting here.
So Jochaim asks, Plausible tracks information about display size, but this isn't allowed
under German law, TTDSG, did you plan to disable this by option?
Yeah, there's actually on our GitHub, in the pull request, there's a pull request that's
actually, right now we're taking the device sizes from the browser screen, like the browser
window, but there is a pull request that is suggested that we change that to use the user
agent instead, so that's something that's in works in their own GitHub, and that's something
that we plan to change in the future.
Right now basically, the way it's shown right now, it's like if I visit a website, and if
I change my browser to be smaller, I might fit into a mobile, say even though I'm on
a desktop, so that's because we're using the browser as the way to decide what screen size
you're on.
This was made because early on there was a lot of designers that wanted to use Plausible,
and the reason was that they preferred to know what browser width people are viewing
their site on, they don't care as much about the device itself, the size, they care about
more like, are they viewing it to like half screen or full screen and so on, and this
is how it's built until now.
Okay, awesome.
Another question was, did you plan to include MTM campaign keywords for tracking?
This would be great to compare with Matomo tracking.
No, nobody has asked for this feature before, so it's not something that's on our radar
currently.
We just use UTM tags for now, but you know, like everything else that we do, when people
come to our GitHub and add a feature request saying, oh, you guys should add this and kind
of tell us the explanation why and send us a link or two, then if enough people upvote
it in our forum, they're on GitHub, then that will automatically be placed more prominently
in our own product backlog, so then our developers then are looking like, what's next thing to
build?
We can rank those feature requests by popularity, by upvotes, and we're like, okay, this is
now number two feature that we're missing to the second most popular, and that will
automatically mean that we will put it higher up our list as well and we will build it faster.
So everything is kind of until now has been done in that way.
We listen to the audience, to what people tell us, and kind of the upvoting and kind
of what's more popular, we try to build that next.
Okay, awesome, somebody's still typing on the chat.
Okay, we have it.
Do you get blocked as malware or add blockers by Avast, by Microsoft Edge, et cetera?
Not the malware.
Not from what I've, I have not heard this reported.
What does happen is that we do get blocked by ad blockers.
So like if you're using, say, uBlock Origin on Firefox, by default, I think easy primacy
list would include plausible.io as a domain name to block, and they will also include
things such as plausible.js to block, pretty much similar to what happens to Matomos.
So that is what happens because ad blockers have decided to block every tracking script,
good or bad, or less privacy, more privacy, they block them all.
And we're kind of putting that category.
So Matomo will be blocked, GA will be blocked, Plus will be blocked too.
On our docs, we have something that we call a proxy, and that allows you to actually,
for those people that want to, we basically, we're very upfront about this, we tell people,
you can use our default script, but that means that you, it will be blocked by people that
use ad blockers, and in our own testing, between six and 26% of people are blocking scripts
by using ad blockers.
And then you just know that, okay, I'm using default script, but maybe I'm not getting
100% of the visitors, but that's also the case for Matomo, Google Analytics, and everyone
else, so I'm blocking that.
But then we've also said, are you concerned about this?
Would you actually try to track something more accurately?
And then we provided the option to do a proxy.
So basically, you will be running plausible from your own domain name, which means then
that the fact that our domain name is blocked on block lists would mean that your domain
is not blocked, and you will be able to count also people that use ad blockers.
So basically, I've asked Microsoft question, I've never heard that that will be blocked
by malware, so that's not the case, but definitely ad blockers themselves, they're more the ones
that you would use in browsers, such as uBlock Origin, I don't know the other names, but
basically they would be, some of them at least, will be blocking our domain name and our script,
which means that those visitors won't be counted by default.
Okay, let's just wait one more minute if somebody else wants to drop question.
Sure.
In general, for a lot of questions there, they'll be answered in our docs.
So that's what I've been using a couple of times during this presentation.
But basically everything will be in there, such as, you know, if you want to invite your
team members, assigned roles, we have a section in the docs, you know, how you can do that,
you know, how you can embed your dashboard on another website using the iframe.
So that will be there, you know, instructions for that as well.
So basically, we've tried to build a lot of these useful features that people have asked
us for, and they're part of the docs and part of your site settings when you log into your
account.
You know, for example, one interesting thing is that you can open up your stats to the
public.
So similar to what we've done on our own website, you can do the same for you.
You can actually, with one click, you'll be able to set your...
So I'm going to go into the site settings here to actually show how that works.
But basically, with one click, I can enable my stats to be shown in public.
So basically, that's a cool little feature.
Basically, we have another thing is the Search Console integration.
So you could integrate plausible with Search Console.
So when you go to your dashboard, then what you see on the Google, if you actually click
on Google, in your top sources, and you go to a longer time period where Google has data
or you will then be able to see what search terms people arrive to your site with.
But basically, there's a lot of these kind of additional features we have, and they will
be documented in the docs.
We have our trial.
There's a free trial of 30 days if people are interested.
There's also the, obviously, completely free as in beer, self-hosted version people can
install.
Recently, one of the big things was that people asked us for Google Analytics import.
We didn't have it a few months ago, but we ended up spending, I think, more than six
months of development time.
And now it's online.
So basically, if you're one of those that wants to escape from Google Analytics these
days, especially ahead of Universal Analytics being shut down, I think June, July next year,
there's now a way to do that and import your data into plausible because Google doesn't
allow you to import the data into GA4.
Yeah, so that's basically we have the APIs.
Another thing that's not kind of prominent in the dashboard itself is that you have the
States API, which allows you to take any of the stats programmatically.
We have the Events API.
So say you want to use Plasmo without JavaScript or you want to track your mobile apps, you
can do that through the Events API or the Sites API, which allows you to add sites,
delete sites, create goals, all that kind of stuff just programmatically.
So for example, several SaaS businesses are using plausible as their web analyst provider.
So then they will be using things such as Sites API to create websites for the clients.
Then they will create these shared dashboards that they can embed on their sites in their
own UI or they're using the Sites API where they can take individual metrics and place
them directly in their UI.
So they can, if they don't want to show our default dashboard as it is, they're just going
to, okay, I'm just going to show the number of visitors in this part of my UI or I want
to show the top pages here.
They can do that through the Sites API itself.
Another maybe another thing to mention, the recent change that we did is all those European
countries that have said that Google is illegal because of them being a US owned company and
using US owned cloud infrastructure, plausible, at least the plausible IO version, which we
run in the managed hosting, it's fully European owned and we only exclusively use European
owned infrastructure.
So that will mean Hezner and Bunny rather than AWS or whatever else people are using.
So that's another kind of feature, I guess we can say, in plausible that may not be there
in some other tools.
Awesome.
Thank you very much, Marco, for your lovely presentation and for joining us today.
You're welcome.
Thank you very much for the invite.