Okay. So it's currently 5 p.m. and that's the end of the first in the history Matomo
camp event. So this last conference will not last 30 minutes, but maybe if we have a lot
of things to say, it can go up to 30 minutes, but probably I guess that we're going to make
it in 10 minutes. Just probably the simplest word to say is thank you. Thanks for having
it done so far. That was a really dense event. Two full days, many different speakers. Here
are some KPIs. By the way, feel free to go on chat.matomocamp.org. You have a specific
room for this last conference. And I'm closing a ceremony on which you can just say thank
you or just give feedback about the event. Just a couple of KPIs that we wanted to show
you guys. So we went for two days of talks. Three languages. So we got talk in English.
Mostly in English. Some in German the first day and some in French in the second and the
first day. It was mainly English and German. We got 26 conferences in total. For a total
of 26 recordings. Representing at the mid journey of today, those recordings were representing
already more than 10 gigabytes. So I guess the ended result will be close to 15 gigabytes.
We got 24 speakers. We would like to send them once more because I viewed half of the
conferences and I was really impressed of the level of all of them. Whatever the topic,
whatever the expertise was about, it was really impressive. Up to 1 p.m. we had a number of
804 visits on live.matomocamp.org for the two days. I recently watched back the numbers
and it was around 930 visits on the two days. And let's say optimistic goal forecast for
this event was at 1,000 visits. So to say these events went beyond our expectation.
It was really a remarkable event in terms of content brought by the speakers. But as
well in terms of visitors on the website visits. Even if we don't have, we don't put in place
any system to measure the number of individuals. So I guess the 900 visits that I'm referring
to doesn't represent 900 individuals. But I guess we are getting close to these figures.
On chat.matomocamp.org, same thing measured here. It was only for the first day and a
half. We got 95 users who make an effort of creating an account on chat.matomocamp.org
in order to interact with us, which is a lot. We used another KPI during the pre-event,
which was held one month ago. This was the number of IP connected to the stream. For
the pre-event, we got 28 IP connections. And today at 1 p.m., including everything which
was made the day before, we were up to 385 individual IP connected. Taking into account
that we have some people who are coming from the same institution or company. Of course,
those IP does not relate to one individual, but probably in some cases to more than this.
42 is the funny number. In fact, now it came to 43 is the number of unread emails that
we'll have to deal with over the weekend due to the fact that I was fully busy for this
event. I hope that for all the other organizers, it's not that many because 42 means for me
probably one full day of answering all those emails. But that's part of the game when you
are part of a big organization such as such as MatomoCamp. In terms of other KPIs, 45
countries were represented during this MatomoCamp. So according to Matomo's data, the
attendees were mainly from Germany, then from Sweden, then from France, then from the United
Kingdom, and then the Netherlands. And I'm happy to announce that we got visitors from
all the continents. As you can see on the maps, of course, mainly Europe, because the
time zone were more convenient for people based in Europe. But we really had all the
nationality which were represented. I was really impressed to see so many flags within
the Matomo system that I looked at some hours ago. So I really would like to thank all the
attendees from all over the world. What's next after this event? Well, we're going
to let's say gather all the organizing committees of the MatomoCamp in order to define and
see how they react to the event, what they like, what they dislike. Maybe we will launch
another survey. I don't know. We just need to plan a meeting in order to see, okay, how
did you like it? And after, we will of course see if we want to go for another version of
MatomoCamp. Do we need to think as well about local events? For example, I was really surprised
the first day to see a lot of people coming from Nordic countries, Denmark, Norway, Sweden.
So I don't know. There may be some spaces in order to have a MatomoCamp version for
Nordic countries, but as well for Germany, Sweden, as we just saw was a huge part of
the visitors. Maybe France. I don't know. This really depends on, in fact, all the attendees
that we had today, so as the people within the organizing committee to see in which sense
we would like the Matomo community to evolve. But we don't have any plan at the moment.
Just would like to say that if you would like to join the super team that we had the chance
to have this year for this MatomoCamp, please feel free to contact us through matomocamp.org.
Some people informed us that the contact form on our website was not working. It's a bit
more complicated than this, just that you need to push several times on the button.
I had the same feeling this morning when I tested it. I had the feeling that it wasn't
working and then I pressed it twice and then the mail was sent. So, yes, the matomocamp.org
contact form is still the way to contact us. If you don't receive an answer by your team,
just send another one and good chance. We are answering to everything except spam, so
you, of course, will receive an answer. If you don't receive it in the proper time, feel
free to send another one or try to connect to us through another web by your different
name. The names are the ones that you can see here. So, I really would like to thank
all the members of the organizing team. I really apologize if I miss anyone here. For
example, Marcus Asenberger is probably the one who did the more apologizes because I
forgot to mention him during the opening ceremony. So, thank you, Marcus, for being part of the
Matomo organizing team. Today, Marcus, today and yesterday, Marcus was here in order to
do the moderation of the different conferences. This event could not have been without Lukas
Winkler, who is the guy who took on his shoulders a huge amount, an impressive amount of work.
He was here all the time where I could not manage anything anymore because I didn't have
more time, I didn't have more energy, and he's really the guy who is doing kind of everything
within MatomoCamp. So, I really would like to thank him. Silva, as well, joined the team
during the evolution of the creation of MatomoCamp. She was the one in charge of the moderation
of the different talks, so as all the communication part. I would like to thank, as well, Stéphane
Konig from the Netherlands, Peter Borg, who helped us with all the system administration
and IT infrastructure. Frédéric, as well, was here for the moderation of the talk in
French. A huge, huge thanks to Emprunt Digital, to Valentin Bares, who is the one who holds
all the different streams. And thanks to him that we will get the recording of all the
different conferences. I would like to thank, as well, all the digitalists, the AAB team,
and in particular, Thomas Pearson, that some of the attendees have seen many times. I'm
not 100% sure about the number of talks that he made, but I think it's close to five, and
they were all incredible. So, thank you very much, Thomas. I would like to thank, as well,
Stéphane Gill, Thomas Zeithnamerl, and Joachim Neckel for the organizing team. Lukas, am
I missing anyone here within the organizing team?
I can't think of anyone at the moment. Hopefully, I also don't miss anyone.
I would like to thank, again, all the speakers. They were coming from all the different countries.
They have made all great and impressive speeches. Of course, Lukas Winkler, Joachim Neckel,
Richard Stark from the InnoCrafts company was making the conference with a time zone
difference of 12 hours from New Zealand, Jorge Powers from the Digitalist AAB team in Sweden,
Thomas Ekman from Germany, Nathan Freitas, Silva Arapi, as well. The Italian team represented
by Davide Porovecchio, Pier Luigi Tassi, Claudio Czelligin, Thomas Czernik, Stéphane Konig,
Peter Buhelke, Thomas Pearson, Christian Hallner, Valentin Bares, Baptiste Steven, Victor Vexei
from Hungary, Boris Budini, Frédéric Forster, Aurélie Pauls, Cathy Newbay from the United
Kingdom, and Ronan Elow. Sorry, Lukas, same questions again. Did I
forget anyone here within this list? I hope you didn't.
I'm sorry for my pronunciation as well. I would like, once more, to thank our sponsors,
so Matomo, who, once more, allow us to create and use a logo which is similar to theirs
and as well allow us to use Matomo within our communication support, who as well supported
us in terms of communication. So, probably without their communication impact, we couldn't
have reached you today, or at least some of you guys. So, I would like, once more, to
say thank you, Matomo, and of course to provide the world with a free software and a GPL license.
I would like to thank, as well, Empreinte Digital, who, as I said, are the one in charge
of all the streaming parts. I would like to thank, once more, the company of Stefan König,
who missed analytics, so as Sonora from Peter Voelker and Stairs from Ligue 1. And many
others, as well, that I would like to thank, who, as I said, many organizers who have been
speakers during this MatomoCamp and who have spent a lot of time and energy within this
project. And, of course, yes, I can answer shortly. Of course, the one organizer you
forgot to mention is, of course, you, Roland, who initially had the idea to organize a Matomo
camp and were the one getting everything started and planning the whole concept from the beginning.
So thanks again for this. Yeah, thank you. Thank you so much. I have to say that I couldn't
have made it without all of you guys and without all, let's say, the IT, free software technology
expertise. I have to say that by myself, even with all the energy that I could brought into
it, it's... I just put the energy of someone who wants to create an event and that's it.
Thank you. Thank you very much. I appreciate it. And, of course, thank you to all of you,
our attendees, because it's always hard to find some time on our working time to come
and assist all those conferences. Thank you for all your kindness because we didn't have
any trolling experience on the social networks. You have been all nice to each other through
the chat. You played the game. You accepted to post some questions on chat.matomo.org.
You sent some questions. And to the question that most of you will probably ask are where
the materials are of the speakers and where the recording of the talks are. Well, the
recording of the talks, correct me if I'm wrong, Lukas, but they will be posted on the
URL named videos.matomocamp.org within the coming days, am I right?
Yeah, we will set up the video platform in the next days and editing all the recordings,
of course, will take some time and we will just go on and publish them once they're ready.
So if you follow us on the social media accounts or if you look on the video platform every
few days, you will be notified whenever a new recording is published.
So yeah, if you just refresh matomocamp.org webpage from time to time, if you follow us
on the social network, good chances that we will announce at some point that the videos
are live. You can already find one, which is the one about the pre-matomo camp event.
And if you have some time, I invite you to break meet.matomocamp.org, which is the based
on work adventure, which is a social place on which you can move and meet the different
people who are connected on the platform and then interact with them in real time in video
and webcam.
And I'm going to go there in something like two minutes once I finish this slide. And
I really hope that I will have the opportunity to meet some of you guys there and to connect
a little bit more like if we were in a physical presence. Lukas, Valentin, do you have any
any things left that you would like to say before we close officially the event?
Nothing major for me. Just thanks everyone for making this event possible and such a
huge success as it was.
Same for me. Just thank you for your time. All of your speakers and Lukas, especially.
Perfect. Thank you guys. Take care of you. Have a good weekend. And for the one who still
have time, just go on meet.matomocamp.org and we will be there in order to party. Have
a great weekend and thanks for spending some time with us at Matomocamp. Bye.