So, everyone, thank you for attending this session.
Today we will have Jorge Powers, who has been working for 10 years with analytics, CO, development
and DevOps.
His talk today is how to manage Omatomo with millions of page views per month, where he
will tell us more about their work at Digitalist Sweden, a company which manages some of the
biggest Omatomo installations in Sweden.
So I'm giving the word to Jorge now.
Thank you.
As you heard, I've been working with analytics for many years.
I've been programming since I was a kid in the 90s, but I started professionally about
11, 12 years ago, working mostly as a front-ender from the beginning, but yeah, I wouldn't label
me as front-end, back-end or SEO expert.
I'm a generalist and I'm wherever I needed, so I'm a problem solver, you could call me.
I have recently been on parental leave, so I'm just back working, so this presentation
is put together recently, so bear with me, but I'm sure I can get any questions if you
have any.
Yeah, let's move on.
So I work for Digitalist now, I've been here for six years, and I've been working with
the DevOps team, I've been project manager, and I've been working with Omatomo for three
or four years now in Digitalist.
So what am I going to talk about?
And we started with Omatomo, it was still called PIVIC, and everyone knows that GDPR
in 2018 was getting in effect, so the government agencies in Sweden were very good at how to
track the data and take ownership of the data.
So the Swedish tax agency, Skatteverket, they had a procurement and reached out to
us and asked us if we knew Omatomo, and we have had PIVIC installations running for probably
ten years, so, but we were no experts yet, and we took on this, and yeah, so a little
bit of the story, Sweden, it's a small country in Europe, if you look at the population,
but still we have a million plus population in Sweden, and the fiscal declaration, I mean
Sweden is very progressive when it comes to digitalization, and in 2021, 4.5 million people
did their fiscal declaration online, and all of those people went into this declaration,
and they have other online services as well and other websites, so a lot of traffic into
their sites, and if you look at the timeline here and you think how big applications were
driven back in the days, the entire app would run on a server, Apache or some kind of services,
and then in 2014 Kubernetes came in and changed how the landscape of applications are deployed
today, so, and we signed with Skatteverket just before 2018, and so we had a bit of time
before May 25th, I think it was the date when GDPR was in effect, and at this time, if you
downloaded the source code to PIVIC, like it was called back in the day, you could go
to the online documentation and you see that it's a LAMP stack basically, so you have Linux,
Apache, MySQL, and PHP, and for us, this is, yeah, we've been working with open source
for 20 years or so, so this is a very familiar area for us, but the challenge here, because
Kubernetes was open sourced in 2014, and yeah, it was a little clear how to host this big
installation where we knew that we were going to have a lot of traffic, so we put together
a team of our engineers to try to figure out the best option to go forward, yeah, until
2019, we could find more documentation on the Matomo website to run a big installation
for 100 million page views per month or less, but this is similar to the conclusion we came
up with at the time, but when it comes to running this and monitoring and so on, there's
still challenges, we can't just deploy some service and hope it will run for a long time,
so we started to sketch our own infrastructure with guidance from the Matomo documentation,
of course. At the time when we installed Matomo, MariaDB was still supported by Matomo, and
I'm going to come back to that later, but how should we build a big application? A monolithic
application you could say is where everything is compiled into source code and you will
put it on a server and it will just sit there and run the whole application by itself, which
you have services, you have the things that you see and the communication layer and the
database basically, or microservices, so these were the options we were looking at the time
and of course we can't deny that we had requirements from our clients, and now I'm imagining that
there's a big crowd out there and you've probably seen a Rocky Horror Picture Show or something
where the audience shout out the boo or whatever, so we had for example backups, we need to
have backups, we need to have redundancy, we need to have security certified hosting,
we need to have the status of the application, we need to have scalability because everyone
doesn't go in to do their physical declaration once a month, this is something you do once
a year probably. You need to be able to restore the systems if it goes down, you need to have
a certified standards, you need to be able to roll back and we need high availability
so that people from all over Sweden can go in and do their declarations basically. So
we went through our hosting partner, we've been working with for many years and they
are certified Kubernetes, the only one certified Kubernetes in the Nordics at the time, so
they were of course proposing that we should run this on Kubernetes because it's the next
big thing and that's in tech. We wanted to go with the Kubernetes setup and for us it
was a black box, it's not the traditional way you should think about certain applications
so we threw it to someone else, the works in Digitalis, we took some crash courses in
Kubernetes and looking back at it now and I remember I was thinking like it was a big
question mark in my head at the time but as more we dig into Kubernetes and everything
around Kubernetes, everything became more clear. So you need to throw everything you
know about servers and hosting out the window and you need to rethink how you think about
applications and services. So this is a picture I took from the Kubernetes website and you
can see the traditional deployment, you have something similar to the three-tire architecture
or you can have VPSs and you could have Docker or some kind of auto scaling hosting, can't
remember the name you call it or you could have like running container like microservices.
So if you want to know what Kubernetes is in depth to the Kubernetes web page and there
is a lot of documentation you can read but basically the things that we get out of the
box here to meet the requirements was that we could have rollbacks, auto rollbacks, we
can have real-time updates or raw updates and this means basically we can do the application
without taking down the service. So if Skatteverke for example they have let's say a hundred
data analysts and they go in and they work office time you know nine to five and we don't
want to take down the application just if you want to run out if we want to deploy some
configuration. So this needs to be very careful doing upgrades. Yeah so at the time because
we were new to Kubernetes we had our partner Elastics they come up with the architecture
so this is what it looked like from the start you could say we have changed some bits through
the years but the basic concept still and so when a user either if you go into the dashboard
as an analyst you get to one container you could say or if you have installed your tracking
script the tracking data will be sending into servers. So this is how we can scale up and
down depending on where the load is in the application. And of course when you dissect
a big application like Matomo you're going to run into some challenges and I would say
the biggest challenge at the time was configuring the database to handle all the load that was
coming in and we could use many of the community everything was open source by the way I forgot
to mention that but we are an open source company first of all so we like open source.
We like to keep our infrastructure as code and the best way of doing that at the time
with the help from our partner Elastics they come up with Helm. So Helm is a way to keep
your charts as they call them the templates for your infrastructure. So this is how we
can easily tweak bits and pieces of the application without having to access to a server and go
in manually and change something. So every change needs to be documented so we can do
this in our version controlling system with Git. Yeah so this is Helm and of course we
have requirements as like you can't ship out code deploy code that have vulnerabilities
in them. So we had to figure out some kind of CI CD workflow where we can automate stuff
and because you can't really track all the vulnerabilities that come up all the time.
So we automate as much as possible. We have a drone. A drone is a CI service where you
can plug in different kind of applications third party system that will check your code
your base code. So if you package all your Matomo into a container in Docker let's say
and all the underlying system applications that are in this Docker image drone will start
service and then we will use something that is called Clare which is the next slide here
and also it's an open source service that will check for vulnerabilities. So everything
is running containers. So before we deploy something out to our production site this
will run up a similar environment where it will check for vulnerabilities and when we
get a green light then we can do the deploy to the production and of course being an open
source company and how much the community means for us we have also open sourced our
Helm base setup so anyone can take our work and replicate what we have done. If you go
to our GitHub you can find the Matomo Kubernetes base setup that we are using. Of course there
are other dependencies so we use this as a base and then we have a different project
where we open up every client we have. Of course dissecting an application like Matomo
you want to have control you want to automate as much as possible so we are dependent on
the CLI tools which at the time we couldn't use we can add new users so every deploy basically
we destroy everything and we build a whole and if you know Matomo and how to install
it basically it's a clean install every time so to be able to keep our database without
wiping it and we had to come up with different CLI tools to automate some of the stuff so
and we have contributed this back to the community and we have some plugins in the Matomo marketplace
one of them we use is the user console but also most importantly I would say the extra
tools where we can automate a lot of things like DB backups or installation of Matomo
and I took the screenshot yesterday and it's been downloaded over 4,900 times I think that's
fantastic. Yeah and this is more abstract overview of our application this is more...
So in Kubernetes world you have called a pod and a pod can run multiple containers and
you can have different pods so for example if you want to run the core archive job as
the presentation before me you mentioned the core archive in the if you go into the server
and you use the CLI tool you can run the archive command and in a cron job in Kubernetes world
this is called a job just a job yeah so and because of the high load or the millions of
page views every month a single core job wasn't enough for us so we tried to come up with
different ways of running this which has led into other problems too and we have learned
a lot during the years so and we have had discussions with the Matomo team to how to
solve this properly the correct way and yeah I bet they have run into similar issues like
we have and but they have probably solved them differently. Yeah of course monitoring
is important to know when you need to scale up or scale down your applications so of course
we use with Kubernetes it's very standard to use Prometheus that will check status and
we use Grafana to visualize the metrics which is another tool very like Kibana if you're
used to Kibana or Elastic Stack so yeah jumping into Kubernetes was a lot of fun but it's
a lot to dig into because you need to know about a lot of stuff so fun yeah so just to
give you a hint of how much how many page views we're dealing with here so I tweaked
the numbers a little bit so I don't want to give away the real numbers but this is very
like the real deal we have also other clients with even more data than this so we know what
we're doing we have done this for many years now and if you look here the fiscal declaration
for the Swedish tax payers it's opens up in Mars and you can see there's a peak because
everyone wants to go in and to see their tax returns if they're getting anything or if
they need to pay more taxes so this is something we can prepare for and we can scale up our
services we can also under the hood we can also add more servers or hardware if you want
so that's possible too so we but doing a migration that's something I would not recommend for
anyone so if you want a big motormist you can advance so you have enough hardware in
place because doing a migration is a tough project and so here's a little peak from one
of our time where we override the values in our helm charts so this is something where
we can prepare like is the fiscal declaration is coming up in its opening we know that we
can we can add more replicas to the dashboard or to the tracker pods and if you look behind
the red line you see also one of the console commands this is also one of the challenges
we had because we couldn't at the time we couldn't use a read write many NFS folder
so we had to come up with an idea how to regenerate tag manager containers so this is a way you
can do that in the Kubernetes setup is to run the command so this is where the console
commands are so important for us yeah we can also add more CPU more memory to each pod
or group of pods I wouldn't recommend to do it individually per pod but you can you have
a basic template and then you can tweak that for different services we have one that is
tracking the tracking data is sent into a Redis middle layer where it stores because
if the database is too busy we need to keep the data so it doesn't disappear or take down
the database so this is how we can queue tracking service and this is a peak from the beginning
we would only use CLI tools but now the bigger we get and the bigger the team gets we need
to automate a lot of stuff this is a CICD workflow tools and there's called OCD which
I think it's really awesome also open source of course where we can go in and see all the
pods in a nice graphic view and can check logs or we can see the health the status and
green heart means that everything is operational and running you see the magnitude of the pods
or the microservices there is running in the background and yeah and this is a tool that
I like that I've been using a lot through the years it's a K9 and it's a nice CLI visualization
tool to see the health and status of your cluster so I can highly recommend to use K9s
if you're more into sitting in a terminal than having a graphical overview yeah so the
challenges we had through the years was the DB configuration and jumping into trying
to debug a black box from the beginning to find throttles or bottlenecks in our application
yeah it was yeah some of the ways we do it now we have added more shared all of those
to the community yet because they're not ready for days I would say but we get enough of
data to find if we want to run a MySQL tuner to check the health of the database we have
automated a lot of stuff to do that nowadays and from the beginning MariaDB being an open
source company and the fact that MySQL wasn't no longer open source or it was open source
but kind of because they were acquired by Oracle we chose MariaDB and when Matomo added
more features 2019 I think to run big Matomo installations they wouldn't support MariaDB
and that was very frustrating sometimes I did a patch so I can do stuff now today that
we couldn't do in MariaDB back then and then of course the core archives having a lot of
data and one of my colleagues Thomas is going to talk more about some of the challenges
we had or how you can break Matomo I think his session name is the title of his session
and I would recommend to join his sessions because yeah he will talk more in detail how
to break core archives and we had problems from the beginning with forms they would automatically
include in every site that you put up in Matomo and that gave us a little bit of headache
but we have dealt with that and the segments go hand in hand with core archives I would
say because the Matomo features in the UI and having a lot of analysts working there
and putting up their own segments with queries that are getting a lot of data from the database
could potentially take down your application and of course the transitions because it's
querying live and to add indexes to the database and yeah I don't think you I think we still
have some problem with the transitions heat maps and session recordings I would say it
works very well very well sometimes but sometimes it's you could spam the logs or we have one
of our clients is using a network monitoring service that will traffic that it will detect
as spam or denial of service attacks or whatever so this is something we didn't foresee and
when one of our clients activated heat maps and session recordings so that was interesting
so a quick recap because I think my time is running out here yeah so we use Docker Tomo
has a Docker template if you go into the official Matomo github webpage you can search for their
and we have we're of course hosting our own Docker template but I would say that's a good
start if you want to run Matomo in a Docker setup in a cluster environment and yeah Kubernetes
I've talked about a lot any questions feel free later let's see I have 10 minutes left
yeah drone to automate stuff when we push our code into github or git lab or git lab
is actually running their own CI service but drone is something you can integrate with
your github repos and then clear to check for vulnerabilities in your in your images
in your Docker images github git lab I mentioned there's probably something I have forgotten
I think you get the big picture and it was an interesting journey I would say and I will
leave room for questions and I will see if I can open up the chat here
okay there's um hey Jorge I've shared some of the questions here in the chat okay yeah
from Valentin in our chat thanks for contributing to open source with this repo you're welcome
question have you ever used Matomo fake visitor plugin in order to have enough data within
your Matomo data in order to make some crash tests do you make some crash tests with empty
Matomo database the idea would be to educate ourselves about system administration yes
I have used the fake visitor plugin and yes I wouldn't say that it's the best option to
test a big data set because it takes a very long time to get enough of fake visitors so
some of the penetration tests or the load done we have actually taken a big dump of
of course with from a production because we want to have as like production as possible
but I would say there's still we haven't figured out the perfect way to do this thing and if
I could give any advice yeah there's there's a application I can't remember the name right
now it's used a lot to load test the varnish for example I can't if you ping me I can't
you in LinkedIn or Twitter I will share my links later okay question from Roberto with
million of page views how big is your database have you ever met issues regarding the size
of UDB and the archive process so I would say no it's I would say around it's steady
around 800 gigabytes one terabyte I would say it goes up and down when we purchase some
data sometimes after archivings are done some some of our clients have different requirements
for example that they want they want to do some querying to the database one year after
of course that database will grow very big but the class only store for 180 days so we
can start to delete all logs after 180 days and that's it's more that's better for the
application in whole I would say and you can also integrate Matomo to a data lake a hadouk
hadouk cluster or Kafka or something if you want to be here so superset it's something
we have been looking into if you want to do more pivoting of the datasets and asking big
queries to the database so yeah and the archiving process yeah we have had a lot of issues I
think we have if you want to follow our issues we have had through the years you can go into
the Matomo issue queue and you can search for our core archive we have had but I think
we have reached a level of acceptance now and one of the challenges I think Tomas is
going to talk more about and it's about educating your analysts how to build segments or what
else forms you have goals and all those different plugins or applications that needs some kind
of archiving because if you do a too big query on a big dataset with a old type of monolithic
database system or what is it called a tabular database like MySQL or MariaDB you will eventually
hit some problems bottlenecks with you can always optimize the configuration but I think
if you want to do big queries on a database you will need to integrate with some other
system like superset that I just mentioned what else perhaps I missed a number of events
at Skatteverket the figures you showed were page views right yes that is correct I don't
know in from top of my head I don't know the events but since because they aren't using
the tag manager as much as others some of other of our clients that uses a lot of single
page applications we haven't had that many it doesn't differentiate that much of course
there's a there's more events of course I can probably look I can jump to the next question
is MariaDB not supporting Matomo or is it not recommended for large installations on
Matomo yeah so the supporting of MariaDB was it two years ago I would say you can still
install with MariaDB of course for small sites but for large installations if you want to
use some configuration such as there are some MySQL specific configurations that Matomo
is using and I think my time is up there and but of course you can reach out and somehow
I will share my slides if you want to get in touch with me or ask more questions I will
be more than happy to share them with you so thank you for your time thank you for listening
and thank you for the MatomoCamp team awesome