Hello everyone. Thank you for joining another session of MatomoCamp. In this one we have
Niklas who will tell us more about dashboards in Matomo. Niklas is a web analyst with a
background in digital marketing and communication. He has worked with Matomo for years supporting
governmental agencies and businesses in Sweden. Today we'll learn how to get insights and
how to adjust the dashboards in Matomo. Niklas I'm leaving the floor to you.
Thank you. Yes. So hi and welcome to my little talk about how to get a kick-ass dashboard
in Matomo. I think my talk is going to be a little bit more straightforward and hands-on
than other talks for example yesterday. And I'm not going to mention anything about code
or something like that. So you don't need to know anything about that to master how
to get a kick-ass dashboard in Matomo. You just need to master how to drag and drop basically
inside Matomo. Yes and yeah the chat is lagging so I think I'm going to answer questions at
the end of my talk. I think that's going to be the best way forward. So this is basically
what I'm going to talk about. Firstly just going to talk a little bit about what the
dashboard in Matomo is and why you should use it. And the main part of the talk is about
how to set up dashboards within Matomo. So I'm going to demo Matomo and I'm going to
go through how the dashboard works, the default dashboard like the first dashboard you see
when you log in to Matomo. And then I'm going to try to set up two dashboards for different
needs. One for basically for goals and conversions and one for how you can get a dashboard for
your or how to see how your campaigns perform. That's basically it I think. Just a short
notice about who I am. Niklas Tarnsett is my name as Silva mentioned. And I'm right
now a web analyst at the Swedish digital agency Whitespace. I think I have worked with Matomo
since 2016 and I have been a product owner for Matomo for the largest organization public
sector in Sweden. And yeah I have a background in digital advertising and marketing. And
I like to try to focus on what kind of actionable insights you can get with the right data so
you don't drown in all the data that is available for you. Yeah that's pretty much who I am.
So just to talk a little bit about what the dashboard in Matomo is. You can say that it's
like your home page in Matomo. It's the first thing you see when you log into Matomo. And
as I mentioned briefly before there is a default dashboard in Matomo that InnoCraft has set
up for you. That one you can change and adjust according to your different needs and so forth.
And I think it's around a hundred different widgets or reports you can choose between
when you set up or adjust a dashboard in Matomo. So the sky's the limit you can say. So the
thing to focus on is which widgets or reports you want to show in a dashboard. And you can
actually create I don't know I don't think it's a limit to how many you can create. Maybe
someone can correct me if I'm wrong there but basically you can create many different
dashboards for different needs and you can for example let your internal stakeholders
get one kind of report or dashboard so they can see maybe the overall performance of your
website and maybe your market department need one other kind of dashboard that is more detailed
about maybe goals and conversions for different campaigns or how your site perform regarding
SEO or something like that. So I think it's quite a neat tool to use and in my experience
I think it's not used so much that it should be I think. And the last point here is you
can get quite useful data so you can maybe get some more actionable insights regarding
how your website perform and maybe what you need to adjust or take action on regarding
maybe conversions or how your SEO performance is. So I think it's quite a nice thing to
use and definitely something you should look into if you don't have like work with the
different dashboards and adjust them to your different needs. That's it about the dashboard
in Matomo but the talk is not over yet. I'm gonna demo the dashboard and yeah this is
basically what I'm gonna demo I think. So shortly about how the dashboard works in Matomo
and the default dashboard that you get. And then these two examples how you can adjust
your dashboard for goals and conversions and one for how you can track the campaign performance
if you're running a lot of campaigns in other channels like social media or newsletter and
so forth. So I'm gonna jump over to Matomo I think. Let's see here. So I choose the right
window. Yes. So this is the dashboard in Matomo. I hope you can see my screen now. And yeah
this is the default dashboard when you log in to Matomo for the first time or if you
do it regularly and you haven't adjusted the dashboard or chosen which widgets you want
to see. And I should say this is the dashboard if you're a super user. So I have like some
kind of gamification attempt here from InnoCraft to like set up the Matomo. But yes this is
the default dashboard and you can actually remove a widget or report how you want to
like if I don't want to have the real time widget. And it's the same principle for every
widget that I can remove like this. So it's quite neat and quite adjustable how you can
change the visual representation of data in the dashboard. So maybe I don't want this
welcome message even it's a nice message to get. Yeah so it's quite long here. And here
is all the options you have for the dashboard. And as you can see it's a lot of options for
different things. So I'm going to show you how you can maybe create a better dashboard
for your needs. So maybe if I just remove all of these widgets. And basically these
widgets as they are called are reports that you can find in the left menu here. It's basically
the same reports but you can visualize them in the dashboard instead of clicking through
the left menu here. So I had a lot of widgets here. So now it's empty. And maybe you want
to have some kind of data about how your site is performing. So this KPI metric widget is
quite a good widget to use for different needs. And for this I want to show how you can use
it to see how much traffic you get to your site and from which sources. So you hover
over here to this little symbol and then you get a lot of options here. The default is
visits and as I said I want to show you traffic sources. So now we have four search engines
and to get another one you need to do this again. And go down and then I want to have
four visitors from social networks as well. And maybe four visitors from direct traffic
or direct entry. And here you can see like a spark line and how many visitors from direct
entry compared to the previous period. And now I have 3rd of November. Maybe I should
choose like one month instead, like October. Yes, now it looks better. Yes, so it's quite
quick to get like an overall view of how your site performs regarding, oh, sorry, regarding
your site. So I can get like, this is from, there, this is from websites and then maybe
this is from campaigns as well. Let's see here. There we have it, visitors from campaigns.
So, and now the dashboard is in three columns. I usually prefer to work with two columns.
So then you can scroll down here and change dashboard layout to, yes, you can see here
you can have just one, two or two, but the first column is wider than the other one.
So yeah, I prefer to work with two so the dashboard don't get cluttered with too much
data. Yes, so this is I think much better than the default dashboard that we saw earlier.
One more thing or two more things maybe for just this default dashboard. I really like
this one, insights and movers and shakers. You can say it's some kind of overall association
how or the biggest changes in October compared to September then, because I've chosen that
time period. We can see what kind of page titles or page URLs have had the biggest increase
or yeah, in this example, it's just increased, but it's also, sometimes it's maybe a big
decrease in traffic to some website, web page on your website. And then you get like, yeah,
the percentage here, but in red, if it's decreased then. So it gets like, yeah, from Facebook
it increased a lot. And I think it's because our client here had some kind of campaign
in social media about this one. This is in Swedish. It's about more collection, waste
collection in the municipality Höganästan. So then they can see that the campaign attracted
a lot of traffic from Facebook. And then we can also have, if they're using smartphone
or desktop or tablet or so. And then that one I want to have here on the right. And
then you can hover scroll. Now you can move your mouse down here and maybe change to pie
chart. So this is the device type. Oh, there I go. And then the screen resolution, maybe
it's a good thing to also have. And that one I also want to have as a pie chart. Then you
can see, yeah, the smartphone is like, yeah, around 65% for October month. And here we
can see which ones are the most common screen resolutions. And that's a quite, yeah, it's
not like so much insights you can get from that, but it's a nice thing to know, like
a hygiene factor for your website that the website performs as you want it to perform
in these screen resolutions and that it performs well on smartphone then. So like this page
should be very good in the mobile, especially as it was quite a big increase from last month.
And this is one way to adjust your dashboard so it gets, I think, more easier to interpret
and easier to digest the data and maybe get more relevant data. And the next thing, if
you want to have this as your default dashboard, you can actually go down here and pick this
one, set as default widget selection. And you can click yes there. And I forgot to mention
the dashboard is connected to the user, like the user account. So this is for me then when
I log into Matomo. But if you want your colleagues to have the same dashboard, you can actually
copy it, copy the dashboard to user and then select which user should have the dashboard.
But it's quite important to know that if you change your dashboard, you need to do a new
copy of the dashboard to your colleagues. Yeah, this is one way to adjust the default
dashboard. So I'm going to create a new one, create a new dashboard. And it goes, oh, goes
and conversions. And then you can choose if the dashboard should populate with a default
dashboard or just an empty dashboard. And I choose empty so I don't need to remove all
of the widgets. And then I click add a widget. And for this size, I'm going to again use
this KPI metric widget. I'm going to create a lot of KPI widget here. So yeah, this is
a start. And then I also want to change the layout, change dashboard layout. Something
like this. And now I want to visualize how my goals are performing on the website. So
for this is this is for our client NSR. So I want to have one that shows all the conversions
on the website. And then maybe one with conversion rate. See if I can find that one there. Conversion
rate. So this is kind of like the overall performance regarding all the conversions
on the website. And now I want to have for each of the goals. So I scroll down here.
This is one goal. The goal is in Swedish, but it says login to my pages. And I want
the same but for conversion rate as well. There you have that. And the next goal. Yeah,
now I need to create a new one. Yes. So now you have just a dashboard for how your goals
are performing or in this example how our client's goals are performing. This is the
overall for all conversions. And it has increased. But as you can see the conversion rate is
down but not as much. That can maybe one explanation is like the traffic to the site increased
a lot but maybe not the rate of how many converted on the website. And this is for login to my
pages and the conversion rate and here the conversions and the conversion rate for the
next goal. So I think it's a nice feature to use the dashboard to adjust it and show
it for your colleagues. Like this one I should think the market department is quite interested
in. So you can use it to yeah you can do like this as well and then use this link to send
it to your colleagues. Yes. And the last one I want to show is a dashboard for campaign
performers. So I'm going to create a new dashboard. Sample of campaign performance. I'm going
to choose to leave it empty. Then I'm going to add a widget. And again I'm going to use
KPI metric and some other widgets as well. But we start with KPI metric. And yes I forgot
this one I want to have just as one column. I think you're going to understand why shortly.
So we're going to create more KPI widgets here. Something like this. And I want to have
this one visitors from campaigns. And I also want to have the percentage from campaigns.
Presenter visitors from campaigns. And I also want to have data for SEO traffic. Because
campaigns often affect your SEO or traffic that comes from search engines. Because it's
not always the user clicks on the link on like social media directly. Maybe they Google
it later or something like that. So then I want to have visitors from search engines.
And also direct traffic. Like all other traffic that Motomo can't identify basically. And
I want to have let's see here. Yes this one under acquisition campaigns and then campaign
names. And I want to have that one in the bottom of the dashboard like this as well.
And I think a couple of releases of Motomo or some releases lately released the ability
to show the spare table with goals metrics. So I think I'm going to do that. So yeah this
is in October so they had just two campaigns. And if you regard conversions for goals that
I had set up it wasn't so successful. But I actually don't know what the campaigns were
about but here you can get a glimpse of how the campaigns perform regarding your goals
that you have set up in Motomo. And you also get how the traffic to the website from the
campaigns for October. And also how the traffic from search engines and direct entry was for
October month. And this one is quite easy to grasp I think. And again it's something
maybe the market department is interested in to look at how their campaigns have performed
for a given period and see if it gave theirs the effect that they wanted or if it was just
basically a waste of time. So now I've just chosen like campaign names but you can also
see if you want if you see how it performed based on which source the traffic came from
like if it was Facebook or a newsletter or something like that. And then you can also
add let's see here acquisition and campaigns. And then you can take campaign source medium.
And you can yeah I'll put it here. Yeah it was a newsletter they sent out. But here again
you can change to goals metrics. Yes and here you have the campaign names. So yeah for this
example it's maybe not so relevant but if you communicate in different channels I think
it's quite neat to have one widget for your source medium as well to see if it was Facebook
or Instagram or a newsletter as in this example that performed best. Not performed best like
in visits but in conversions if that was your intent with the campaign. Yes I think it was
all that I had to show I think. Let me see here. Yeah I'll leave it there. So I don't
know if someone. Yeah I got a question here from Marcus. Is there any frequently asked
question from users transitioning from Google Analytics? Yeah well one question is how they
can get like the easy dashboard or visualization of data in Google Analytics. How they can
have the same in Matomo. And my answer is this is the closest you can get to like Google
Analytics have some similar solution. Like when you see the numbers you see the sparkline
and you see the comparison from the previous period. That's one question they have. One
common one that I don't have any good solution on is like secondary dimension. Or you can
if it's possible to use that in Matomo. And I don't think it's possible without some customized
code if I'm correctly. Maybe someone else have a better answer that. Yeah and got another
question from Diana. Is it possible to embed the dashboard in an external website? Yes
that's possible. You can use. Yes the short answer is yes. You can do that. I think I
think like adjusted dashboard in Matomo is very good for people that have not have not
the analyst skills that most of you have. Like you don't need to have an external tool
to get like some kind of improvement of the visualization in Matomo. But this is for like
the basic the basic things I think. Yeah I don't I can't I can't see any more questions
in the chat room. But if you have any questions regarding this you can always email me if
you want to. I'll write my email in the chat here. Yeah I think I'm going to say goodbye
and thank you for your time. Bye.