the hello and welcome everybody who you
might to today have heard already a
lot about matomo from different angles from
different use cases from beginner friendly content
to acquire a topic for thoughtful
focusing quite on experts and i guess
a lot of questions about the topic
of matomo the beginning from the usability
to technical questions a lot of questions
might have revised so that's why today
we have her q and a session
or you can ask her these questions
you have about matomo to the
sir speakers we have here today so
the way this works is quite similar
to the talks to have already had
pier today they can see obviously the
live streamer if you're watching and we
have a chat room for this way
you can ask her any question you
have about matomo and there i will
then forward this question
to one of the five speakers we
have here in the room so to
give you a bit of time to
collect her questions and post them in
the chat room i can start by
quickly introducing a our speakers here so
let's start with an all canal is
a metamora analytics or
expert since two thousand and seven and
is mostly focusing on training and doing
consulting for all types of companies institutions
always around about matomo analytics fifth and
corning our second expert here is a
also an expert mostly on her focusing
on digital analytics and co
conversion rate optimization he has a lot
of experience with moto moiety will be
able to answer your analytics related questions
then behalf thomas to nature his seo
and web analytics expert from their border
between austria and germany and here you
might know him from the chairman mccomb
explanation
videos hit us off from the to
also extension motto more hell povich might
yeah some of you will be using
and he will be able to answer
your question about how to use moto
more and how to solve issues using
to use interface then we also have
here as are far far off speakers
stefanki
when he is part of the mathematics
since two thousand and ten and he
is working full time on there mclemore
caught development in the last years so
he is part of their core development
team and to expert for all the
code related christians in matomo and besides
this is also maintaining them automaton
installation and device to attacked at a
separate project will share a converts user
agent into the nicer device information reports
we can see in their matomo and
lastly we also have feared the boy
ticker his part of the matomo complete
immunity from the very beginning in two
thousand and eight
and since then his supporting com panies
with all operations along the tomo and
he can answer all kinds of technical
questions around matomo
and
yep the bitterness i hope everyone can
see the screen and let's just wait
to have a few minutes for questions
maybe in the same meantime while people
are typing questions mere sum of years
some one of you if any one
of you have answered
quick introduction or talk about some topic
or they can talk about it now
or maybe
a question to all how do you
learn something about matomo or what is
your entry point or what was your
entry point
or were there too you can ask
questions and beyond this matomo camp
heavy born maybe as first of all
and maybe not everyone knows that there
is a forum aboard and they can
ask questions where you can ask questions
in your mother tongue like germany and
there is syrup at a good support
in there
there and the other one is and
the the motto more support your cut
if you take the matomo cloud version
and maybe the other ones have also
some tips how to get more knowledge
about matomo
and a good point a bitter forgot
to introduce myself of course i am
lucas winkler and most of here of
course ma will know me from the
matomo for whom i spent more a
lot of my time answering people's question
on the matomo form but also maintaining
some other documentation and to
answering to get up issues and this
is also kind of the answer to
your question is sir if you have
any question about matomo if it's a
general question something doesn't work on your
your set up something like this the
best way probably the matomo for him
that a lot of people already have
asked that question
stand and it's a great way to
slowly get to the bottom of the
issue if you know that the finger
asking you to definitively a pack i
do have heard definitive steps how to
produce them you can skip the fallen
and go straight to get up and
a critic or her issue require air
back request
a back issue and there are that
way it ideally describing a lot of
details so people can reproduce it and
this way if people can see it
it's a quickly organized under it's easier
to fix them
okay bye visit this introduction to have
been a lot of questions and i'll
start very fonda question from peter jones
and his asks there we can add
to use us in the matomo into
for a face or if wonder if
it will be possible to use groups
in the future this will be useful
there are hundreds of thousands of users
though
does anyone have to say something about
this maybe sir stephen i personally don't
know about this feature about this suggests
i don't i'm not even sure if
someone hassle even suggested it until now
but indeed the to my instances where
if a large amount of users and
some kind of grouping might be useful
especially to give fair access rights to
his site too many people at once
and there had been a couple of
requests m four and m more extends
and permission management and matomo am and
yeah some of them were i guess
asking for groups but there currently aren't
any plans
yep then again as a workaround until
ten or all of their use a
management feature say can be air also
accessed via the api i saw if
the issue is just having to manually
add to the hundreds of users to
add to the sites then of course
you can easily automate this with her
a script and the programming language of
your choice and to add to the
useless there
so
i hope this roughly answers the question
as a bit of their delay so
i will go on and if you
have any follow up to this or
simply ask again
so valentine asks which a killer feature
from google analytics do you think should
be included in matomo
secondary dimensions
and that there is sad that the
customer report is a very great plugin
for the moto macleod or you can
pay for the on-premise version but i
approve
maybe i missed something like secondary dimension
in time to to filter in time
not to make the customer report and
then maybe the the data takes a
little bit longer to process so i
wish
she i think i editor of a
feature request to to the second dimension
feature but on the technical side it's
a very huge feature and it's a
very i think it's very complicated to
integrate into matomo
i sing the data visualization parties as
well are missing somehow a highly asked
to buy into google and eight excusable
as google does to you or your
lover a conference tomorrow doubt of humbert
is that isn't that how to use
a mi
database with a matt white experts it's
still something which is kind of tacky
so you cannot put it within the
end of her marketers so a sink
of walking mohan the integration of meta
will wither the self pity that the
visualization system ought to have it's corner
more of a success that
that this realization system is of paramount
importance for her though metamora
one the feed feature that could be
included that valentin suggested that i and
now that i'll read it also find
a good idea is simply a life
view that shows the number of hits
in the last five minutes to get
the really close sir the hallmark
like i said seeing the website right
now a few which incidentally the now
that i am looking at the reports
for the matomo camp might also be
something interesting to see
in addition to i agree with thomas
as well definitely secondary dimensions then also
the decent way to to import and
adds additional data into the toolbar to
combine it with the dataset that you
already have in thing that would make
sense as well
okay i see an interesting not a
question from peter tones hey they have
an altar pv can stems for the
client to migrated to matomo by what
are your experiences of migrating period data
into my tomo may be something for
a pizza or stephen
and while i can take on this
one and it is it is possible
it depends on how much data do
you have in that instance so also
with low amounts of data and also
with high amounts of data it's definitely
possible but in case it can with
a higher
amount of data takes some time because
a lot of skin changes for the
my sql database are necessary and also
things can break because the version jump
from two or three to four is
is a major one and saw a
lot of things in the in the
database scheme
has have been optimized and have been
changed also so you should definitely make
sure to have a real good backup
before you start doing the that migration
and then think also about some some
outage of your matomo instance while you're
updating
at least with a with a bigger
amount of data you have in your
instance and a workaround could be for
example like you could just leave the
tracker running or writing into a locked
file and then after your migration is
complete you can import this lock file
with the replay law
the functionality of the locking porter so
you don't lose too much data
so the the replay logging are probably
the best solution for importing nearly this
data that would have come into the
instance while you had this outage but
all in all
you have to make sure that you
have a few hours of outage and
hematoma instance so your users have to
know and the stakeholders have to know
but all in all i also updated
i think twenty to thirty big instances
to matomo from pv or from the
early versions
and everything went perfectly well
one for a minor thing i also
want to add is something a lot
of fear even if it's a small
instant something a lot of people are
fighting there for if they have a
really alter period version is that this
really alter version of course also vans
with a really old version of e
h b and there might not even
be a
version of psp that is really old
people russia is compatible with and then
he was for tomoe vashon is compatible
with so that if it's a really
old version it might be useful to
appear few intermediate champs of a few
intermediate versions of matomo and maybe if
their compatibility requirements also required also
intermediate versions of dhb to make sure
the migration van face as smooth as
possible a lot of people might not
know it but on belts automotive on
the download page you can download air
to throw the motto every single matomo
version i figured has been released since
two thousand and eight
it's this way you can easily update
to another old version before you to
the next champ
so
another question form to let it sir
is there a possibility to to aggregate
that data directly in matomo saw the
number of users grouped by a certain
customer variable for instance she says i'm
mostly using the a p i and
then aggregate that data with python pandas
personally i can't see much helpful things
about it don't really have from much
experience with an use case where you
would have to aggregate data of costs
that way you are doing it for
your think they apply and then they're
doing any data processing afterwards of course
we're off
always works but might not be the
most idea one probably juliet will be
good to elaborate a bit on that
what you're trying to achieve because in
the custom dimension reports you have everything
grouped by the custom dimension in a
in in the sense of that every
key
custom dimension has it's own round trip
report if you're trying to group all
other reports in the dashboard for example
of for those accustomed dimensions combinations or
a single accustomed dimension this is probably
not possible in the in the dashboard
at least so going with an external
solution like
like a python pandas or a tableau
powerbi i meter base or something like
that would be the way to go
at least for the moment
i have been a quick note to
peter's previous explanation for every plane the
luxor a parrot chris is a been
a foreigner twice to go this way
and escape attempt the downtime of the
upgrade by afterwards replaying the saga looks
at
each tomato masala one of course has
to pay attention that all requests sent
to matomo i get requests not post
requests as advice of course the data
won't be written into every plots in
the server logs
and the mikael has another question about
databases speed and he says that the
database faith is a big issue and
is it possible or has someone tried
to use solar or any other database
for quicker queries
maybe that i can say something about
it
and as far as i know there
aren't any plans to support of our
databases because at some
yeah it's it's heart m to start
the boarding other databases when you have
a software that should be available for
your every user on a hosted system
and and my sql is simply the
mostly supported database
indeed the main issue i think is
if he wanted to add support for
another database and it doesn't matter if
it's for something a podcast is krell
or something completely different it would always
mean that you'd have to revise a
huge portion of matomo
and in this case it might even
be quicker to simply export the data
for matomo and if you're already rewriting
it from scratch or to the queries
in this database directly
and of course the other thing is
if it would be a writer a
huge portion of matomo to support other
databases data may be more specialized for
analytics data is that either both vashon
said that would differ quite a lot
huge lever to need to be maintained
in the future
aa which is really hard to do
or to myra credit come with only
my credit compatible version would have to
be dropped but this would mean that
nearly everyone who can at the moment
simply installing about amanda sava using my
squirrel yet to be able to something
like this are able to have major
issues continuing to use moto
when does the future so because of
all of this i think it won't
change in the near future yeah i've
had my tumor will be my credit
and maria depay only
an interesting question by pizza makers is
are there any ideas about integrating a
half that i have that side carbon
calculator which myth says how much impact
your website has on the planet it
could be a unique selling point for
potential new users
if no one else has something to
say about this i think this is
one of the use cases servitors would
be a really nice matomo plugin because
it's something only a few people would
be interested in but it would be
a nice feature for them and it's
something you can
quite easily to put a round of
matomo without having to modify something or
of the qr code so this would
be a nice a simple plugin and
if someone gets around to over the
air programming it it will be really
nice if they could publish it on
the marketplace i think
in the meantime maybe a question about
her translation how does the translation process
back in matomo hire if a hooker
if i there either if haematoma isn't
completely translated in a language i speak
or if i notice a typo or
sentence that doesn't really make sense in
the matomo how can i fix this
how can i report this maybe stefan
has something to say about this
mv recently and switched our translation platform
to contribute to and all our translations
are currently hosted on replicate it's another
open source software to maintain translations and
yeah everyone can em suggest
or change the translations there to any
language m and from there m the
translations are automatically pushed to our github
repository am and will later be included
in any new release of matomo or
any of our plugins
okay then
a bit more analytic surpise question from
a reverse is sir
they're currently using matomo more in order
to safer page that they interpreted what
they like to but we like to
be able to categorize the pages based
on his department and the data for
this is already in the page and
could you please let us know how
to proceed
this one is is basically what you
can do is if the information is
already there you should be able to
store those kind of input within custom
dimensions and then basically also be able
to two seconds on this later on
as well in the tumor would recommend
to start
measuring it together with with the default
page view tracking and also adds to
some certain custom dimension tracking with with
the given values that you have for
the given departments and store in the
air and then you are able to
filter it segment is or create custom
reports with it as you wish
yeah it should be easy be easily
doable with the the technology typically you
can just sell silkair there's the sir
element on the page which isn't the
future under fatah was just given html
attribute so they can gallop this given
attribute that they
insult within the custom dimensions fitted in
the matter more custom valuable configuration valuable
within the tech manager and every tended
to pages going to be loaded as
this given element is on the page
is going to grab it and put
it as a custom they mention and
then it will slice your cat
finger is a cutting
perhaps also as an important comment on
exactly this problem is from the performance
view of things and you should always
tried to put as much business complexity
in in the trekking runtime so try
to put as much complexity as
possible from your data reporting and dashboard
reporting and to segment definitions etc tried
to put it into the tech manager
because
if you have to filter for accustomed
dimension it is very quick it is
very performance very effective and also the
the underlying my sql queries and if
you for example have your segment definition
and grouping one hundred a page your
else
to to try to to define your
your branch or something else some page
grouping of your segment it will be
very ineffective and slow so try always
to to do as much as possible
in the tech manager with custom dimensions
and track some events with extra data
and so your performance days are
says good
yeah just noticed that i missed the
question a bit above from melody that
they have for problems aggregating certain reports
for month liver parts of your data
then to a daily reports in the
intent of such report and to which
a
actions could we take to analyze the
problem so i figure this is something
that's hard to do to a genuine
guy spot were how can one approach
such an issue or how what is
the easy way to get in the
direction of the issue how to start
troubleshooting
so perhaps i was just start on
on trying to answer that do well
the troubleshooting probably starts
with
yup and making clear which part of
the system makes this error so probably
one thing to to keep in mind
is that the archiving could be could
fail on the month's monthly archives mostly
mostly this is the case when the
memory limit is reached so you will
have to search in the server log
files for errors in the archiving process
when you have a look so if
you are using the cron job and
so you should make sure that you
disable the browser archiving and i think
we can attach some some links to
to that page later on in the
chat also to that you can make
sure that you enabled the cronjob for
the as in cronus or cutting of
data and then you can also read
on that page how to how to
lock the things that disgruntled writes to
the console how to
plug it into the into a file
and then analyze the that file for
errors in the monthly archive generation and
yeah that's that's probably in ninety percent
of the cases the problem that the
archiving shop is failing for some reason
that's one general i think it could
at www
vice if the rear to issues with
the reports maybe check the output of
the archiving process if you are using
a cone shop talk regularly call it
or because then it can be quite
verbose and the awesome time it that
your venture can add to make it
even more verbose and sometime
you can find something beard or some
violence into which sir i could hint
to in which direction to look
bearish a shot question from nicholas who
has problems with the heatmaps and before
i quickly recommend you to send a
quick email about it to the premium
plugin support team they can help you
with this probably quite easily
then another question from caesar because we
talked about get and post requests previously
if there is a way to switch
all requests to get
i can say something on that and
it em by default and the matomo
tracking users and send beacon from the
browser which uses a post request you
can either disable this was the method
disable always use speaking or something like
that or you can force them the
request
the method with set request method bosom
should be javascript tracking options you can
send you the tracking code
the only thing to keep in mind
there is of course a data limit
of how much data can be sent
in the get request a matomo all
of all of the old versions automatically
switch to a post request if the
older data that would be simply be
too large i mean i think
it's a quite a lot of data
that would need to be sent for
to be the to launch it if
i get but if their website you're
tracking has enormously long you are also
something like this this is something to
maybe keep in mind just to mention
it this will always be the case
and if you are trekking m heatmaps
am and
stuff like that because it em tries
to send all the hatem m html
body and with a tracking request and
that is required to send put to
bed with post as get won't work
and another question by valentine or average
or was a better answer than a
title by the i just want to
mention it here and stream for the
recording or if it is possible to
set the custom time for a scheduled
task for example to to stay at
the scheduled tasks should always wanted the
night went off yamato
number of website visitors at the server
has less load or something like this
and as far as i know there
isn't yet a feature like this it
might be something that could be added
and that a lot of people might
be interested in a back around to
have somebody to suggest that it's of
course you can run them at almost
casual task individually so if this is
something you cap out you could
if i set up a thing separate
corn chops for older scheduled task and
matomo
i have been questioned by a team
kata it said there are plans to
introduce filtering much like what exists in
google analytics because segments stone to cover
always sets a which doesn't suit that
purpose
the thighs i know there is actually
an issue on get up but em
i don't know the current state of
it but i guess it isn't bland
currently
yeah and i'm sharing the same and
so i don't have the answer here
so for the guys who are not
familiar with google analytics typically no matter
more you get to a different way
of walking so zef laker within the
global set settings you can exclude by
a p address and
by adding for example the spam tracking
prevention you can exclude bay countries
but you don't have as much flexibility
as the google analytics filter which i
including those two dimensions that they just
to mention including as well user agent
i forgot in google antics you of
all your zoho dimensions possibility to use
us filter to come in
to filter out are included within a
within a within google analytics and he
stood at sir currently met and does
not offer them orlin and i don't
know zeph plan of doing it yeah
i posted a link to the get
up is sure stefan refer to if
you're interested entitled this topic i too
i command you to
a look at upper there
in the meantime while i am looking
for the chapter i am for question
questioner i think to her always been
twisting a tour or interesting or to
hear is how can one contribute to
matomo either a how can i report
a notice of back in matomo how
can reported on
or if i know how to program
how can i even fix it myself
okay so hey a fellow sufferer i
think the better the thing i mentioned
in the beginning so if you're just
have a vague issue and are not
sure of what is exactly going wrong
the easiest thing is to ask on
the forearm and to that way find
out a better low savage
exactly the issue what is going wrong
if you know it or if that
sir and if you know exactly what
is going wrong and over how someone
can reproduce it then a new criminal
code then you can echo directly to
get up and create to get up
his shepherd of crosser
the things that sets how to reproduce
it makes it a lot easier to
understand the issue makes it a lot
easier to fix it because er oftentimes
sir it's obvious for the person writing
a github issue to know there it's
obvious for them votre they are talking
about but if you're not
they're up to date on what they
are doing it's quite hard to understand
it and is adding steps to exactly
reproduce the issue makes it a lot
easier to understand the issue and in
that way also a lot easier to
fire developer to the packet and then
fix it
and of course if you're you're a
developer yourself and know how to fix
it then at the easiest figures of
crawford to change the code created importantly
cost if the change and to contribute
a tumor tumors yourself
the pune if you're a developer but
don't know it they're not that familiar
with moto more than you can also
go to their matomo developer page which
has a
great pager about how to get started
with the code base of matomo and
how to set up a local motto
more into the development instance which makes
it a lot easier to contribute code
changes
can a ma analytics or a related
question about funnels me before stefan arkansas
am
at least see the question itself lie
repeated for people who are watching the
recording or talking about funded refers how
does it for homeless at whacking if
you have a family like this where
the separate first step is entered them
going to a conversion directly does it
get to be fearless in the steps
afterwards as before
article conversion
maybe on all of the fun have
something to say about it i'm not
that familiar referred i can't really help
here advice the question would again be
to ask the support team
will you you can of course set
your goal in there and the conversion
will be set in the second step
when when it's needs directly being a
chiefs
and it depends whether the fifth is
also being set as a conversion in
your goal configuration you can set it
to allow to cool
to make a conversion multiple times were
to do it only once within the
given this is the kind of things
matter of figuration was
as soon as someone
moves across additional steps it depends on
whether certain steps are required or not
to check whether this instance has been
achieved and it really depends on your
goal configuration settings
a question by a mass alert i
think a lot of people are asking
is they have a website and they
want to collect a reader for your
feedback so feedback by the people visiting
the website something like how does the
story make you feel and
it makes sense to collect the state
and moto moto moto connected to the
outer data and can't could this be
realistically be implemented on top of moto
more of a moto my state store
and of course he could to a
program something i kiss rather easily yourself
if you're to the user interface pot
yourself and then sent that data for
example a ser or custom event or
something like this but by chen sir
we have a talk tomorrow by thomas
a person is talking about a plugin
they developed which dusk right exactly this
so richer it's a feedback or feature
to her
website you're using matomo so you might
want to listen to this talk tomorrow
yeah i added the link within the
the chat and i think doomed focus
yourself on the the fallen which is
under the patronage that i that they
show you because a sink that's in
the link that that you sent your
like eight different buttons a sing that
you can add with this plugin
custom layout in order to have more
than a than two buttons and twelve
eight like yours are the best thing
is yes of course westward to thomas
but the walks in sp for me
two years on display again as though
that's going to be a pregnant pitcher
saw that sir mod the path where
your eyes go down let's say that
the it's always
good to to discuss wheeler with him
too scene factor was edited and the
spirit behind and the and i have
the chance to avert to assist to
several conferences at the move that maidens
it's really impressive and great feature
he may be in the meantime with
her mom marketing really or usa related
question that i get a lot of
times is there that now that there
is matomo tech manager what are the
differences between using matomo direct
your love way and the using matomo
tag manager
so i i could say a few
words about that
so basically or generally are both things
are working and will work in the
future so that's the important thing to
know at first but mostly also with
bigger teams working on an matomo also
more than one on
analyst and if you have more than
one requirement collected for tracking capabilities and
everything and the tech manager makes more
sense than the legacy tracking code and
the reason for that is probably if
you want to extend your your trekking
the concept and you want to have
more tracking features collect accustomed dimensions events
and have some behavioral stuff included into
the tracking code for example if it's
just a simple thing like trekking clicks
on on a call to action button
or some kind of other interaction stuff
and you would always have to have
a release cycle and close contact to
the developer of the of the website
to just give him the code and
prepare everything and he has to included
in the website and then you have
to release a new version of the
website to include the new version of
the tracking code
and then in worst case you have
made an arrow anywhere audio you need
more data you have a stakeholder that
called with a with a feature request
in the last second and it didn't
bring it into the current sprint or
something like that and so it's quite
a nightmare to maintain this this kind
of code with a tech miniature code
and it's mostly or most of the
things you can do
the tech miniature configuration in the generic
user interface so this is this is
not a free ticket for everyone to
to do everything with tags and release
new container versions and stuff because you
can break the site with that ah
so there should be a workflow for
that but basically it is
your time to market for the for
the trekking is much better than with
the legacy code and also the maintain
abilities is much better and you can
feed information that you can't collect from
the from the html directly you can
gather of your data layer so that's
the the single point
of a connection between you and the
developer or the cms the data layer
and you have to ask the developer
to pass over information that you can
get from the html and then to
composite over to the tech manager and
process everything with it so it makes
things and life much easier here
that was the truth noticed if you're
really interested in this topic you might
want to leave the session right now
and go to the other lifestream boom
because thomas person is currently talking about
matomo tag men are trying to basics
of it
not in addition you have also everything
in one place and every tracking scripts
you do you know where the tracking
script is implemented and so on and
if you do a relaunch you don't
have to make a list of all
the tracking scr
crypts in page path five hundred and
so on until you you can only
open the technica contain i'd see which
scripts you're using
sometimes it's easier to troubleshoot everything up
with the development or debug view and
you have some templates some you can
fill in so you don't have to
code something if you're not familiar with
coding until you can use
use some templates and to integrate some
external services and yeah and if you
want to rollback you have an version
control and i think it's easier to
roll back tack miniature version then the
release version so i think
in time you can easy rollback of
the russian intact miniature and the like
up to say you have to go
to the developer and say okay can
you reverse please the last version and
so it's it's easier and yeah sometimes
you can
can see you have also documented who
changes what barricade in the development you
have this too but there you have
the use and permission management in one
place and i think sum up this
are all very good feature
us and i think er in mind
i would never integrate tracking scripts without
and container without matomo tech ledger or
something else something or some other tech
managers
hey i think i have answered most
though the questions of course the matomo
camp thousand and now we still have
a rest of the day and then
full day tomorrow and there if you
have any more questions just feel free
to ask them in the chat
yeah
people will still be here people will
still be able to answer and maybe
if you wanted to talk to other
people attend the advertisement in the breaks
or maybe after the last talk today
or you can go to meet that
matomo camped at ark and their dad
talk to other attendees
matomo camp maybe some of us will
be there i'm not sure
well thank you very much for all
the questions that you ask can we
hope that you are her having a
great mentor mckim
thank you very much
they have an assistant in guys
you too
i know right