Exactly, then it starts now. Welcome to the Matomo Compact Workshop.
Maybe for a very short time. What do you expect today? You may have already read it in the description.
So I'll just give you a quick look at the Matomo reports.
Just a brief basic understanding of the individual metrics. What do you find? Where? How can I evaluate what?
We'll take a look at the search log, the behavior reports and the acquisition reports.
Maybe just a quick thing about myself. So I'm Thomas Schernek, I'm a senior SEO and web analyst at an agency in Salzburg and also self-employed.
At the same time, in the Matomo universe, I tried to make a few YouTube videos on the topic of Matomo in German with my head.
And if you have any questions, please feel free to chat in the big blue button.
You can also mute the questions if there is anything or you want to ask something in the current report.
So we can do a quick Q&A session afterwards. Or you can just ask like this.
Or you can just write it later, either in here or just via LinkedIn. That works pretty well too.
Then we'll get started. Exactly. How we're going to do that today is we're going to take a look at the Matomo demo page.
If you go to the demo.matomo.cloud, you can take a look at the Matomo Cloud version.
So take a look at the demo. There are demo data in there from a fictitious site.
Maybe if you now have On-Premise, so you have installed it yourself,
then it will probably only look like this if you have only installed the most common plugins or just that is the basic installation.
We're just going to take a look at the demo page now.
So here are also mostly more plugins installed, which maybe one or the other doesn't have on it.
But that's the version you have when you use, for example, Matomo Cloud.
So we go in and what you see first, so up here is the normal website selection.
So we have different pages that you can select here and depending on that, the complete one changes here.
It's similar, I'll tell you now. Maybe one comes from Google Analytics.
It's similar to the Analytics data views or properties that you can select here.
The second one is the date picker. Now I have selected the current day today.
I can also go here on a weekly basis. You can already notice that complete lines are marked here.
Or let's just take a look at the month of October.
Up here there are the segments. So you can segment in Matomo, just like you have segments in Analytics.
There are already a few pre-made segments. At the very beginning you have the one that everyone uses.
That's just unfiltered. I'll show you the segments themselves very briefly on the other one.
Here you have the option, for example, I have already set up organic search here.
That means the channel type corresponds to, for example, search.
And you can just save and take over that. Click.
The whole thing is so that it takes a while at Matomo Cloud until everything is completely processed,
until it can be displayed.
Here we already have something, for example, that means NZ visitors.
These are visitors from New Zealand. I can now simply select them here, for example.
If I just go up here, then it's completely selected.
You can already see that the visitor card is now changing to New Zealand.
If you have the opportunity to compare all the segments together,
then you don't go directly to the segment title, but go to this comparison symbol here.
And so you have compared all the visitors to the visitors from New Zealand.
Unfortunately, you can't see much here, because the visitors don't make that much of the total visitors.
Of course, you can also customize this dashboard. That means it's not fixed.
I have the option to simply place each widget, these are individual widgets,
here somewhere else, for example here on the right.
And then you can already see what you have on every Blanco dashboard.
You always have such a nice welcome screen where you are greeted.
You can take a look at that. This is always the first thing I close later.
Actually, you don't need it anymore. You can simply click away here,
confirm briefly that you actually want to take it away now, and then that's it.
If you now say, okay, I'm going to have a report here, that's not a problem.
Here, when you click on it, you have the option to add widgets, different widgets.
And the whole thing is just as integrated as exactly the left tree.
So you have this left menu tree here.
Just like here, you also have the different values. Let's take a closer look.
I would now be interested and would like to know, let's take a quick look,
which websites the users come to on my page.
Then I have the option here that I have inserted the widget right away
and you can see here that diveadvisor.com, for example, brings the most visitors.
You can customize everything here.
You also have the option to add this dashboard or several dashboards.
You can simply find that down here, for example, change the dashboard layout
or you can also add a new dashboard.
Unfortunately, I have to go back to the other demo dashboard, because in the demo,
you have to know, you can look at a lot of things.
You actually have view access.
But you can't change a lot, for example, in the demo dashboard.
It's just for looking.
And here, for example, you could also create a new dashboard, just enter the name.
And then you have the option, for example, to add the split layout.
Exactly, add the widgets quickly.
And then you have the option.
Let's add it here for a moment.
Exactly, of course, you also have the option to change the split layout.
So that you say, okay, the layout is too strange for me, three splits.
If I have that once, because I just have very few widgets,
then I can do it very easily here.
That would be it in the area of the dashboards that we have here.
So you can add different dashboards here.
We'll just look at a report.
That would be the visitor tab, which is always very nice with Matomo.
It's probably the case with Google Analytics, that actually the most important metrics,
which we list under the reports, for example the visitors,
i.e. the properties of the visitors, that you just have them together here.
And the most important metrics are simply listed here.
And then you can go deeper into the detail later.
Here we have the graphs of the last visitors on the website itself.
You also have the option to change the metrics in addition to a line chart.
So if you say, okay, I'm not interested in the visitors right now,
I would like to have the pages.
Then I just select them.
Then they will be compared, for example, or I tick off the visitors, for example.
Then you can just see the comparison of all the data you have here.
You can also export all the data.
Here there is another button at the bottom where it says,
okay, I want to export the data to another format.
Here it is always quite good.
So if you make reports or the like,
I usually use TSV, i.e. also in Excel a good format
and I usually get all as a drawing limit.
You can export that.
If you need it theoretically more often, or if you want, for example,
you can import it into a Google Data Studio.
This may also be possible through an API or an interface.
Then you have different other formats, such as JSON,
and you can display an export URL.
That means every time it is called, you can export this report here.
What I need for that is an API token that you can create
so that you can read the data.
Why do I have to do that?
So that not everyone who calls the URL can just read my data at the same time,
but you just need a key for it.
The possibility, if you can do that graphically,
you can do a screenshot on the one hand,
but the possibility of pulling an export image with Matomo
or simply saving with the right mouse button
is also a nice feature you have here.
Maybe some of you have already noticed all these text boxes.
These are all the comments you have here.
So if you go here and say, for example, I have relaunched a website,
then I can just leave a comment.
Then I may just have information and say, okay, what happened there?
Why is there a really big drop in the side views,
almost half down?
Then I can just take a look at it if I want to.
Exactly, there are all the data and here are the most important metrics.
Let's just take a look at them.
What is very cool in Matomo and what you actually pull through Matomo
is this visitor log.
In theory, I can just pull out every user and take a look at it in detail.
I think this visitor log is very, very good
because I have detailed information about the user in here
and I can also see what he is doing exactly.
What he is doing exactly, I'll show you on the other side here in this area.
I now have the option to see on the one hand where the user comes from.
Here the IP address is anonymized depending on what settings you have given here
and I can also see the device, operating system and how he came to my website.
Here you can see the campaign is PPC, Pay Per Click.
How did this happen or how can you do this?
This is actually quite good with Matomo. There is also Google Analytics,
for example the URL image, so that I can simply overwrite various things
such as the source and the medium.
So here, for example, the source Google Ads has simply been overwritten
and the medium is CPC, so Pay Per Click,
and it is simply a Google Ads ad over which the user came here.
For example, here the Avengers Playing Cards is simply the first entry point
and then you can just see quite well.
He just clicked through all the pages,
got stuck with one product and then simply got out again.
There are also, for example, direct access here in this area
or maybe also access to other search engines such as Ecosia
and this feature, I just think it's really very good,
because you can see everything in detail very well.
If you now also click on the visitor profile,
you still have the opportunity to look.
This is not the case when the user, for example,
has come to the page more often.
Let's take a quick look.
Do we have someone here?
Here we don't have any action, unfortunately not.
What we have seen earlier, the user simply gets on the page
and when a page call has taken place,
you can see it, for example, on this folder symbol.
There are also different categories of events
that can simply be carried out,
for example, an internal search.
For example, the user simply entered FINS at the top
or, for example, checkout form.
So if someone has taken part in form view,
then it is simply displayed here.
The whole e-commerce tracking,
so if a warning box that was filled before was simply broken down
and events.
So events are actually almost the same as with Google Analytics.
You can also send additional data to Matomo itself,
which you can then select all of them later.
So.
Then let's just look further.
Well, the real-time report is always very nice.
So you can always see when something comes in at the top.
But this is not so targeted for a detailed analysis.
The visitor card in real time is also a nice feature
where you can just see where all the users come from on my website.
It gets really interesting with the local report.
Here you can see different widgets.
For example, I can now go directly into the United States
and with the mouse over I can then just see
how many visitors really came from the United States.
It then covers itself with this area here on the right.
And now I'll show you something again.
Here you can still see a segmented visitor log
in all the metrics.
This means that this visitor log, as I said earlier,
is pulled through the whole of Matomo.
Now I have simply filtered the visitor log
onto the United States of America
and can evaluate it in detail quite well.
I don't have to segment something in detail beforehand,
but just take the pre-made segments from Matomo,
for example, that it is now filtered onto the land,
take it and can then evaluate it completely.
The tab is also very extensive,
more extensive, I would say, like in analytics.
So we have here next to desktop, tablet and smartphone
we also have different other devices,
for example game consoles,
which for example come to the website.
Here as a reference, for example, from Reddit directly on the website
on a game console.
This is also an interesting feature.
Here you also have more information.
Of course, device models can also be completely evaluated here.
The brands, depending on whether they manage to do it or not,
so if it is unknown, then there is simply no
allocation in Matomo in this area,
which is also quite good for responsive design.
You can also take a look here,
how many users are accessing, with which resolution,
this is actually a very good metric.
Software, which is probably now only there
so that you can just take a look
at what kind of browser support I have to offer as a website operator.
Do I still have to go there and say,
okay, I have the Internet Explorer,
do I still have to offer an older version?
This is a nice feature.
The times, there are always two things.
There is simply the visit to local time,
that is, let's assume my server is now in New York
and I arrive at 8 o'clock Central European Summer Time,
then I would probably be tracked in here.
The server time can be completely different,
for example here.
This is actually very useful when you say,
okay, you have a high server load in several time zones,
maybe then combined.
That means, okay, in the morning I have a lot of traffic
and in the evening I have a lot of traffic for the server
in different time zones, for example,
then built-in traffic to server time.
So that's always the time when the user looks at the page
and that's where the server has the location
and where the call is generated.
If you, for example, are a website operator
and you have an online shop where users can register,
there is the possibility to give the user ID directly.
Whether the DSGVO is technically okay or not,
unfortunately I can't answer that here,
but it is possible that you, for example,
give email addresses or user string here and there.
Then you have the opportunity and can, for example,
look at what a big tank has here for the visitor profile.
For example, he has come up here very often on the website
and what he has looked at at all.
It's actually very good what you just have with you.
If you have the shop, you can give it bundled.
You can also give different other variables.
Let's say you have a blog and you have different authors
and you can also, so you could now,
by adjusting the tracking script format a little bit.
How to do that is usually found here under the help items.
It's always very good if you don't know which one,
what kind of metric that is, what it's about,
you have the opportunity to always show it here either
through the mouse over or to look at the documentation
or an instruction.
So now you have to give my tracking code.
That means if I call a blog post and a certain author
has written it, for example Charles,
then it is simply given next to the URL, the type and so on,
as a user-defined variable.
It's actually a very good thing,
how you could add your data, for example.
Exactly, that would be it for the part,
for the visitor part.
Do you already have any questions in this area?
Otherwise, I'll just keep looking.
Otherwise, always feel free to ask questions.
Otherwise, we'll just keep going and take a look at the other two reports,
namely the behavior.
When it comes to behavior, it's really about the page itself.
Here you simply have the most important metrics,
page views, clear page views,
two metrics, why are they so different?
Well, of course, I can call five times in one session, for example,
one page, then I have a page view of five
and clearly one, because I just called it once in the session.
And all the metrics such as jump rate and how long
do you stay on this page on average?
Here you can simply see that bundled based on the folder structure.
That means, if I just look at it here,
then it's just slash diving, slash and everything that happens behind it.
So it's actually like the report in analytics for content pages.
If you don't like it now, you can go all the way down
and say, okay, I'd like to structure this one
not hierarchically, but I just want to show it flat.
So flat simply means the first level
or every page URL is simply displayed in detail.
And now I just have the individual pages here.
Of course, you can also call me when I go up here
and then I have my page ready.
The entry pages are the landing pages.
Here it's just about how the user gets on the page,
what is the first page when he comes to your page
and exactly those are the pages that are listed under entry pages.
In other words, exit pages,
you can probably already think of them as the pages
where you're done with the whole session and where you just stop.
That means closing the browser is the exit page.
If you say, okay, I don't want to look at the URLs anymore,
I just want to see the title, then you have the title here,
but that's always very important.
I change the title once, then I have, for example, two cards
and the other title would have to be combined again.
That's why the URL is actually very good for evaluating
and very important that you just do it really URL-based.
The internal book, you can also do that by, for example, adjusting it.
On the one hand, there is the tracking script,
on the other hand, I can go into the settings and say,
I want such common parameters.
In WordPress, I think it's S or Q that are attached
and then it's just left behind.
So if you're looking for something in WordPress,
for example, here floats and then press enter,
then it's really in the URL,
that's then S equals floats and that after the is equals
it comes in directly.
These are the search terms and when you search, for example,
then you just look at what happens after that.
That's pretty good, maybe a little SEO tip.
Let's face it, very often something is searched
and you don't have it in the menu,
it might be worthwhile to pick up this site prominently.
You may also come to new keywords,
which you may not have thought of yet,
which you may then be able to integrate in certain subfolders.
What is also a very cool feature,
but you also have to ask the technology
whether this is implemented,
that's just for an additional call.
What happens if the user is looking for something
and there are simply zero results?
If it happens too often,
then just put a new page on it.
That's actually very good in Matoma,
you can also go in and take a look at it completely.
In that area.
If you now go to the settings,
simply put your domain,
then you also have the opportunity to see
where the users go afterwards.
So what is the next click?
There is click tracking on external domains.
Here, for example, there is LiveAboard
and I also have the opportunity
to turn it off if this is based on a domain again.
If, for example,
different URLs of a domain are grouped again.
Of course, I can also display it flat again,
not hierarchically.
And then I also have the opportunity
to look here in detail
where this link was clicked.
This is a link click here.
And at the same time,
it is also set as a goal.
That's also a great thing.
Maybe that's also quite good.
You have certain partners and say,
OK, you can link a banner with us.
Then you actually have a statistic at the same time
how often a banner was clicked
to an external partner, for example,
if you need it.
There is also download tracking on the fly.
That means, it is simply looked at.
Is it PDF, DocX, also JPEGs,
depending on the one.
You can also add more in the tracking codes
and then the downloads are simply tracked.
It is important to know that a download tracking
is not something like this
if I would call this URL directly.
Then it is not tracked.
Why is it not tracked?
Because no JavaScript code can be
executed, for example,
or in a PDF, actually not.
And that's why the call is not tracked,
but actually just the click to the document on the website.
That's actually quite good or important to know
in that area.
At the front you have the events.
That means you have events that you can
additionally send in that area.
Here, for example, click tracking was also
integrated as an event category.
That's back to top.
You can look at this again with the segmented
visitor log.
Where is that about?
For example, on this register page,
there is simply apparently a back to top button
that you can track.
Click tracking can then usually be done
quite well with the Atomo Tag Manager.
When it is integrated, there are already
good templates, how you can do it.
We'll take a closer look at the content.
Then we also have content areas,
which you can add here.
It's also a good feature, but you have to
define it beforehand.
Very well, we'll take a closer look at
engagement.
These are all metrics,
average duration of time,
how many actions were carried out at all,
how often a certain user comes back to the
page, how many pages will be in the
section.
These are all metrics that you can
look at bundled there.
Let's take a look at the visitor flow.
It's also a very good chart.
Here you can just look at it.
If someone goes to the job page,
for example, there are 59% exits.
But where do all the other exits really go?
So where does the user really go later,
on which pages?
It actually visualizes quite well.
This is also a feature, for example.
There is now only either cloud hosted or
is just a premium plugin from Atomo.
That's why I don't want to go that far
because I don't know if any of you have
this feature.
Down here we have our user-defined
variables, as we have already seen before.
This is, for example, the page authors.
They are listed down here.
Acquisition report.
How do the users come to our site?
So here we have again in the overview,
as well as listed everywhere,
the different channel types.
Direct search engines, social networks,
websites and campaigns.
The whole thing is again
opened up to channel type.
For example, search engines.
Then the search terms are possibly
displayed here.
But I wouldn't leave myself 100% on it now.
For example, this is hardly any more.
These are not provided.
Actually, 95% of clicks from search engines
don't include keywords.
So it's not that someone just says,
OK, there are 53,000 visitors
and that's 319 times the search term.
Maybe it's the one that is searched most often.
I just recommend to just look
into the search console.
Search data.
Then we look again at all channels.
Here we have again the different channels
simply opened up.
For example, also the reference search engines
and search terms.
Here it would be all in detail,
what we saw earlier,
opened up.
Also quite good, I think,
this search engine distribution
and at Matomo also a big pro feature
that there are icons everywhere.
You also have the option to export it well
and then show yourself completely
in the diagram.
We go again briefly.
These are the different search terms
for the different search engines.
Yes.
For the websites,
it's about who refers to me
or how many users come from certain websites
to my website,
as well as social media networks.
Which ones are there at all
and how do the different users get there?
For example, Reddit is very much in demand here
and if I have campaigns myself.
With the campaigns it is now like this.
On the one hand, there is this campaign name
theoretically the keyword and so on
and down here there is a campaign URL generator.
If I go on it now,
I can build what is later in the campaigns
myself.
That means I just put my URL in here
and say, okay, take my campaign name,
for example, go here and say,
okay, source medium.
So where does it all come from?
If I say, okay, this is for example
a newsletter, the medium is email,
then I can enter it here and then I have it later
here in my campaign report search terms
and well, there is now unfortunately
no more data in this demo,
but then I would have everything compact here.
That's why my appeal.
There are a lot of channels
where it is called the direct traffic,
direct none may still be known by one or the other
from analytics. This is usually actually this
starting point of the traffic that is not assignable.
So partly these are users who enter something at the top,
partly but also users who click on a link
from the email program. It is always very important
that you, for example, send a signature or newsletter
such a campaign URL is generated.
This is then the URL and behind it are the whole,
for example, what is this really for a source,
what is for a medium and then it comes, for example,
here with somewhere else and not under direct
traffic. This is actually very important, because otherwise
you are a bit thrown away.
There are different scenarios. Here you are also talking about
QR code. If I want to evaluate a QR code,
I also have to create a campaign URL,
because otherwise nothing else remains.
Actually nothing else remains,
because I don't know how the users come to the side
and I can only do that by creating
a campaign URL.
If you have a shop,
you also have the opportunity to track the complete sales
with e-commerce tracking.
Here again the course of the orders
and you can easily see
the conversion rate, which is very important.
And you can also
look at it with the expanded e-commerce tracking.
Where are the warning boxes left at all?
For example, users are added,
but never bought, then everything can be
completely in here. What is very good,
you now have the e-commerce protocol again.
For example, the visitor log
is only filtered to e-commerce activities.
You can also look at it again.
Here you can see all the complete data again.
As I said, e-commerce tracking is another league again.
You have to implement and test it
from the development department.
But it is actually a very good feature
that you have all the most important information here.
What does my shop even bring?
Exactly, you can test it again.
These are the product data,
as well as the turnover. With the turnover,
it is again the case that you go really deeper
in the Atomo and have the opportunity.
You can look at the turnover by channel types.
There I have the opportunity to say,
where do I invest more? Here, for example,
the network has simply made the most traffic
in the CEO, rather the least.
It may be that I, for example,
put a little something in here in social advertising
and there are a lot of things that you can then
evaluate directly here. Even if I have
certain campaigns here, for example,
I probably don't have any campaign names now.
I also have the option,
for example, if I have a company that doesn't tell me any names,
I can maybe think about whether
I might switch it off in that area.
What is a website without goals?
Actually, without goals,
a website should never go online,
because each website follows a goal.
And here you can enter different goals
and also follow them.
For example, I have a website
with a number of conversions
that you have in this area.
And that is actually an important thing
that you have to manage the goals.
Let's take a quick look here again.
Unfortunately, I can only manage the goals
if I manage the goals myself.
You can simply define a completely normal new goal.
For example, I want to have a website with a certain title.
I can do it by event.
I can download a certain file, for example.
If I say, OK, I want to have this goal,
a certain click on the link on the external page.
It's like the example before.
For example, I offer banner places
and say, OK, banner place XY.
I just want to take a look at how often, for example,
there is a conversion rate.
Then I can simply set a goal,
just like for a while.
And then I have the opportunity to simply
add that directly.
That's actually a very good thing that you have here.
Now in the normal Matomo,
that would still be in that area.
We have five minutes left. I'll show you the premium plugins
that you have at Matomo Cloud.
There are the funnels.
The funnels actually build on the goals.
I can define a funnel for each goal.
That means I have the option here
to define different steps in the job application form.
That's just saying, OK,
where do the users come from on the job board?
How far do they go?
For example, a little less jump here
further.
Then a job is simply looked at
and will really apply for this job.
That means we have a conversion rate of 0.8.
Why is that?
Yes, well, I have about 600,
6500 entries up here
and down here 52 conversions.
That's a nice plugin
that you still have here.
Either the Cloud Hosted Plan or you can
have a look at it in the Matomo Marketplace
and then
buy it.
For four users it costs,
I'll give you a tip, that's 179 euros per year.
If you need several plugins,
then most of the time
a Matomo Cloud version is enough.
If you just go with it
and take a look at Matomo
and then
if you go up here again
and then look at the prices,
no, they are somewhere else,
pricing here and say, OK,
let's take a look at the other website
and then we would be
with the Cloud Hosting 19 euros
quite well, depending on how big the site is.
You can here, for example, 35 euros,
if you now counter it and say, OK,
you have 100,000, 35 euros would be
say 400 euros a year, 400, 500 euros a year.
That's actually the price for three
plugins.
This is the Activity Log, for example,
Funnels, which you have with you.
You can do the complete white labeling and these custom reports.
Just like this form, form tracking
is also very good for you. Now I can only recommend
this form tracking is,
every form is automatically
measured by Matomo and
here as a form.
And then you can just look at it, when you have
Apply to Job form. What is the starter rate?
The starter rate is simply when something is clicked.
So when the focus is set in the form,
the first time with the form is entered
and you have such a submission rate is actually
also a very good plugin,
what you have with you here. Media,
for example, video, audio, player, YouTube
like Meo or Selfhost, which you want to analyze.
Then you actually have it here with you, you have the title,
you do the video resource,
great feature, A-B testing,
of course two versions against each other,
heatmaps, as you normally know them,
fail to load,
it doesn't work right now,
but most of the time it does.
What we then have the option,
are these session recordings, here the real click
is recorded. Let's take a quick look at it here.
So we have something here
that you should normally deactivate.
So you can just take a look at it,
how does the user click, what is the mouse interaction
and so on.
A great feature, if you really want to try things out
or want to measure how something pops up dynamically
or works, I can only recommend
user-defined reports.
If you have any report, you can build it yourself here,
it is then simply calculated
and you can then display different metrics against each other.
This is also a very, very good
report.
Exactly, now it is
that we are actually at the end
in this area.
You can now also ask questions,
be it in the chats or here, you can also unmute
if you want to and then just directly
ask, if you have any questions.
But let's take a quick look.
Now let's take a quick look at Melanie.
I have a question about the period reports
for search terms without results.
So internal searches, exactly, the monthly reports
deliver less hits than the daily reports
in the respective month. So how can it be?
Does the aggregation not work
or do I still understand the report wrong?
You have to take a look at that now.
I don't have it on a specific
example.
Let's take a quick look
at that.
I hope I can actually
replicate it here. That means
you actually mean for October
the visits for internal search questions.
I don't know if you mean that.
You can also
take a quick look
at the reports.
Let's take a quick look
at that.
Exactly, search the reports without results.
So that here, actually, if I take the daily ones
together and then actually the aggregated months
are different. Normally that shouldn't be the case.
You probably have to take a closer look at
why that's the case.
Actually, that shouldn't be the case
normally. But you can
take a look. We can take a video session
afterwards. I'll just take a closer look
at where the problem might be
if that's okay for you.
Exactly.
Then we'll just do it that way. Just message me.
Otherwise...
Otherwise,
I hope I could give you a good
overview of the questions.
About the different reports.
If you have any questions, feel free to come in here.
If you have any questions,
I can tell you how I did it back then.
There's the Matomo Forum. Lucas was there as well.
He also helped me a lot.
It's a Matomo Forum.
There's even a German forum.
You can post something there as well.
It also helps a lot if you have the cloud version.
There's even a Patomo support.
There are videos. There are English videos.
I also have a few videos.
What else is there? Exactly. Lucas is still writing
a Q&A session at 4 p.m.
There's Melanie.
That's in English. Could you possibly
take that with you?
For example, if there's a problem,
you can also ask good questions.
You can also ask questions.
If you're interested,
you can also ask questions.
There's also the
Techmanage integration.
Self-hosted and so on.
That's about the five experts.
We'll see each other in 10 minutes.
Feel free to switch into the Q&A session.
Maybe Lucas will post a link
so you can chat in that area
right away.
Thank you for listening, for staying tuned.
There are almost 20 people.
I was very happy. If there's anything else,
just write to us.
There are no stupid questions.
Just don't be shy to write to us.
We can look at it together
and solve everything together.
I wish you a very nice day.
Thank you for your time here at the Matomo Camp.
Tomorrow is another day.
Take a look at a lot of interesting presentations.
Take care and stay healthy.
Bye!