Hello and welcome to the second MatomoCamp, it's really great to have everyone here again.
My name is Richard Stark, I'm one of the support team members here with Matomo and today we're
going to be talking about multi-server setups for Matomo and we're going to have a little
practical walkthrough on setting up Matomo with a Docker image that we can use for multi-server
deployments.
So you might be asking yourself what exactly is a multi-server setup?
A multi-server setup Matomo is when we have multiple different application servers and
multiple web servers that are all working together to serve requests, to handle tracking
requests or UI requests, we can have dedicated servers to run core archive command for example.
The goal for that is basically to have many different servers working together to handle
all the requests.
The benefit of this of course is that we can scale up these multiple different servers
quite easily when we have high traffic and we can scale down again and have low amounts
of traffic.
It also gives us some really great redundancy so that if a specific server has an error
we can quickly remove that server from the pool of servers and continue on without losing
much or without losing any data at all.
So one of the most important things when we're talking about a multi-server deployment for
Matomo is that we need to have the same code base deployed across all of the different
servers.
So this would be the same version of Matomo, the same plugin files and that sort of information.
If we have for example one server that's out of date or we have one server that doesn't
have the same plugins that the rest of the servers are, it's going to be serving the
wrong version of the Matomo tracking code.
It might not be able to process all of the tracking requests that we send to that server
so it could cause some data loss as well.
So apart from the code base there are some other files that we also want to synchronize.
These are files such as our config files, it's something that we would expect to edit
from time to time so we wouldn't have to want to have to go through a redeployment
every time we change the config file so that's not something that we would want to bake into
our deployment image.
The other thing as well is custom user files so these are things like your favicon or your
logo.
If you change that through the UI obviously you want to make sure that that is synchronized
across all of the different servers.
There are some things that we also need to do in a multi-server environment in terms
of configuration so we'll have a look at those configuration settings further on when we're
busy with the setup.
We're going to be using a couple different tools today.
One of those tools obviously is Docker.
We need to have Docker installed server or device that we're going to be using this on.
The other thing that we're going to be using today is Portainer CE, Portainer Community
Edition.
It's a really nice graphical user interface that we can use to make our lives a little
bit easier.
It's also a little bit easier to do a video on.
Not many people want to spend 30 to 40 minutes staring at a terminal screen so we're going
to be using the graphical user interface.
The benefit of this as well is it's quite similar to a lot of other container or Docker
orchestration tools that you'll probably be familiar with in other systems as well.
So we'll start off by going to the containers and we'll create a new container.
So for the name we'll just give this Tomo for now and then for the Docker image we want
to set this to Tomo Latest Version.
We'll scroll down here to the bottom and we'll set up a bind mount.
Now this bind mount is specifically done so that we can synchronize our config file.
So for now what we'll do is we'll put the location of a folder beside the container
that we know is going to exist.
It's not going to be something that is deleted if we volume or something like that.
So that that file can exist so we can create a similar link for it later on in the process.
Then for the host portion this is going to be wherever you have your config file set
up on a network share.
So this could be for example an FF share, it could be some other type of shared network
location.
In the example today there is no config file present.
We're going to be creating that config file but if you already have a config file set
up for Tomo with your database and everything configured you can reuse that existing configuration
file.
And then to make life a little bit easier with the setup today we're just going to
change the network to host and click deploy container.
Once that is running we'll click on the little icon over here that looks like a console.
That's so that we can execute into the container so we can run a couple of mounts.
We'll leave everything as default here to connect as the root user.
And the first thing that we're going to do is we're going to run an apt update.
This is so that we can install a couple of other tools that we're going to be using
during the process today and those tools are cron, unzip and nano so that we can edit a
couple of files.
So we'll hit yes there when that asks us to and we'll give that a minute to shut
installing.
Next we're going to change the directory of where we are right now from the working
directory for the mitomo codebase to the source directory for the mitomo codebase.
And then we're going to download a script file.
This script file is specifically so that we can automate the process of downloading all
of the different plugins.
Once that is downloaded we'll do a chmod command to make that file executable.
And then we'll edit that file.
Alright, so what we want to do is we want to grab our license key.
In that third line where it shows license key is to just paste that into the file.
Hit control O to save and control X to exit.
Once that is done we have our file placed or our license key placed into the file.
We'll run the script file.
So the benefit of using the Docker image in this case is we have access to that environment
variable so we can make sure that when we run this command or if you eventually copy
paste this command into your Docker container you can be 100% certain that you're getting
the correct version of plugins for the version of mitomo that you are running.
The plugins that it's downloading here specifically are the premium bundle plugins as well as
a couple of the extra optional plugins that we recommend having installed.
If you do not have a premium bundle plugin license you will need to edit the script so
that you can move those files.
If you have some other optional files or optional plugins that you do want to install that are
not included in that script you can also edit those in and add them to the script file.
Next we're going to move all of the plugins that we've just downloaded into the correct
directory and we'll clean up behind ourselves and just remove some of those empty folders
and that script file because we're not going to need that script file anymore.
Next we're going to be setting up a crontab for the www data user.
The first crontab that we're going to set up is specifically for the custom js update
command.
So it might sound strange to say I don't have any custom js on my server.
What this command does is that every minute on the minute it runs this command to update
the Matomo.js file so that it has all of the correct tracking code for all of the plugins
that you have installed.
A lot of the plugins and especially some of the premium plugins are designed in a way
that if you're not using them, if you're not tracking any data for them, they're not
going to add their tracking code to the Matomo.js file just to keep that file as small as possible.
This is specifically the case for things like the eat maps or session recordings and we
also want to do a similar sort of crontab for the tag manager.
This is important because if you edit a tag manager container through the UI and you click
update or save or publish, that command is only going to be executed on the server that
you are directly connected to through the UI.
So this will make sure that those container files are updated across all of the different
servers continuously.
Once that's done, we'll hit control O to save and we'll hit control X.
Next, we want to download our geolocation database.
Again, we're going to make some use of some environment variables just to make our lives
a little bit easier when you copy pasting these commands and we'll download that.
Next, we're going to unzip that file and we will rename the file and move it to the correct
folder.
Now that that is done, we have a mostly working code base that we can use for Matomo.
And what we'll do is we'll connect directly to that Matomo server.
Looks like we're connected to HTTPS there.
All right, now we're going to be going through the database creation setup for Matomo.
So we'll go through our system check over here.
Everything looks good.
For the database, this is hosted on the same host as the Docker installation, so we'll
leave everything as default.
This is going to be different depending on how you have things set up.
Server, so we'll type our password in there, our database name, and then you can select
your data table prefix over here, click next, and have the database installation done in
just a couple of seconds.
It seems to be taking its time today.
There we go.
Oh, it's taking us back to the start of the thing.
I'm not sure what happened there.
We'll just go through that step again and see if we can get things working.
Let's see if we can get it going second time.
Type our password, select Matomo database, and today, let's give this a different table
prefix just in case something already triggered on the previous install, that just a second.
There we go.
Tables are created.
Now, we do need to go through the setup process because this is a new install of setting up
the superuser.
We can sign up to Newsletter if you want to, do that for this fake email address, and then
we will give our new website a name and time zone.
All right, now that this is set up, we just need to ask a couple of steps to make sure
that everything is working.
All right, so that is working, so we can go back to our retainer page over here, and what
we're going to do now is we're going to move the configuration file that has just been
created, the working directory for Matomo, into the source directory that we were talking
about here.
All right, once that is done, we're going to edit the entry script, entry point script
specifically for the Docker container.
This is so that we can run a symlink command specifically for when the Docker container
starts up.
So we'll copy that symlink command directly to the file, and then we'll hit Ctrl-O to
save, Ctrl-X to exit.
Next, we're going to edit the config file that we've just moved to the source location,
and we're going to install some of those, or going to set up some of those config options
that we were talking about earlier.
The first config option that we're going to do is to be able to tell Matomo that we're
working with a multi-server environment.
What this does is in a lot of the places where it would be enabled by default, it tries to
prevent Matomo from writing to the config file very often.
It also disables certain options that wouldn't normally work in a multi-server environment
just to prevent any sorts of issues.
The next thing that we also want to do is we want to disable the plugin administration
option.
Because we're running on a multi-server environment for Matomo, we cannot install or activate
or deactivate plugins through the UI.
We need to do that through the command line, because it also is going to require us to
edit our base image and to do a redeployment of the entire cluster.
The next one that we're also going to disable is we're going to disable the auto-update.
This is the same principle as the plugins.
We don't want to accidentally click the update button, and then we have one Docker container
that is updated, and the rest of them are outdated.
That can cause some serious issues.
The next one that we also want to disable is the general settings administration.
This is things where you'd set, for example, your trusted host names, things like that.
We don't want to be editing the config file through the UI.
Whenever we do that, we want to be editing the file that is set up in our shared network
location.
All right, now that that is done, we'll hit Control-O and enter to save, Control-X to
exit.
Once that is done, we're just going to change the owner of that file to make sure that we
don't run into any permissions issue further down the road.
Now that that is done, we're going to switch over to our terminal or to our SSH section,
and we're going to run a Docker commit command.
This is simply a Docker commit, Tomo.
This is the name of the container that is currently running, and then this is the name
of the Docker image that we're committing the changes to.
In this case, we'll just give it a name, something like Tomo Premium.
That should take just a second.
All right, now we have our Docker image configured and set up with all of the code base files
that we need, as well as our geolocation database for Tomo.
We will switch back to our Portainer, go to the containers, and we can now shut down this
running Tomo Docker container.
Now when we start up the new container, we'll be using the brand new container that we've
just made all the changes to.
So I went and skipped a bit of a step there, but if we go have a look at the images over
here, you'll see that we now have a new image named Tomo Premium.
So this is a locally stored image.
If you wanted to deploy this to different servers, what you'd need to do is you'd
need to copy that image file.
If you're using Portainer, you can select the box over here, and you can click Export,
and that will export that container image, and you can use that to copy onto your different
servers that are running Docker.
If you have a private Docker repository or Docker image repository, you can also upload
that there so that you can make it a little bit easier for your deployments.
So we'll go back to those containers over there, and we'll add a new container.
So we'll give it a name that's different to the one that's already running, so we'll
just keep it consistent and go for Tomo Premium.
Also change to advanced mode over here, because we're not using an image from a Docker repository,
we want to use the local image.
So we'll name that one Tomo Premium as well, add the tag there for latest.
Now we'll scroll down here to the bottom for the volumes.
Now we want to mount two different volumes.
One of those volumes is going to be our config file, so this is going to be exactly the same
way that we set it up previously.
This is the config file in the source folder, and this is the location of the config file
on the NFS share.
And the second file that we want to set up on the network share is the user folder.
This is the one that contains all of our user custom images and fabricants and things like
that.
And this example, we'll set it up on host and we'll hit deploy container.
Shouldn't take too long to deploy, so that's done.
We can hit refresh on our page over here just to see if the Tomo server is up and running.
Great, so that's all working perfectly.
So what we're going to do again is we're going to execute into the container, but this time
we're going to connect as a different user.
We want to connect as the www data user.
It's important that whenever we execute any commands on the Docker container or any Tomo
server in general, that if we're executing a console command or if we're changing files,
we need to do it as the correct user, otherwise we could face some pretty nasty permissions
issues.
So the first command that we're going to do is we're going to be setting our license key
for the Tomo marketplace so that we can activate all of our plugins.
So we'll run that one and right, great, that's all set up.
And now it comes to a fairly important part about a multi-server setup for Tomo and that
is how to activate a plugin in a multi-server environment.
As I mentioned earlier on, you can't just activate a plugin through the UI, so it has
to be done through the console command.
Now the benefit of going through all the steps that we've just gone through for setting up
the container, we make sure that all of our plugin files are consistent between all of
the different servers.
We have our config file synchronized, so when we have all of that ready and we want to activate
that new plugin, we can just run that console plugin activate command.
So this one specifically, it's a short little script that we're just going to execute directly
in the console.
So this is just going to go through that list of plugins that we had set up earlier that
was downloaded and activate them.
There's a couple of other plugins such as the Tag Manager plugin that we want to make
sure is active because it might not be activated by default in Tomo server.
Right, that's running now.
So this is a good point to really talk about how important it is to keep this synchronized.
That's kind of the most important thing that if you don't take anything else away from
this talk, the most important thing to understand for a multi-server environment is that we
need to have same code base synchronized across all of the different servers.
Because we're connecting to the same database in the backend, if we have servers that are
differently configured or they have different plugins and they try to activate them and
deactivate them, we can very quickly run into some major issues.
And the problem with those sorts of issues is they usually show themselves in the form
of lost data or serious issues when you try to connect or pull reports from your instance
or track some data.
Things are just not going to go right.
So we'll give it another minute over here to activate the plugins.
If you're doing this on an existing Tomo server, it can take quite a bit of time.
The larger the database is, the longer it's going to take to activate new plugins.
The reason for that is that it often has to make some schema changes to some of the existing
tables and it's also makes some links, some farm keys, primary keys, things like that.
That in a lot of cases, if you have a very large database, it just takes a lot of time.
Should be the last one there.
Great.
That is the last one in our list.
So we'll go back to the Tomo dashboard over here and we'll just make sure that everything
is working.
We don't have any issues.
Also go to our settings and have a look at all of the plugins or some of the plugins
that we've configured.
Are they set up correctly in the back end of Tomo?
All right, great.
So we've got our search performance over here.
We have some other options as well.
All right, great.
So this looks like everything is set up correctly.
Thank you so much for joining us today.
It's really great for you guys to have joined us.
I will be sticking around in the chat afterwards as well if you guys have any questions for
me.
You're more than welcome to ask.
You're also more than welcome to, if you're watching or recording this, send us an email
over to support at matomo.org and just mention that you'd like to chat to Richard and I'm
sure he'll be able to get to some of those emails at some point in the future.
Hope you guys have a great MatomoCamp further.
Bye.