Well then, it's about two o'clock
and with that it's time for the
next session
for this i would like to introduce
Silva Arapi she is a
digital rights advocate with a special interest
in the topics of privacy and intersect
and she is also one of the
co-founders of Cloud68.co
working to make the use
of open source digital infrastructure easy and convenient
in her talk how
to stay compliant with privacy regulations with
Matomo analytics to recover the importance of
compliance with privacy regulations especially for business
perspective and how matomo analytics makes it
easy for people to ensure the privacy
of the visitors for this to regain
all their comparison with google analytics and
with that take away
many thanks for the introduction michael's hello
everyone i'm very excited to join this
very first event of matthew camp today
as marcus mentioned i will be speaking
about compliance with
privacy regulations by using digital analytics tool
such as mega man olympics
i have a quick look into the
agenda for today i will quickly go
over
the discussion about personal data why
are so many regulations in place in
order to safeguard this data from
the companies let's say for a while
hosting personal data we will go through
the alternatives that we have when it
comes to using digital analytics tools such
as google analytics madam analytics which will
be made the
the main focus of this event but
of course there are also other tools
out there which you can use and
then we will go over the main
requirements requirements of gdp are and we
will look into the tools that moto
mo provides us with which
it helps us which support us to
respond to the requests of data subjects
and as a consequence that makes compliance
easier
so a few words about me i
am a free software and online privacy
advocate at least this is what i
do on a volunteer level i am
a board member of open labs hackerspace
and in tirana albania and
ngo where i have contributed for the
last couple of fears and where i
had the opportunity to learn about the
free software movement and since then i've
been engaged in various small open source
projects software i've mainly been engaged
with advocacy and with a special focus
on the topic of online privacy i'm
also one of the co-founders of clouds
is sixty eight a company which supports
all their small teams to make use
of free and open source software
i
i have been using matomo in the
last two years maybe have despite the
fact that i haven't used it in
a set up where we would handle
like a huge amount of data either
close it or closely looked into it
as an alternative of google analytics
and which of course and not only
makes compliance
easier but has many other advantages compared
to this proprietary tool which i will
try to go into more detail later
during this presentation
and so i'm sure that everyone who
is hearing this session now couldn't have
missed a hearing the expression that data
is the new oil we hear this
spread pretty often maybe in the last
decade and since
two thousand two thousand and thirteen with
the edward snowden reveal the asians about
how personal data was being mishandled not
one hundred not only from companies but
also from government bodies there has been
a lot of discussion and many other
cases of data breaches have been published
which created an increase
this need for a public debate about
how companies were storing personal data how
they were processing it how much data
they were holding and how much information
does the public have about this and
this increase of
of of the cases of abuse we
can say have increased also the need
from public bodies to create proper legislations
on the ways how do these companies
should handle the data and how they
should also take measures
to to protect it and to not
abuse with it
the reason why companies are so eager
to collect as much data as possible
because is because of courses this expression
says the data is then it means
that
there is also there are also lots
of profits about collecting and making use
of the of the data
so this is why it's really important
to have proper legislation in place and
to how to hold these companies accountable
about their actions
so privacy compliance
i have a very short definition of
the term is that it is accompanies
accordance with established personal information protection guidelines
specifications or legislations good but depending on
your country where you are operating or
where your customer base is that you
might face
calling two different regulation regulations so this
is a case by case this can
be treated on a case by case
scenario but two of the most not
only popular but also more strict regulations
is in play
these are the european general data protection
regulation dpr through which also during this
presentation we will look into more detail
but also the ccp a which is
california's customer privacy act both are designed
to protect unauthorized access to what's called
personally identifiable information with which we will
also define in the
upcoming slides and so basically this presentation
will mainly be designed for those companies
who are gathering personal data of individuals
who are performing digital analytics but i
are also looking for tools which will
support them to stay compliant with this
virus regulations
and so despite the fact that there
is like there has there has been
this long discussion and abuse about the
misuse of personal data at the end
companies also need to collect it because
it's also way to
to serve their customers to improve their
experiences to perform innovation and so the
main considerations here is that we should
perform digital analytics actions in this gdp
our era by having like ethics in
mind and by
complying and by using the right tools
which support our ethics
and so as i mention why while
there are virus
regulations in place one of the most
streak that most discussed wants is that
european gdp are which requires all companies
despite the fact if they are in
basing the eu or not if they
are serving to eel based citizens
yes
they will have to comply this is
a regulations which strengthens and unifies that
data protection from for all individuals within
the eu
and the this regulation of course is
quite complex and if we well to
go and dig way way much deeper
of course we would need the support
of
what consultants do
so to discuss like everything related to
it but in a more or if
we were to explain it very easily
it is applicable to accompany every time
that it is collecting personal data if
you're starting from personal data of this
individuals then you have to come
comply with the data protection principles which
are guided by the duty pr so
of course in order to collect this
data you should also have a legal
basis for doing so you should always
communicate this legal basis to your users
which are called
the data subjects and so they should
be always informed about the type of
data that you are collecting about them
and why do you need this data
and of course they show they have
various rights upon this data which again
we will look into more
details
and an important aspect of the gdp
art is that
it also included some other identifiers in
the concept of personal data and for
example ip addresses if an ip address
can be used to uniquely identify a
person this under the gdp are this
is
also i consider the personal information and
personal data so it's not enough to
have like very concrete information about the
person which falls under the pii such
as their name their home address their
email address but if
the there are some sort of third
party identifiers which you can use to
match and two in in in in
another way to identify a person's identity
that falls under the personal data and
here we include ip addresses
located in the fire spades you are
else or page titles user ids e-commerce
or derive these locations and heatmaps and
session recordings so this is a this
was a major upgrade with a gdp
iron to to also include this kind
of identifiers a spa
i have the legislation so every time
that you are collecting this information you
should meet make sure that you are
following all of the gdp our guidelines
so when and especially in the case
of small companies who do not have
all of the resources to go over
very careful
and
check of their internal procedures they should
try to minimize as much as possible
look the amount of data the amount
of personal data that they are set
saving about their individuals and when possible
if they do not really need it
they should
should do
completely avoid doing so and of course
there are ways for example if in
your website you are hosting the digital
analytics solution but you are mainly interested
in analyzing the user behavior but you
don't really need to know who this
user sar than you
should make sure to configure your tools
in the right way so you so
that you just get the information that
you need but without a whole thing
any type of personal information about your
visitors
so in this way you will save
your two herself a lot of time
and resources and which can be which
you otherwise would have to dedicate to
communicate what kind of data you use
you are hosting through your privacy policy
and all
also to comply with the data subject's
request so in every scenario when you
can avoid that so all of hosting
personal data you should consider doing so
and also another benefit let's say of
not tossing personal data when that is
possible
and which you can achieved by using
up like matomo as we will see
later is that you can configure it
in a way so that you can
also avoid the constant screens which are
to those annoying screens that we see
every time that we open a new
website full asks i will inform sir
about cookies and the data that they
are storing because this has proved to
also impact the customer experience so if
you can in a way avoid this
at a wall
that can also be beneficial for for
your business purposes as well
moto mod actually provides a way for
for you to achieve this so in
the case that and you do not
track personal data and you also have
a need to have enabled calculus tracking
you can
bypass this requirement which is quite usual
by legislation such as gdp yard and
the privacy to display this banner asking
for cookie or tracking consent
the reason why with matomo this is
possible is that visitors aren't tracked across
various websites as it happens in the
case of the google analytics visitors can
be tracked within different days so we
know the timeframe of matter
obama does not do
perform profiling of visitors and of course
other data can be used for your
own purposes and not for other purposes
such as in the case of google
analytics with whom if you share the
data they can also use it use
it for their own
offerings
and
an important consideration under the gdp are
are the rights of other data subjects
for the people to whom you are
hosting this personal data either the gdp
are they have various rights which they
can exercise anytime and inara
drip to stay compliant you will need
to have the necessary tools to respond
and to perform this request by your
data subjects some of this er rights
are the right to be informed you
have to always communicate and the kind
of personal data
you are collecting through through a privacy
policy at least this is the most
usual way to communicate this to your
users they have the right to access
this data so they can ask for
you all of this information and you
will have to share it with them
they have the right
to ask for erasure of the data
they have the right to ask for
a modification the that they they they
pretend that the data that you are
hosting is not correct or net needs
to be updated they have the right
for date of birth of ability which
means that in some cases they might
ask for this day
data and you will have to send
them send it to them in a
machine readable format which they can easily
use afterwards they also have the right
to object this mainly happens in the
case where you are not asking for
consent but you
or performing the data collection under the
legal basis of legitimate interest and in
this case your users might have the
right to object or the data collection
and of course in the case that
you are asking for consent they have
the right to withdraw consent and usually
it's advisable to offer an opt out
option which is easily accessible by your
data subjects
all of these specifications
under the gdp are put a lot
of pressure on companies of all sizes
because no matter of the size of
the company they have to make sure
that they are respecting this personal data
so they need to take all the
appropriate measures to stay compliant
this requires additional resources additional more and
education within organizations to also train their
internal staff and to design all the
organizational procedures with the data protection principles
in mind
so with this being said you when
it comes to making the decision about
your do
digital analytics tool you might have to
go through a decision making process when
choosing the right and appropriate goals and
as i mentioned during this presentation we
will mainly go over the compression of
a google
politics and madame analytics and why i
believe that matthau moist bathroom for privacy
compliance but of course there are plenty
of tools out there the only thing
that i would suggest is that when
you make this decision up we should
also
so try to do luke and to
consider as a factor in the decision
making process the tools that the software
provides in terms of privacy option so
if usually the decision making power
losses we consider simply the features or
the olympics
how powerful this tool is in terms
of analytics i think it's really important
to also add in the decision making
and these other options i haven't used
any other open source tools besides matomo
but when i looked into it as
the alternative
two google analytics it really makes things
easier and it does provide great documentation
in terms of how you should treat
the gdp are cases
the why you should consider my thermo
as a replacement of google analytics
the main reason here dimension is the
fact that what what when you are
using a google analytics who you are
sharing your data with google a big
tech company which we cannot say whose
reputation hasn't been that great in the
real reason that last couple of years
do we also know that google uses
these data that you share with them
of your visitors they use it to
have feed their data basis for user
profiling which has been considered a big
threat by many privacy advocates a threat
not only to people of people some
data but
also to democracy we can dare to
say
with the google analytics you also do
not have ownership of the data you
are sharing data with google it belongs
to them and you have to agree
with their own with their own terms
anytime with my thumb or you have
options
such as the option to halls the
data on your own being eaten at
your home server if you have like
the technical
and skills to do so
as we discussed third year with my
thelma you also have this option to
annoy to avoid this annoying tracking concept
screens for those businesses who might be
able to
to configure moto mo in this way
while with google you cannot do that
because you are sharing
because they are using every data that
you share for their own purposes as
well and also with my thermo as
in the case of every other open-source
software you have flexibility since the software
is open source you have the freedom
to customize the software according to your
own needs too
develop plugins
so that they can perform other actions
so if you're a developer and you
want to customize it based on your
organizational needs you can do so or
you can allocate appropriate resources to customize
with my domo and of course you
have the option
the hosted on your own premises or
you can go for the month on
the cloud offering which in any case
one does not use the data that
you host in their flowed for for
other purposes as in the case of
google analytics and of course you will
be you will have this option to
be more independent because in a scenario
for example even if you are using
the method macleod
loud and they change their pricing model
you can also always have the option
to self post or look for other
options available and while with the google
analytics it is as it is appropriate
dirty software this migration process might be
a little bit more accomplish
kate it then simply moving metal mall
your muthama data from one server to
another so this are some important considerations
to to take usually when people just
look for an analytics solution it's easier
to go for google analytics because it's
free in the sense that you do
not pay any money for it but
you do pay
and with the data that you are
sharing beat your visitors data and of
course and also by using a more
privacy compliant tool you can also gain
competitive advantage because in the cases of
data
shoes companies can also have like very
negatively impacting their reputation so if you
do take this appropriate measures about your
competitors don't then you'll automatically in a
way are gaining some competitive advantage over
them
so why do i tamo some of
the main benefits of using moto mod
as i mentioned is the fact that
you have one hundred percents data ownership
it provides so many privacy options which
you can customize and will help you
stay compliant with the virus legislation
and privacy laws depending on your scenario
where you are based or what kind
of data you are hosting
it's reliable and secure moto mois open
source and there is an active community
behind it for like actively contributing to
the source called reporting bugs and helping
in improving it and you have the
option to hosted on premise or on
cloud
regarding the privacy options of that moto
mod has to offer
it really makes compliance easier by providing
many features for the bedroom
and and to quickly go over this
feature matomo provides you with data anonymisation
and
because it is designed with privacy by
default in mind so it implements range
of data anonymisation techniques for example you
have the option to not record the
flight ip address of your visitors here
is a screenshot from the moto mo
interface where as you can see you
have
do the option to select how many
bytes of your visitor's ip addresses should
be masked and this gives you more
flexibility let's say in other way that
you are how you are hosting this
personal data of your visitors it has
a gdp our manager
two which of four for which we
will go in more detail later but
it helps you which will support you'll
have to respond in a easier way
to your data subject's request matomo can
be configured to not process any personal
data or b i i've shared in
the resources of this
slide a link which has a very
detailed guide on how you can achieve
this
there's the option to configure moto moto
automatically delete logs from the data that
database
which means that you can also automate
this process as well also according to
gdp are you should have this and
and this procedures in place also do
about the timing on how about data
retention which means how long do you
need to save your customers' data
so according to this procedures you can
also configure moto all in in the
right way
so that you comply with these regulations
are met almost supports the do not
track preference which is like do
about browser configuration of your users so
that they notify ultimate magically met the
omo also indicated that they do not
want their behavior to be tracked
moto mo has other options such as
to disable the life features to disable
tracking cookies you can customize the way
how your users opt out of all
the trafficking you have you can delete
visitors data when requested through the gdp
prior to which we will look into
later
i also imagine that previously that the
date i stopped used for other person
purposes compared to google analytics you have
the option to disable visitor logs and
profiles
and options in terms of wherever you
are starting these days though
so we also mentioned earlier all of
the rights that the data subject has
under the gpp are legislation
a sorta part of the background noises
i saw the gdp our manager hasn't
been developed to ensure that at websites
are fully compliant with this regulation and
it provides you with the right tools
so that you can take appropriate steps
to to comply here is a screenshot
from the gdp article from the motto
i'm an olympics and as you can
see it makes it quite clear and
it keeps you informed of all of
the options that you have when dealing
with a subject's data so the first
do
djing in this menu would be to
search for the data subject
and this is what it looks or
what it looks likes in my thermo
so you have the option to choose
and have the data source which can
be for from which website or if
you're hosting different websites who controls the
website from where you want to filter
this data
and here you can find data objects
by performing different filtering options to find
the matching data subjects
and in this way through this filtering
tools there are various actions that you
do
can perform such as for example if
a data subject or subject was performed
they write off access to this data
after searching the data by using this
gdp article you can export the matching
results and send it to the data
objects and this can very easily
we'd be done by these export selected
visits button another option is to delete
the selected visits and you can apply
these in the case when the data
subject are on
applying their right of erasure and the
procedure that you have full always the
same you filter out the data but
in this case you will simply delete
those visits and inform the data subject
or for for this action
the data subjects also have the right
of rectification so in some cases you
might need to update the data that
you are storing in the moto mall
you'll have to do this by accessing
the database or modifying the records but
in some cases a workaround of this
law
when in setup word of that disposable
might also be to simply delete the
data if you don't need it anymore
and your data subject also have the
right of data birth ability and in
this case you will again exercise a
similar similar steps as in the case
of the right to access and you
will send in a machine readable format
there
data through your data subject so that
they they can access it and they
they can use it
for for their for example if they
are moving from your offering to another
service provider they have access to the
right to ask for of this data
and another right of your data subjects
is the right to object this is
applicable only when processing personal data with
a main interest as the lawful basis
and in this case you should offer
an opt out feature to your user
source
matomo again makes this easy through the
interface where you can customize the output
i frame as you wish and then
you can embed get scold on your
website to make it as easy as
possible for your data subjects to opt
out when they wish and the
the also
visitors have the right to withdraw consent
and this is obtainable and only if
you are using constant as a legitimate
ground to to collect this data
i am migrating from google analytics to
matomo in my personal experience i have
faced this question a few times and
the procedure has been like quite simple
method that provides again very good documentation
that you could follow but again i've
tested this scenario with do not like
huge amount of data
but in each case you should go
over an evaluation process to make sure
that everything is working as it should
for you so do for this process
as well and the resources of this
presentation i've shared a guy
guide from moto mo which hopefully will
make the migration easier for you in
case that you have already started google
analytics and you want to consider a
switch and start using method
so many thanks for hearing this was
i
the presentation for today so if you
have any question you can feel free
to arrive them in the chat or
thank you so
ready to questions or discussions in the
tub the first one is what do
you mean page to page titles and
pitch your own opera data do you
mean together with all that they do
but yes i do this because this
kind of data in the sort of
way can be used to identify and
can be converted into a b i
which means that if there is a
way that your data controller which is
the person who is tracking this data
and can match or it can reach
can i after your identity i
identity after collecting this information that means
that if you are hosting this kind
of like a search square is that
usual user month entering your website that
means that you are hosting personal data
and you should take appropriate steps to
save
quieted as jpr guides us
venture revenue
and even if anonymized a part of
the uterus isn't the whole of beatrice
stored in the database
in the in the database it's stores
only the anonymized version of
the ip address but of course
i know anonymizing ip addresses is not
enough to say that you are not
storing personal data you should also make
sure about what other type of information
that you are posting but this is
like one of the features that my
thermo provides so that you can minimize
that information so at least this is
like a step to more to more
privacy
okay and we have another question i
think it may relate to the prescription
because we have a bit of delay
but what about pixel tech
well that also falls under the
i have personal data because in some
cases they do a caucus might save
some unique identifiers which can then be
used again to identify a person's identity
and thank you about that i am
going to wait for another minute to
see any more questions pop up
but that seems to have been the
case if any other questions arise feel
free to keep using the tablet it's
gonna stay up and besides that once
again thank you for the presentation and
depth and ready
they think everyone