the hello everyone my name's christian i'm
a greeting you from the city of
hala on their zala in the beautiful
country of germany and and well stretched
to topic we're going to talk more
or less exactly about the dat and
re wire to be more specific i
am seated in germany in europe in
the european union where we are in
gdp our country soda general data protection
regulation
in effect since twenty eighteen has changed
some things to be a little on
the stated in this case andrea looking
about the public reaction so matomo and
the masses to the people really care
about gdp our compliance does is one
of the up
big
barbecues piste at one of the big
unique selling points of metal but in
general it's well in a very big
letters on the homepage as well dad's
motto more is a data secure alternative
to google analytics and two other discuss
not open but closed source software as
so
is this even a good selling point
in this case so uh what did
people think about data security about data
privacy
so to be his daughter here and
if you can't see the infographics data
well and we can provide you with
the presentation afterwards does is no problem
anywhere this here and now
sorry for not having the exact routes
in any case but we were asking
some people or in this case as
the t style did so or how
half the new data protection regulations to
gdp are impacted on your sense of
security
at the chateau de pere auto sorry
so did anything change after the gdp
r came into effect this was asked
in this case to be exactly in
sweden so we are in northern europe
and according to the survey seventy five
percent
sat well no difference in any rate
so most of the people well before
g power and after gdp are no
difference at all
fourteen percent at least said i feel
more secure now soda gd per hour
at least for a round or a
sixth person did make a positive difference
and had a positive impact for four
percent not so much they said i
feel less secure and i
was seven percent do not know anything
about it or didn't care but
and in this case
so sorry i had this case so
dumb
majority well didn't think there was a
big difference before and after the gdp
are and at least fourteen fifteen per
cent around worried about i feel more
secure through the gdp are so in
this case most people hat at least
in sweden and it's seen as a
high
having a positive impact so did gdp
are as a while force of good
if you want to say
but howard's how was it done on
the well more regional or state level
dis case so another survey about gbr
enforcement so the data protection authorities this
case lack of expertise
so most public administration and is not
really ready for gdp are enforcement but
run second i've got a question from
ronan have you ever heard of german
citizen suing any websites because of misuse
of a rep analytic solution
i have come to that in a
moment of regarding the public authorities in
this case and you while they aren't
seen as that fit for the digital
digital age in this case mostly because
we have for example in germany rich
as a to country on the far
left side
site we have around seven hundred people
in personnel doing non technical staff and
only about one hundred so one in
seven people as a technical expert and
scares everyone else not so much in
other countries it's sometimes
more extreme for example uk which isn't
part of the european union any more
but there we have twenty two technical
experts regarding two six hundred and fifty
eight non technical personnel so does his
bit more extreme does case soda or
public authorities are very depend
and on the populace too i will
talk to them regarding our data breaches
and to coming to rollins questioned and
yeah i have i have heard of
german citizens swing while nato websites themselves
in germany you can't sue of bad
upside because of data privacy breach you
have to make an immigrant to the
local authority in this case to do
well data protection authority in germany data
protection is a thing for the specific
german states for example in
my case i'm living in a state
of saxony on the halt in germany
and just recently am working as a
data protection officer as well and just
recently i've actually had a case where
an online shop was suit
and by a person who wasn't a
client from that shop because the shop
dwell did i
did had some settings that ran exactly
gdp are conform so
it had it happens but you can
sue at least germany's you can sue
a website directly but you can make
an inquiry at a jar with your
local data protection authority so this has
happened this happens sometimes a lot but
not so much in germany as it
is in some other countries for example
many complaints were made in italy and
spain if i recall correctly
surprisingly not so much in germany new
rare as are regarding stereotypes re drums
have a bit of an
every bit of the offices in germany
do not have a bit of an
image as other big complainers about in
other countries it was well far worse
to beat her to be put in
brackets in this case about to be
answering their trolley yes it happens yes
it happened
ah and this is not so much
to fault in this case of the
weapon that it takes solution itself but
of the company who uses this solution
for example when you normally use google
analytics and a generous setting when you're
just
implement google analytics but moto mo as
well with the well default settings they
aren't gdp are compliant you need to
put them in some kind of sandbox
the typical cookie banners this case and
do you have to ask your customers
or your users to rep said users
before you track anything from them you
have to ask them if they are
okay with that and you have to
have an explicit yes and no button
and on this cookie banner and when
you do that you're fine when you
do it not well up until this
year may be there wasn't a data
protection authority who well was complaining about
it but it happens rally that beginning
at least in germany beginning with next
year to public authorities declared
that they would
controlled these well for example websites or
businesses or companies or whatever but it
would control the world gdp are complied
see far more thoroughly so that some
some things at least will change in
twenty twenty two
and this case but moving on i
hope i answered your question
well for gathering these factories so not
much has changed in everyday lives of
the people may be that some people
are complaining about having to click on
so many cookie bearers on websites at
least debts are what what i get
in germany that
people are like to complain that with
the gdp are everything is far more
complicated and you well at least that's
what i'm saying they are complaining about
having to make a decision
i saw i guessed this will become
a far more used to in the
coming years but right now re putting
aside this nuisance in this case not
much has changed and at least the
public sees it that way as well
that of the at the
is it across countries don't have much
expertise in the topic so in essence
why should a populace care about using
data friendly solutions
right now it's a bit of a
nuisance in some countries data protection is
even seen as a while kind of
hindering stone for innovation or up
for other sing other things so why
should the populace care
this case
sorry for the german-speaking part in this
case but i will translate are well
one big part could be
corona corona pandemic and his case and
use of the german recall it home
office no offense to brits in this
case to the homeless to remote working
situations we have at least since march
twenty twenty
different in many countries but at least
in germany i doubt was
a survey made by the b v
d w decison the german and
ah that cant earnest german association of
form at the digital to digital business
economics so indebted day the survey any
read regarding
can you imagine working in home office
working remotely because of covert or after
that as well and this case around
through re quarters seventy five point four
percent said yeah i can imagine working
from now on remotely
keep a sixty six per cent or
even expect their employers to happen appropriate
technical as well other kind of solution
for work remotely and fifty eight percent
even set that i want to have
the explicit possibility
eighty of working remotely
in this case in germany we had
some and not laws but some guidances
that came to effect during the lockdown
phases of the pandemic but they row
while they were were running out during
the re of the summer so they
are no longer in effect in germany
however in neighbouring austria since april they
even have a home office loss so
diskettes were
the mold working loss so very different
situation depending on the country but at
is the german populace wishes to half
warm of it's possibilities but they doubt
as with the public authorities they doubted
that their employers are ready for that
so and disaster
white is the right survey i was
asking questions is your employer well technically
ready so have dated do they have
the technical infrastructure too
enable you to work remotely and discuss
fifty four percent said yes but also
forty five per cent said no and
regarding the mistrust of an employer does
this even higher so this for once
also regarding blocked out phases maybe some
of you
you experienced this in your countries as
well when you had lockdowns up i've
here had some newspaper clippings regarding the
consequences of lockdown for example
in cologne
there even was an app developed regarding
the well kuroda regulations chaos debt and
suit because every state made more or
less their own rules there was a
bit of chaos there also regarding the
so-called home schooling so
add to the lockdown and the locked
on a school school stuff sorry i
which was also a big mess at
least in germany so that the typical
a joke was going on yeah what
do we expect only teachers working
in schools they don't have a clue
about i t infrastructure so of course
for example when december and a heart
lockdown was set in germany and first
day of so called homeschooling i was
done of course every sarah was well
stressed to the seams
https and broke down
so in this case regarding corona and
doctor one situation people are
on one hand bit in mistrust regarding
data protection but on the other hand
see well digitalization as a necessity at
least and maybe in combination of the
two and the well populace will develop
up to a prospective that i'm working
more and more in the digital realm
but who controls my employer that he's
not sniffing after me that he's not
trying to survey me to spy on
me
and at least in germany i've got
he has some paper clippings as well
regarding the while general
while the general outlook for example especially
not for example especially with regards to
the gay from economy is so google
amazon facebook metre apple microsoft etc
they are what
general and mistrust i especially like that
one thing that sat at well regarding
google pay and co at they are
warning once again of them so even
the journalists are getting tired of while
reporting about day
data protection incidents with facebook with google
with everyone else so on one hand
people don't really like data protection because
well it's an it's an hindrance isn't
it's nuisance it's a well staff to
do that i don't want to do
about
on the other hand we are at
least when our regarding germany we are
a very mistrustful folk regarding big corporations
it has a lot to do with
our history regarding kings and koreans doing
as they please regarding the national socialist
regime in the nineteen thirties and
forties regarding the stasi in the german
democratic republic and add iron curtain stuff
that happens so
we value on one hand and at
least germany b we value our privacy
very high but data protection is for
many is seen as some kind of
a nuisance so this is bit schizophrenic
discourse but that's a situation at eastern
germany where we are
r
and
to summarize this one so remote work
is more prevalent the dangerous for data
privacy are more apparent at one thing
that works in germany very very good
to stuffed think about the children for
example in school when you have to
work with for example zoo with microsoft
teams
with whatever often it's the case
that are teachers as well as parents
as well as the general populace they
say well if it works it works
and it's free so it's okay that's
the one hand but on the other
hand the well safety of children of
families as well as to genoa safety
as a stressed very highly so as
i said a bit of a schizophrenic
situation this case
but something at least the german speaking
countries have at least some kind of
well as sensibility in this case so
they say we while we have to
do something to keep us safe what
i dunno that's to general
thing does case but authorities are controlling
more often as i said in the
beginning twenty twenty two at the german
data protection authorities said that it wants
and will control more frequently
so what can we do regarding matomo
so what strategies could we apply for
once we meet to look more abroad
in this case we need to look
at other countries when we are living
in europe at the gdp arts
often seen as our some kind of
nuisance at least regarding international situations of
these countries that are on this map
green day rare implementing laws in recent
years that had a g d p
r as a template as an explicit
template some countries are not doing so
rally regarding data protection for example brazil
at are also and australia this is
a well not that good of situation
about the distance because that other laws
are lacking the united states for example
the state of california
it's demanded a specific law that was
modeled after the gdp are
but unfortunately california as part of the
united states and this case and united
states have laws like the u s
freedom act do you as cloud act
and other laws that are above the
california law and
and enable public administration in this case
a specific offices like the national security
agency and as a and ah
other are well security organs of the
state to well spy out everything that
is saved on a server even if
it's in europe to use cloud act
which came to effect on twenty eighteen
explicitly states that in regards of homeland
security and stuff like that
i'd add that the public authorities are
enabled to control every white person corporation
etc
and the stuff that they are having
for example they can control everything at
that is saved on any microsoft service
because microsoft has its seat in the
united states even if the server isn't
germany the company is the united states
that's degenerate problem discussed so
on the one hand the dpr isn't
as template as a model for well
similar laws and the world but on
the other hand we have i don't
want to call a loophole but we
have another situation
okay
where we have other countries that are
well gdp are compliant with out having
the gdp are as a law in
their country so on the one hand
we can look into countries that are
that are that are having laws specifically
i made after duty pr mp for
pixar before marketing and stuff like that
so there we could market matomo as
a good alternative also
and these countries that are heal labels
are labour green we can also have
the gdp are
as a some kind of our quality
seal
because matomo is open source and everything
else it's a good starting point for
having a while gdp are compliant tool
and discount with europe or canada while
for commercial organizations at least so canada
is half and half in this case
i regarded safe paddock states or the
countries of switzerland of norway of iceland
of argentina uruguay
new zealand south korea japan israel and
well some other countries as well like
the channel isles soda of these were
specific constituency that are and are not
part of great britain as well as
some
hm
other parts of black the faroe islands
up in the northern seat and they
have a specific situation regarding their legal
status so they are part of it
as well and the fun stuff actually
is since brexit great britain officially became
at least for three years
gdp are compliant again
but i would call this more like
a political dealing than real well real
act the legislation escaped by the channel
islands disconnected island of guernsey or the
isle of man and there are more
gp are compliant than the whole of
the uk this case
because they have a so-called adequacy decision
from the european commission so does this
some kind of knob
while you you apply for that to
some kind of application at this or
a multi step and a multi year
inspection of the loss and after practices
in the specific countries that are applying
for these adequacy decisions and for example
in june twenty two
the one south korea was admitted after
three years of being observed and while
applying for the status of an adequacy
decision dpr compliant whatever you want to
call it a country so these countries
a half loss and the effect that
are on the same level as the
gdp are in the european union so
in this case every company every citizen
every corporation every entity this country have
had has to have
well technical solutions tools software that is
in essence gdp are compliant so potomac
could look into these countries regarding getting
a foothold and
though in this case to differentiate it
more clearly from tools like google analytics
and stuff because you could at least
in this country still blue rods are
part of the european union the green
ones are safe in this case because
of this these countries you can argue
with legal consequences
when does use google analytics in these
countries and you don't do it right
you can get well suit or have
to pay a fine or whatever and
regarding the gdp are at fine can
go up to twenty million euros per
case or risk his scenario
four percent of europe
of your global revenue locked up sorry
global income
sole to gross income to be exact
africa sample and twenty nineteen
google was sentenced in france to pay
a fine of fifty million euros and
just this year amazon was in awe
thing was sweden spent somewhere into your
opinion did i have to look it
up where exactly but amazon had to
pay a fine of four sam of
seven
one hundred million years because every one
of these companies they were well violating
data protection
so and risk case scenario google is
fined and you have to pay a
fine as well because you are using
google you are using an illegal software
and at least regarding to germany
we have the
ref the local authorities as a set
or the data protection in germany as
part of us as a as a
matter for the states so not the
federal government is doing the data protection
but every state has a specific office
and the state's officials are meeting at
le
just once a year for so called
federal data protection meetings and at least
in september twenty twenty at the
conference data protection conference germany add as
set that
an american
specifically you asked american companies are not
legal in germany
day as explicitly mentioned are marks of
three sixty five and just under february
of this year the data protection authority
in the state of berlin set the
dead for example cisco webex was illegal
to discuss cisco webex was mentioned specifically
but up
among others like zoom as well this
caster stead of batman burton back or
witches in the south rest one after
richard's richest states in germany a day
well more or less outlawed zoom in
twenty twenty and march twenty twenty then
zoo
you did some paperwork and the outlawing
was a while was reversed and justice
while general warning label that every united
states company has in germany was applied
but in any case
the at is public authorities have a
very
very us put up are putting very
strict eye on every united states based
company on this case on every non
e u based company
kit so and regarding once again the
well disguised companies but also part they
are part of the general populace so
that should count that were as well
discuss french companies or ask so what
are the implications of the gdp are
according to what french data driven and
non data driven companies so in essence
to
light blue once aura regarding data driven
companies to dark blue rods are done
data driven companies so in general
i t digital internet based companies on
one hand and more or less traditional
companies on the other hand
and it and genoa of the traditional
companies seated deeper are more as a
constraint
were asked to a data driven company
soda more or less i t based
companies seated gdp are at while disguised
as a guideline to improve marketing strategies
as well as an opportunity for customer
relationship
some also see it as a constraint
but in this case a more data
room companies see de paris a general
good thing for while developing their marketing
strategies as well as to customer relationships
so they see it as an opportunity
so discus to make the best out
of the law in the best case
scenario even to make it as a
part of and use p
and discussed a unique selling point could
be we our gdp are complied we
value your privacy something that matomo already
does so nothing new for you guys
at least
but
something that also many companies seem so
discuss the public opinion at least in
well i t centric industries is more
pro gd pr than contract dpr because
the
sorry because dub
companies are already working with data they
are fluent in this field etc so
a company could best case scenario could
use the gdp are in gdp are
complied tools in this case as an
advantage in contrast to their to their
opposition to their job
to to to other parts of france
thread on that the rudder is right
now and one company that does it
is actually my my own company but
i come to that admitted that data
driven companies are for example these wants
some of dams you have heard some
may be
not a trello maybe heard of them
they are part of at lesean now
so de australia based and others like
monday dot com black dropbox asana ever
know there are u s based at
the ones on the bottom mind meister
meister task a down austrian based company
so they are
on the standard settings gdp are friendly
because they they must be they have
to be it's law
so for example these are some but
when you look at other companies that
are mostly and well communications sector
some of them are very very good
to regarding gdp our compliance for example
when you look at messages like a
signal like three ma also open source
stuff like gizzi all right now we're
the big blue button these are okay
but some have a bit of a
dwell
mixed image this case when you look
at zoom they are bakery owner of
the pandemic you have to admit that
at least i and many many that
are using zoom they think well it's
such a great service it's relined it's
blah blah blah
where as zoom is actually a very
data hungry service also a very dirty
service as well and there's a website
called a website carbon dot com where
you can put in domains and they
will well recount how much c o
two how much
gram c o two
does it cost in wealth energy in
and energy production or when you want
to look up that site and for
example i once tested that one was
with my old site we came round
out zero point six nine gram per
website use rare zoom has around eight
or nine gram
so tenfold
and stuff so in this case reddit
used an external service disc has wins
u s based also and you have
to have to take into account the
environmental friendliness so how
don't have to read where no sorry
but while how good for the environment
how reliable how
three how sustainable as how sustainable is
the service as well this is one
thing that comes more into effect right
now for example when you look at
a fragile future and other movements
so in this case a potomac can
make points as well regarding where you
can install the trouble on your own
servers so you can decide how environmental
friendly it will become but also how
regional service will be you don't have
to communicate all the time with united
states
for other countries to add a service
art so you can decide this case
also another thing that deserves on the
right bottom that's cisco webex or the
old logo of cisco webex and for
example cisco has a seal mate
that at least was a one time
i didn't seminar for a federal agency
and are also warned about the tomoe
air guitar and what about cisco it's
tough cisco webex had stuff that were
tomita was all right and fine but
rabbits i want about them because while
they aren't us based
but then the federal agency told me
no no no but it's our ride
we haven't had this case we have
a weather seal made by the german
bullous emphysema jihad indeed matsuda technic orchards
editor a federal agency for safety endurable
digital infrastructure
baxter while the bad point is
that this seal i looked up at
they have this seal
but while it's not something that the
federal agency itself makes but you more
or less can ask your tax advisor
to
give it to you because there are
well they are the make and all
that at at your company and they
say wrong everything seems fine and i
will get my payment so many many
marketing jargon going on here but that
could be something as well all this
company has
have a sometimes very flimsy
excuses were the tape but we our
gdp are complied we are safe re
looking out after human riots and stuff
like that and here's our seal of
approval for from the federal government and
stuff like that so something that you
could acquire very easily with matomo as
well so to put yourself on
at least the same level of trust
that these companies said that day half
off say that there are
okay and other companies as well regarding
data driven us up and look at
marks of three fixed or three sixty
five or google workspace they are in
general lot gdp are complied but we'll
look at other companies like nextcloud data
as a german best company and will
cloud service
i guess some of you may have
heard of it or an old cloud
that was not as why was a
part of flex cloudless as a with
all sorts of was the scotus essentially
fork of owncloud lag with open office
and a libra library office
i'll offer another company the r seminar
that is my own fulfilling glory
we are working with them apia at
with some apia from nextcloud we are
also working with a big blue button
for our video-conferencing and at least we
ourselves are marketing
the use of open source products we
also use metabo forest statistics and we
market that as well we are using
for example an app called tomorrow that
is essentially green and a sustainable banking
this case and we position ourselves with
debt so when we
for example are looking at our campus
or campus
a disaster or some kind of an
office cloud-like with microsoft through sixty five
a recent german that you can rock
their collaboratively and also secure in the
cloud because we're using the open source
solution we're in we're based in germany
and stuff like that
also with a talk blast that was
actually his big blue button but while
remarketed in another rape
also are with other products we often
discuss our media library and everything disc
as we are say it's well regional
based so the service on germany company
is germany we are sustainable because we
look that we only have to
energy sources route one case original but
also er we only use well equal
energy for this is one big big
pink stone and that our partners our
tea parties or infrastructure partners have to
make that they can guarantee and also
then that they can proof that they
use the data centers at that their
power the data centers only with sustainable
energy also regarding security because we are
based in gdp our country auto with
the data protection as well as d'etre
half while the regarded as that we
have some dean or e s o
lord stir i s o twenty seven
thousand and one
as for example one regarding data security
data privacy in this case stuff like
that for a while discuss one specific
company with the our seminar we even
market more or less we market the
gdp are as a unique selling point
of our company
and we specifically target this case of
example lawyers or doctors or other germany
would urge would call it a boof
skybus tag or so
did most nearest translation would be as
you are secret keepers are based on
your job
when you're a lawyer you are forbidden
germany you are forbidden to use messengers
like or whatsapp or skype etc you
have to use secure messenger sp discourse
like a three ma all like signal
order messages like oh with elements which
are you
which i was using the utter metrics
standard stuff like that lars jeremy half
loudly at least legally i have to
use it as well
so
this could be a good entry point
point for potomac as well that you
can contact all that you can market
yourself for fucks up for companies offer
public authorities public authorities have to have
even more
the rules to follow regarding data protection
okay but what we take from here
is well remote work is more prevalent
the data for do a data privacy
are more apparent and wealth in fact
how do we approach the matter so
in this case we can do it
re guarding the gdp gbr compliance that
we put the gdp r s while
to
the biggest selling point for matomo also
that companies can check for themselves what
moto mo collects from data and also
that they render usta not on-premise but
do not variant of the talbot that
they have total control over their data
okay and with more or less a
good landing discuss sorry
and i'm at the end of my
talk and well if we have still
time therefore q and a please everyone
shoot at any case i thank you
very much and were staggered stay healthy
and
much success in every part of your
life okay but if there any and
a staff going on any questions please
okay i guess the data was silence
also no question from silva so i
guess through in this case
further questions in the torah
so i simply invite people to continue
the conversation there is some other question
related to christian topic comes up
thank you for your thought it was
very interesting
well thank you as well for having
me here alright so good luck everyone
and if there are any questions you
can contact me anytime just google my
name you can find me all right
so have a nice day everyone by
thank you