Yeah, okay, so thank you again for this opportunity to talk about Matomo.
I love Matomo.
I love free software in general.
And this talk is about hardening Matomo in terms of security.
And this is not really oriented to super-experienced users.
This is more oriented from curious persons and to beginners.
But there are some things that can be discussed together with experienced people.
And some I'm here from the Italian Linux Society that is an association in Italy, a volunteer
association talking about free software and open-source software.
And in Italy, it's very interesting this period because everything, everywhere is talking
about Google Analytics and Matomo.
And I will talk later on the reasons.
And I'm also an ET consultant for Wikimedia Switzerland and a volunteer sysadmin for the
Italian chapter, the Wikimedia Italian chapter.
And let's say something that I'm not an investor in Matomo.
I'm not someone who trains users about Matomo.
I'm just a volunteer spreading Matomo everywhere because I like this tool, I like the problem
it fixes, and I like the ownership, and I like its free software and open-source software.
And so I'm here from Italy because some months ago, the Italian Data Protection Authority
said this interesting news that Google Analytics is now banned in the whole nation.
And this is really interesting because it really means what they say that it's not something
related only to public websites.
It's like public administrations, like schools, or et cetera, it's about also private websites.
And in fact, the whole story was about that even the EP address is considered an personal
data.
And so if you have a website with Google Analytics and the user visits the website and you send
the EP of your visitors to Google Analytics because you have embedded this tool, it's
not a very good idea because Google is capable of enriching this data and connect the EP
to their logged-in user.
And so this is really a violation of the GDPR in Italy and also in other nations.
And I'm telling this because it's also something related to security because you know that
in the United States, the intelligence agencies and the government, if they want to investigate
on a user, they can access the data.
And if you are an European visitor and if you don't live in the United States, it does
not matter.
So this is why there are not enough safeguards at the moment.
And so a lot of people in Italy is talking about Google Analytics.
This is just to talk about something I have seen with my eyes in the last months.
Yeah, good job, Google Analytics.
And so let's talk about security.
There are two ways, one moment, in this period, everyone in Italy is avoiding to embed anything.
So they are also closing YouTube videos and they are adopting a lot of open source and
they are also migrating to LibreJS.
I don't know if you know the LibreJS project, but it's something that says that every single
JavaScript alliance on your website should be open and Libre software.
And so I'm not saying that everybody in the world should adopt the LibreJS, but I'm saying
that this is the moment to talk about this opportunity because it's very hot this period.
So OK, we like Matomo.
We deploy Matomo on our servers.
We deploy Matomo on our Raspberry PIs.
We deploy Matomo using Docker, using cheap hosting services, using, I don't know, we
host Matomo in a lot of ways.
And it's very hard for some people, also for beginners, but also for intermediate people
to understand that there are only two ways to make a system safe.
And the first way is the Kirchhoff principle that is really, really, really OK for open
source software because if you have an open source software, you have to think about it.
Everyone in the world knows how your system is designed and you have to keep your password
secret and only the password is the stuff that you can have to keep secret.
And so the other principle is have everything simple and stupid because if you don't understand
how you are applying security measures to your system, you will never be able to have
a well-designed environment and a safe environment.
So I just suggest these two principles, the Kirchhoff and the KISS principles.
Let's start saying that the easiest way to keep a system safe is to apply a lot of mitigation,
a lot of mitigation to reduce the attack surface.
Because when you have a big environment like a media wiki, like a WordPress, like a Matomo,
there are a lot of lines of source code that you have to trust.
And I'm not saying that I don't trust Matomo, I'm just saying that it's a very big project
and that shit happens.
And so maybe a contributor has done something wrong in the very early phases.
Maybe what I mean is that there are a lot of possibilities that one line in this number
of PHP lines or one line in this number of JavaScript lines, that there are a lot of
lines of source code, maybe there is a vulnerability.
And so it's not a matter of if, it's a matter of when this problem will be discovered.
And this is not related to Matomo, this is related to whatever project we can design
in our life.
An interesting part of Matomo is that the plugin directory involves maybe the majority
of the line of codes, maybe because Matomo is very well decentralized in terms of its
design.
So each component has its own plugin.
And I really like this fact.
And so the first thing that we can suggest to reduce the attack surface of your Matomo
is just a reply to this question.
So how many plugins have you in your installation?
And if you have your Matomo, you know that you can go to the system menu and to the plugins
and see the active plugins that maybe, this is not a recent screenshot, this is my platform
some days ago, but I think that there are a lot of plugins that maybe you are not using
it just from the screenshot.
Maybe, I don't know if I can highlight the DBStats plugin that allows to do reports for
super users.
So it's not something delivered to users, it's something for super users.
A lot of people, honestly, I don't use this plugin.
So I am not saying to disable this plugin, to disable a plugin, by the way, you can click
on the link on the left and to activate the other link.
But I'm saying, if you are not using the e-commerce plugin, the example API plugin, if you are,
because maybe you have just a blog, maybe you don't need this to see examples.
Every plugin you disable, you are reducing the surface attack of your platform.
And this is really, really good because whenever you want, you can enable these plugins again.
So it's not a problem of destroying your platform.
You can, whenever you want, enable it again.
And so also the marketplace, the marketplace is maybe a very big plugin and we have connections
to the web.
And so there are a lot of code that needs sanitization, that needs filters, et cetera.
And so I suggest when you install something from the marketplace, to disable the marketplace,
why not?
Also, maybe not all the people have an SMS gateway on their Matomo.
So I just suggest to disable the SMS gateway.
So I think this is just an overview of something that you can do.
This is a list of a lot of plugins that I have not in production and I may recommend
to verify that you use them as well.
And also, let's talk about maybe the two-factor authentication.
The two-factor authentication is really, I really like the way it was implemented.
And I recommend enabling it if you need it, but if you are not using it, feel free to
disable it because, by the way, you can always enable it in the future.
But it's not strange to listen to someone saying that the two-factor authentication
may be disabled in this kind of talk.
I mean, sometimes it's not a very, very, very good idea to enforce this kind of tools.
Using tools like multi-factor authentication in whatever tool may be counterproductive,
maybe problematic because maybe not all your users are trained to handle the two-factor
authentication side effects.
For example, they need to have a mobile phone and their mobile phone, they have an application
and their application must not be malware.
And so there are a lot of components that a two-factor authentication can worsen, a
lot of facts that can be not improved, can not improve.
And so, for example, what about a lot of social media managers that don't know anything about
advanced security measures?
And so maybe they just need to have very strong password and without risking to expose their
mobile phone to additional vulnerabilities.
So do your evaluations.
Maybe don't try to enforce the tool to every user in the world.
Just try to have rigid password politics, very strong password, et cetera, and, again,
do your evaluations.
By the way, if you want to try the best, I think that for me it's the best, the best
one-time password application that I use with my Matome installation, I think I have a very
old Matome installation, but I think that it still works.
Just contact me if it's not.
The free OTP is an application from FDroid.
You know, FDroid, it's a repository for Android smartphone that only contains free software,
and it's very, very, very verified.
It's open source, and this application is easy to use, and so I recommend this software.
And if you have a lot of users and if you're enforcing them to use free OTP, I recommend
in doing it only if they have an Android and if they have not customized a lot the phone,
if they have maybe disabled the Play Store or this kind of stuff.
So a lot of people ask, what if my Matome is compromised?
This is not a good question.
This is a very terrible question, but I can think a very simple way you can mitigate the
risk after your Matome was compromised is to enable this option to anonymize as much
as possible all the IP addresses of your users, because when you activate this option, you
know that Matome does not save this information in the database, and this is awesome.
Matome does not save this information, and so if your database is hacked, it does not
contain this information, and there is less data to be disclosed to the entire universe.
So this may seem stupid, but this is not stupid.
So we are here to understand when we are downloading Matome on our server, we want to understand
what should be exposed, what should be maybe writeable, what should be maybe hidden, and
so I recommend in don't trusting this talk, but just reading the amazing official documentation
of Matome.
I think that one hour in reading the Matome documentation can save your company, so please
read the documentation.
But well, in short, we know that when we download Matome, whatever version, we know to understand
each file, what should be its user, what should be its permissions, who should see this file,
who should execute this file.
This is a very important question for a system administrator.
But before talking about permissions, we need to understand how we are using Matome.
A lot of people are adopting Matome through this method, the PHP FPM method, and a lot
of people without knowing about it is adopting Matome with this component, the mode PHP mode.
So we have two methods, we have two very different methods to adopt Matome.
We have also Docker machines, obviously, but these are probably the most adopted situations.
I have done an interview about it, a survey, and they are very widely known.
A word about the PHP FPM method, how to understand that you are using this method.
You can see that you are using this method if when you do one request to your web server,
these ports that are not Matome, but something else, and your Matome is under another web
server running on your machine, but on a different port.
Probably if you have this situation, you are under the PHP FPM configuration.
Instead, if you have just a web server and nothing else, probably you are under this
configuration, the mode PHP.
The mode PHP version is an interesting and historically very, very widely adopted configuration
because it's very, very simple to install on your Linux server.
You just run IPT install, Apache, PHP, and everything works.
So we have a very big process under your Unix machine, under your Linux.
Usually the Unix user is www.data.
This is the name of the Unix user because you know that in Linux, every system has its
own user dedicated to the system.
So you have a web server daemon with its user, you have a mail server daemon with its user,
and this is how it works.
You have one Unix user running the whole web server, listening on a port, maybe this port
or maybe the HTTP port, I don't know, but there is a very big process handling whatever
website you have in your single server.
So maybe you have one, two, three applications, two domains, server by the same server, and
only one Unix user handling every request.
And this is not optimal for most situations because if you have an application, then Matomo,
WordPress, over the same process, over the same Unix user, what if maybe this application
is compromised?
This is problematic because maybe this problematic application can go in the parent directory
and go up and inspect all the applications and so can expand and write other stuff in
other places.
And so it's not usually a good idea.
There are a lot of very cheap hosting services offering this as default, and users usually
don't know about it.
A lot of users adopting this system do this together with this directive.
What is this?
They open-paste this directive.
If you have PHP running on a domain server, you can say, okay, if you visit example.org,
you can only visit this place.
If you visit example.net, you can only visit this place.
And the process cannot go in the other places.
And this is possible thanks to this directive that can be set in PHP on each virtual host.
But the problem is that this directive is that if you use it, for example, if you declare,
okay, I declare open-based here is bar, home, Matomo, a place on your system, then you have
another web server, another virtual host, and you say another value.
So you can set a different value for each virtual host to try to isolate the process.
The problem is that PHP is isolating the process.
And in fact, this is an Apache configuration.
This is a very frequent configuration.
So you have a server name, and so all the people from this domain go to this place.
And then you say, you declare this directive to isolate the process, and so you know that
you cannot go out of this place.
And this is not really, really safe, because if you read the documentation, it's very,
very clear that open-based here, it's not a security measure.
It's an extra safety.
I don't know what an extra safety is, but the universe is adopting this as a security
measure, and they should stop.
So if you see a configuration like that, stop adopting this, because it's not really safe.
And so let's talk about the PHP, the FPM method.
This is a very, very frequent alternative to the mod PHP, so this is the old configuration.
This is the new configuration.
I invented to have isolated processes that work alongside a front-end web server.
So you really have a front-end web server serving maybe static files, and then you have
an underlying web server serving dynamic files with its own Unix user, and so it can be isolated,
and it runs on its dedicated port.
So it's completely separated.
Now, you can say, okay, I have a Docker.
My configuration is different, but it's not so different, because if you have Docker,
so with Docker, you have a front-end web server that usually is Nginx or Apache.
And then you have your Docker running on the random port, but what I'm saying is that usually
Docker is not in this position.
Usually Docker is not exposed to handle every request for HTTPS and every request for HTTP.
So you have a front-end web server also because it simplifies let's encrypt renewal, I don't
know, or it allows you to have a lot of websites in your server and mix it by the Apache web
server.
What I'm saying is that this is a very frequent situation, and how to secure this situation.
Let's talk about how it works.
So you have a front-end web server.
You do a request, and your front-end web server handles it.
What is your front-end web server?
We saved it.
It's Apache or Nginx.
It doesn't matter.
One or the other.
That's not better in this discourse.
What I'm saying, if you visit example.org, maybe example.org, your request goes directly
to the correct PHP, FPM web server.
Maybe if you want, so if you want Amatomo, you visit this back-end web server and the
reply goes to the user, and if you want your blog, maybe you have a blog, your request
goes to the other web server.
So every site has its dedicated port, and the user usually doesn't connect directly
to this port.
This is the situation.
Every application, of course, has its dedicated file system path name, and the interesting
part is that we are not in a situation where we have a big user with access to all these
file systems, but instead we have a dedicated user with access to that specific file system
place.
So we have another user with access to the other file system place, et cetera, et cetera.
And this allows a lot of isolation.
If you know how to do it.
And that's also, you still have a Unix user, and you still need to know that the user probably
needed to access this file system, but just for static files, for example, and then you
have another Unix user that must have access to this file system for the dynamic files.
So PHP files are executed by this user, and static file are provided by the www data user.
So this is how it works.
And this is a basic example on how to implement everything on your web server.
Maybe you have the front-end web server Apache configured in this way to say that there is
a document root somewhere.
And then I have not put it there, but you can imagine that in the next slides, we have
the proxy, proxying all the requests on the underlying web server.
And this is the most important part of our talk, how to have a PHP FPM safe, secure,
and hardened.
First of all, you have to create a dedicated user for your purpose, and be sure that only
that user can access critical places in that file system of your application.
So you can declare a PHP directive to say that the uploaded files must be in place,
and that only this user can be assigned to this place to access the temporary resources,
or I don't know.
But if you additionally want to set other strange directive to harden even more, why
not?
This is a good strategy to use open base there in a right way.
So using to give something more, so to have everything under a cage, an additional cage,
but this is not the only cage of your system.
This is the cage of your system, a dedicated user, and a dedicated file system path name
with correct permissions.
So for example, on your file system, you have your Matomo installed in this position, deployed
in this position, and you have the temporary directive that is this one.
And its permissions are its user, it's the one in your FPM web server, and its group,
it's the one assigned to the same process, and look about this permission field.
If you know how to read this field, it means that let's clear everything.
What I'm highlighting here is that this Apache Matomo is the user who can read, write, and
execute this in this file.
So execute in a directory context means that you can access this file.
And the user group as well can do the same things, but all the others cannot.
So you have hardened your installation, removing privileges on critical path names.
This is very, very important.
And so again, use your configuration to dedicate a user and have a path name and declare your
configurations in order to instruct the process to use your custom path names instead of just
TMP, that it's global.
And so this is simple but effective.
So if you are curious about how to put everything in a very, very robust cage, I suggest to
just assign everything to the root user and to the root group.
This is not scaring.
Sometimes we hear, oh my god, the root user should not execute this file.
Don't be confused.
If a file is owned by the root user, it means that only the root user can read, write, and
execute.
So if this file is owned by the root group, so you know the user group, it means that
only the group can read this file.
And all the others, well, all the others for this markdown file can read this file.
Why not?
But cannot write in any way.
Also an interesting part, take for example, the Matomo.js, the Matomo.js file needs write
access.
So you can assign it to the dedicated user and to the dedicated group and saying that
the dedicated user can read and write, but every other user in your system cannot touch
that file.
And this is very important.
This file is not secret.
There is no need to remove the read access, the last read access.
So it's evaluate, always evaluate the last column that it's the most important one declaring
what other users in your system can do with this file.
And so for example, I have removed the, you see that the temporary directive has nothing
in the, I have not highlighted it correctly, but has nothing in the last permissions.
So the temp directory can only be wrote by the Apache user and to the Apache group.
So this is what I'm saying, evaluate your application, understand what need read access.
So probably everything need read access, you know, what need write access.
So for this file, you assign the dedicated user.
What needed to be hided to everybody but your users.
And so you do the same, but without the other field, without allowing other users to read,
write, and execute.
Okay.
I don't know what I'm showing here.
What I want to say is that this is not easy.
This is not easy.
You have to read the documentation, you have to understand that the config directory may
be public, but the files inside the config directory have to be private.
So inspect your application, read the official documentation, be, use the change modality
for the files and use the change owner for the files wisely.
So this is really how your application can be hardened in a great way.
Because the nice part about having some files on it by root is that it's like whatever other
service in your Linux system is designed, try to access other parts of your system.
If any other process, for example, if you install, I don't know, I really don't know,
Apache, for example, Apache, every file, the system file of Apache is owned by root.
And only the system, the super administrator can edit this file.
And this is the same for your Matomo installation.
So you should have a script to harden your installation when you want is freezed.
So you want is like in a not upgradable state and a script allowing to put everything under
the user of your web server to be able to upgrade your system.
So you should have two configurations, two scripts and one for everyday usage for production.
So you run the script and set your permissions in this way.
And another script that put your permissions like in whatever cheap hosting environment.
And so with every file assigned to the web server users.
But this is problematic because having every file under the same user means that if there
is a security issue in your application, this user can write in every file of your environment.
And this is not the desired situation.
So it can be a stupid, but trust me, if take care about your applications, Matomo included,
WordPress included, and if you want to have everything in a good state, I recommend having
a kind of hardened production configuration and upgrade the configuration.
So I'm ready for talking about other stuff, but I just recommend subscribing to CVE newsletters
because it's very important to be the first in the universe when something really bad
happens in the code base.
Maybe there is a problem affecting people without authentication and it does not require
many complexity to trigger the issue.
So I recommend to subscribe to CVE newsletters.
I say this because a lot of people don't do this and this is definitely a problem.
Another stupid tip is keep your platform up to date, but if you have the possibility,
use the LTS version of Matomo so you have not to update your software for whatever new
feature is introduced.
Maybe because you don't have time to test everything, but you want an environment in
a safe state where only security patches are applied regularly.
And please keep your users trained.
So it's not important to enforce two-factor authentication on your whole organic base
because if you don't know how to use it, you will just make bigger mistakes.
So train your users.
And please keep your devices without malware because the majority of the vulnerabilities
nowadays don't come from Matomo itself.
The majority of vulnerabilities come from you.
So you are you, the person who has maybe security issues on your mobile phone or security issues
on your Wi-Fi area, security issues on your laptop.
Maybe you installed a video game from a random website and now your computer is totally compromised.
So I'm not saying that it's really, really huge, useful to have a very, very hard-ended
installation if the administrators have not devices with a controlled state.
So try to use as much as possible open-source software.
If you have Android user systems, buy an Android dedicated for work, remove the Play Store,
remove everything, install Android, remove whatever proprietary app.
And then you can be safe to use stuff like the OTP applications.
And so use as much possible free software.
I really have to say, please don't think that you will be not owned because this is the
most problematic assumption.
So please assume that you will be owned in the future and invest in reading documentation.
Invest in exploring your tool.
Invest in trying to hack your system, try to use not-privileged users.
Try to create another Unix user on your system with low privileges and then try to do a privilege
escalation trying to inspect your web servers and your applications.
So these are just bad words to remember to try to be the one that can enter in your system
before someone else do this for you.
This is not good.
So thank you so much.
My presentation is under the Creative Commons attribution.
Share your like.
You can share it for whenever you want and for whatever purpose.
You can sell it.
You can do whatever you want.
Just please put a credit to at least my nickname.
So saying that this presentation is by Valerio.
Thank you so much for everything.
Can I thank again the Matomo organizers because MatomoCamp is realized with 100% open-source
software and deeper software.
And this is really amazing because, again, Matomo is open-source, MatomoCamp is open-source,
and this is really a really, really, really good way to engage technical communities that
care about the privacy and care about software freedom.
So thank you again.
Whatever question can be delivered to the Matrix chat, and I hope that we had a good
time together.
Valerio, thank you very much for your insightful talk.
And you highlighted a lot of important things to consider.
And this is also one of my favorite topics because it is mostly treated very poorly.
And even it is a topic which is neglected in many companies.
And also, you compressed the topic very well.
You talked about many, many details.
And also, there is so much more, but I think you mentioned very important things.
Perhaps we have some questions here that, if not right now, there are some questions
from my side also because you are a security expert.
So perhaps you can recommend the audience something like, is there something like automated
security audits?
Is there a software for that to check the software automatically for CVEs or something
like that?
Okay.
Honestly, I know the part related to WordPress more than the part related to Matomo.
There are a lot of tools.
I think you can search and there are a lot of tools.
I actually cannot recommend any of them because I recommend in being proactive and keeping
the platform up to date as soon as possible and without receiving any of these emails
or notifications.
And this is probably the best way to keep your system up to date.
Because usually, normal users, when they receive this kind of notification, it's too late because
maybe you are in Italy or you are from, I don't know, and we are decentralized against
the Matomo developers who can quickly handle the situation and release a security patch
and offer you an update quickly on your platform.
So I recommend you just update your platform and please feel free to share some automated
tools to inspect maybe not updated platform and this kind of stuff.
Thank you for the question.
I'm very curious and thank you for sharing to me if somebody knows.
Of course.
And as a quick comment on that, it's also for the audience a very important thing.
As soon as an update is out, we mark it if it has a security concern, we mark it with
a minor, major or critical attack.
So you know how important it is to make this update.
That's wonderful.
And are there more questions?
Because I'm really curious.
Do we have other questions right now?
Okay.
If not right now, then the chat will stay open and perhaps Valerio has some minutes
left to answer more questions if there are any.
But thank you very much for that very, very important topic.
And also this talk will be online as a video on the video platform.
And yeah, Valerio, thank you again a lot and greetings to Italy.
Thank you so much.
And again, go Matomo, go, thank you for doing that.
Thank you.
Goodbye.
Bye bye.
Ciao, pane pizza Matomo.
Ciao.