Hi, everyone. Glad to be here to talk about the topic for today, which is imagine an ideal
Matomo. So just before I start, I just want to say a few words about the context of this
presentation. Typically here, what I'm going to be talking about is providing a better experience
to marketing people, non-technical people, because a lot of what I'm going to be talking about can
be addressed using what I call some more technical strategies or resources. This is just my few ideas
and I really like that at the end of the presentation you can share your ideas also so we can build some
kind of list of our expectations regarding the tool in the future. So what we're going to be talking
about is Matomo itself, the Tag Manager, DataVis tool and Consent Management Platform. So let's dive
in directly. First of all, when we're talking about Matomo, there is something really annoying
that I have encountered many times is when you have a lot of websites and you want to find a
specific one. In this situation, you have to use the site's search field, but this site's search
field is located at the bottom of the page. So in my dreams, I would like to have the search site
panel right above so you can just type the name of the website and it's going to be right in front
of your house. This is the first thing, place search fields above. The second one is a bit more
annoying, I think, because when you're doing web analytics, you're talking about digital performance
and you're talking about metrics. And in some cases, those metrics are talking about specific
segments of audience. And unfortunately, for the moment, when you build your dashboard, you are
forced to segment your whole dashboard. You cannot segment just a metric within your dashboard. And
here, again, is some kind of footage that I made with my metric and the ability to have here the
segment directly based on this particular metric. Because otherwise, what we have to do is to take
the data out of Matomo and bring it to an external data visualization tool. It can be done, but for
some users, for some teams, I have encountered the situation where they just want to remain within
Matomo and not go outside of it. So this one is, I think, a really interesting one, because the
whole idea behind presentation is to have some kind of complete web analytics suite. And this
feature, I think, is quite valuable. Another example of stuff that are annoying in the
projects is the situation where you want to follow users cross-domain. So for instance, you have a
client who says, OK, I have three, four, five websites, and I want to see what people do on
these different websites. Is there some cross user journey through these websites? And for that,
you create a Matomo site ID, and you configure it so that the journeys are captured through the
different domains. But unfortunately, in this situation, and this is the example that I display
here, you just have in the report page URL. In fact, you just have the URI. I think you don't
have the domain, and it's quite annoying because you don't know what you're talking about. So this
is the reason why I just added here in my dreams what it would look like. So for instance, here,
mysitea.com, slash FRFR, mysiteb.com, slash, et cetera, et cetera. Again, you can do some work
around with the Tag Manager, for instance. But again, the idea of the presentation is I am not
a technical person, and I encounter this situation that made me unhappy and thinking that Matomo is
not that interesting as a tool. Situation number three is when you look at the events reports,
most of the time you have people that are used to using Google Analytics reports. And it's quite
surprising for them not to see the whole variables, the whole event variables. So you have event
category, event action, but where is my event action? And again, the way I present it here is
when you want to separate the variables, but by default it's not presented that way. So it's,
again, more annoying for most people. So the idea here is that we could have event category,
event action, event names, and of course, event value. So I don't think it's a big deal, but yes,
you have to navigate through the different event variables, and that can be a bit disappointing.
In the same logic, when we're navigating through the different event variables,
and you're using, for instance, a search field. So here, for instance, I typed conversion here,
and I am on the event category level. I have my conversion, so it's filtered the way I want it.
But if I want to go down to the event action level, then my conversion, what I had typed here,
is lost. So again, it would be great if I could keep what I have typed here in the browser,
and also if the search filter could be located right above here, because if you have hundreds
of lines, then you have to scroll down all the way, and it's not hiding.
Another really annoying situation when I'm talking with my clients is why is that not
possible to combine more than three dimensions in custom reports? What do I do when I want to
have event category, event action, event name, and another custom dimension? And again,
for just regular marketing people, it's some kind of situation where they want to reject the tool,
because they think that it's not normal that you cannot, by default, and simply combine more than
three dimension. And again, they always make the comparison with Google Analytics. And since now,
it's obvious that we will have a lot of people migrating from GA to Matomo. I think that we
should address this specific topic. In the same field, talking about the custom reports,
I was a bit surprised to see that not all metrics are available in the custom reports. So for
instance, I had clients wanting the average time on page in a custom report, and I discovered that
this metric is not available on the custom reports. So I think that at least there should be somewhere
where it is explained that this metric or this dimension will not be available by default so that
people can be prepared so that we can explain. And it's really disappointing because you have
something in mind, you're quite sure of what you're going to be doing, and you discover that
unfortunately, it's not possible. So what I suggest is that all metrics available in Matomo
should be available in custom reports. Another situation, and it's regarding the moments where
you have dozens of websites to configure. And the example that I have in mind is the custom
dimension. Yes, if you have maybe 20, 30 custom dimensions to configure for 20, 30 websites,
it can take a lot of time. And if you do that manually, then you can make mistakes. So I again
assume that it can be done using maybe different APIs or technical stuff. But for regular marketing
people, I think it could be a good thing to have some kind of copy configuration button in the
admin section. And in my mind, then you can decide that yes, I want to copy a custom dimensions.
For the customers also, you can decide that you want to duplicate them. For the segments,
it's a bit different because when you create them, you can decide that it's for one website
or all of them. But yes, the idea here is to not lose time in the configuration. And I'm reading
in the conversation, Thomas. Yes, regarding the other side, I've made a change request. Yes,
I think that obviously we should be a lot more indeed to ask these kind of changes. Because if
we are allowed to ask that, then it be prioritized, of course. Thank you, Thomas, for coming. Another
thing is about API testing. And again, this is in my ideal world, because I know that it's something
that may take a lot of time, resource tests and so on. But if we want to have a complete analytics
suite, then I think that we should have a with you. We get each other for any tests. That's what
Google did with the feature that was in the beginning in GA for the test. And then they
launched optimize. So again, you can use the testing feature in that is, I think, quite well
made when we are talking about building the tests. But when it's about, again, you are someone with
not a lot of resources and not able to build pages and have to ask for developers to build
pages to run your tests, it's a bit disappointing. And it would be a great advantage if we could have
everything in a box. And the editor, I think, is also something that might be really valuable for
the two as a global analytics suite. Something again, quite annoying is about the unique visitor
metric. It appears that by default, this metric is not available for custom periods in the reports.
It is documented. But you have to have a look in the documentation. Because what happens is that,
for instance, here I have this metric in a Google Data Studio. And at the first site, I'm thinking,
oh, something went wrong with my dashboard. Something is not working. And in fact, it's just
that unique visitors is not activated for custom dates and custom periods. So again, you have to
ask the people that handle the Matomo instance to make a change in some kind of technical file.
And then it's activated. And apparently, it's not activated by default because it costs a lot in
terms of resources on the servers. I'm not quite aware of that because, again, I'm not a technical
person. But this is something not acceptable for most people, for most marketing people. The unique
visitor metric is some kind of basic metric. And when you encounter the situation firstly,
and you explain to the customer that, oh, yes, in fact, the metric is not available by default,
they just don't get it. They just don't understand why can it be, how can it be possible that this
simple standard metric is not by default available on that tool. And this is the situation I
encountered a lot where people rejected it because they thought that, no, this is not possible. It's
not acceptable that this simple metric we cannot access simply. And we have to ask our IT department
to do some kind of stuff, or we have to ask the Matomo team to do something on the server so that
we can have a metric. So it's just a proposition. Yes, yes, yes, of course. Yes, in the config level,
but IMEI.php, clearly, it's something that can be done. But this is annoying when you have, let's
say, organizations where you have thousands, no, hundreds of people using a tool named Google
Analytics, and they migrate, and they are quite forced to migrate to another tool. And
they discover that this metric, this simple thing, you have to ask your IT department to do something
to access it. And yes, I think that there should be a simple button somewhere in the UI, in the
Matomo UI, saying, do you want the unique visitor? Or just a warning saying, OK, by default, it's not
activated, but you can choose to activate it. Again, it's a presentation that's really
orientated for non-technical people. And yes, this is something I encountered a lot of times.
And now I can warn my clients about that. But in the beginning, when it happened, it was a bit
disturbing. And thank you again, Thomas, for the comments about that.
Another thing that I think could be interesting is that—I'm sorry, I'm reading Thomas' comment,
but I think the stuff could be a little bit strange. OK, let's go on. OK, the other thing
is about generic segments, because by default, you don't have anything like that in the interface.
So I think that you should have, by default, some kind of generic segments that you have within
Google Analytics. So again, it's a marketing guy talking. Some tools like Adobe Analytics or other
don't even have those generic segments available. But again, for people that are used to something
and that are moving to a new tool, not having the basics is something that is a bit annoying.
So I think that at least there could be some kind of generic ones like the direct accesses,
new users, stuff like that. Another stuff that existed in Google Analytics and that people
don't find in Matomo and about what they're a bit disappointed is the value page metric.
This metric is interesting because it was a simple way to identify
what pages were contributing to performance to conversions. And I think it could be interesting
to have this data within Matomo. I'm reading the comments. Sorry for joking a bit.
It's a very complex tool and you just read that we can adopt it for different needs. However,
you should know these details. Of course, configure it with the setting above
enable as an example. Yes, I totally agree. It was the situation that I encountered in
the beginning when I started working with the tool. But yes, it's something that I know now.
But for people that are going to be using the tool in the future since there are going to be a lot of
adoption of the tool because of the legal situation in different countries, I think that
at least the tool should warn users that they have to do something about that. Because not anyone
has the immediate knowledge about this specific topic, the unique visitor topic.
The tag manager. Another thing that could be done is just to allow us to sort the different assets
by name types because here you have really few things, few tags. But when you have really big
containers, I think that if you could sort by name, by type, or even have a search field
somewhere could be a good thing as well. In the tag manager area, again, something
that I think could be interesting is just to have a way to duplicate, copy, paste some sets
because right now you can just edit or delete the assets. Something else that already exists in
Google Tag Manager is the folder feature. So maybe could be also a good thing to be able to have a
clean vision of what's inside your container. A way also to post tags, something you have quite
easily in Google Tag Manager that you don't have in Matomo. Of course, you can decide that you
put some kind of starting day and ending day of the tag file for a campaign, for instance. But
this is quite easy to use here to just post the tag. Number three is about data visualization.
Again, I'm talking only for me. I don't know an open source Google Data Studio alternative.
I think that there are some, so for instance, here, I think it's Grafana, and I think that there's a
talk soon about Apache superset. But again, you have to go outside of Matomo. So I think that if
we can have something that allows us to stay within Matomo, could be a good thing. If we can
do that, could be a good thing. Or another option is to enhance the existing dashboard
system and maybe make other connections possible because with the existing dashboard, you cannot
connect external data sources. So yes, just as the A-B testing feature, I think that it's a big
work to do, but to have something complete, I think it's important to have a complete data
visualization solution within Matomo. The last thing I wanted to talk about regarding my ideal
vision, it's not exhaustive, but just a few ideas I had in mind, is about the consent management
platform. So again, if you have the technical resources for that, you can address
this topic. But I think if we had something internal inside of Matomo that can allow us
to create the cookie consent banner and configure it easily, it would help to adopt the tool.
So there is a comment here, page metric about goal conversion is a new feature since two months.
Goal conversion. Thank you Udo for your comment.
Yes, and now it's your turn. Do you have any ideas about what could make Matomo even a better tool?
Just feel free and we'll take note of that and add it to the presentation. So
if you want to add something, just don't hesitate.
Regarding consent management, I would like that it would be nice
if it can be possible to process content to geo location with a full IP address.
Thank you Udo for your comment. Small improvements to the current dashboard solution
would help a lot. Building a completely new dashboard solution is a big test. Yes, totally agree.
Again, I'm just dreaming awake, but it's the name of the presentation. It's ideal. Imagine an ideal Matomo.
Michael Johnson is saying, would also like to have faster responses, but it is surely a technical thing.
Faster, also like to have faster. Yes, I think they were talking about
server responses on your Matomo UI. Typically, you can be helped by your IT team, and you can also
ask some people. In particular, I'm thinking about Peter, with whom I have already been working.
His work brought a lot of improvement to the time response. Peter is definitely
someone you can reach out to when you want to address these technical issues that can cause low response.
Udo is saying, I totally agree. Marketing clients in particular see like you that some of your
improvements would help a lot. Thank you for your comments. I think that it's also a matter of
internal communication within the tool, just to, again, like for the unique business stuff, just
some kind of pop-up saying, okay, for the moment, you don't have access to that metric, but if you want
to have it, because it's a must-have, then you just have to go to the config in the PHP and make that
change. I think it's like when there's a conversation between people, it's a matter of
anticipate what can happen and communicate in a clear way. Yes, thank you again, Udo, for your
comment. Thank you, Thomas, for your comment also. Indeed, it's like in most cases, there are some
limitations in the architecture for some features as well. Yes, of course, and just like Thomas said,
yes, it is a very complex tool, and I know that in my position, I don't have an overall vision of
all the involvements to make the tool work, but I had this discussion with Mathieu some weeks ago,
months ago. There are at least, I think, three audiences for the tool. You have end users for
marketing people in an organization that are going to be looking at their campaign performance, for
instance. You have IT people that are going to be installing and managing the infrastructure,
and you have consultants like me, people like me, and these are really three different types of
audiences with different expectations. When we're talking about Matomo consultants, and I take my
example, I am a Matomo consultant, but with not that technical orientation, I'm more a digital
efficiency strategist, so I think it's really important to have communications, distinct
communication for these three different types of audiences. And Udo is asking, Thomas, what are your
thoughts on the technical limitations, not specifically on the technical limitations,
but not specifically on the technical limitations?
Yes, but regarding the limitations, I have to admit that I'm not that aware of all the limitations,
and I think that there is a page on the documentation that explains all the
all the documentations, and my final thought about that is that the tool needs improvement,
yes, it's clear, but I think that communication around the tool needs improvement as well,
because I'm going to give a last example about that. The example I want to give is the
Tag Manager implementation of the e-commerce tracking, and I have to admit that I struggled
a bit with the official documentation, and the solution with that came from Ronan Hélot,
who wrote an article on his blog, and that definitely changed my life to enable the tracking
of the e-commerce with the Tag Manager. So yes, I think that improvement around the tool can
is necessary, and improvement around communication documentation is also necessary, because
today, customers are used to have a Tag Manager, because they can handle their campaigns
more easily, and they expect the tracking to be done with the Tag Manager, and I see that
and I see that these different situations of, okay, am I going to use the regular JavaScript
tracker, or am I going to use the Tag Manager, or am I going to use an SDK for an application,
but you don't have some kind of detailed approach, or maybe I haven't seen it, but yes. Finally,
what I think is that the communication around the tool can be improved also.
Improved also. The limitations are mostly about not a mobile user. In relation to database, this
works for small sites, but when data grows, the query gets heavier from a tech perspective.
In some cases, then the need for super skilled DBA skills is needed.
Okay, so thanks a lot for your comments, your suggestions. I'm really glad that we had this
discussion all together. I think that we are going to end the talk. Just like I said, I'm going to ask
some of the propositions you suggested in the chat, and thanks for your attention,
and we talk soon. See you very soon, I hope. Bye.