All right, hello, and welcome, everyone, for our next presentation.
This will be given by our speaker, Michael Weber.
Michael Weber has been working in online marketing and analytics for over 20 years, and he's
the founder of Search VIU, which is a provider of data solutions, especially for SEO purposes.
And he has developed a Matomo Google Data Studio Connector.
Today, he will talk about looking at external data visualization solutions and how and,
if yes, they can be integrated with Matomo.
So, without further ado, I am looking forward to your presentation, Michael, and please
begin.
Thank you, Clemens.
Thank you for the introduction.
It is a pleasure to be here today and to talk about external data dashboards and data visualization.
So, yes, let's start with a little about me.
You have said all already, yes, I'm in online marketing, web analytics since 2001, worked
in agencies and in-house, yes, don't want to talk a long, long time about just one thing.
We have developed a Matomo Google Looker Studio Connector, just could be that in the presentation
I talk about Google Data Studio, Google has renamed it before some time, and yes, that's
about that.
What I will talk about today, a short look on why we do, why external data visualization
could be important, and a short look on what solutions are out there, it's just a short
look, we don't dig into the several things there.
And then we take a look on the data transfer options.
So what's linked with that is how we get the Matomo data into any sort of visualization
solution out there, and we dig a little bit deeper in how that works, how we work with
data, what we need to consider when we do that, and at the end, I think it's enough
time to answer some questions.
Yes, so why should you or should anybody use external data visualizations?
Matomo has pretty powerful dashboards, and for that, there are many widgets out there,
but yeah, it's a little bit limited in the visualization of the data.
The widgets are not as good in time series visualization of some data and other things.
That's one thing, the visualization of the data is important for several audiences.
If you want to build a management KPI dashboard, in addition for some other people in the business,
some other stakeholders in the business, in your company, it makes sense to build own
dashboards for them, filter it already down so the people don't have to click through
Matomo and find their reports and so on.
One other thing is that in the most visualization solutions out there, it's possible to connect
data at other data sources, so you could add, as an example, if you want to make a report
for the SCA BPC team, you can add data directly and other data from Matomo in one dashboard.
Also Matomo has some integrations, it's not as powerful as some other tool out there.
So yes, just a short look at our audience.
Is anybody of you using already an external visualization solution from Matomo data already?
I have created a poll in the chat if you want to answer, it would be great.
So give you two seconds to go into that.
As far as I can see, at the moment, the most people who have entered the poll haven't used
it already.
So yes, we will take a look.
What are data visualization solutions or what visualization solutions out there on the market?
Matomo is Lukas Studio or Google Data Studio, I think it's pretty known out there.
But there are other great solutions like Tableau, Power BI, CSEN, SOA Analytics, all the open
source solutions from Apache, SuperSet, but there are a wide range of other solutions.
So yes, it's something where data can be visualized.
Lukas Studio is for free and it's also a free host, SuperSet is also a free open source
tool, but you need some hosting there, and other tools are in the SOA Analytics is also
open source, as far as I know, the other solutions are paid versions with a different range to
you need to pay.
And yes, see some more people have voted in the poll.
And we have some people here who already have done data visualizations, that's great.
So perhaps they can add some information at the end.
So now, if we have a data visualization solution, we need the data from Matomo to get in that
visualization.
There are several options to transfer the data.
The one is the API, which Matomo provides, the other is to have access to the SQL database.
The most visualization tools have the possibility to add a SQL data source.
And one other solution is data transfer, so you export data from Matomo into an external
analytic database, as example, to analyze with them.
If we take a look on the API option, some benefits are that the data is up to date,
you just talk to Matomo with the API, it's mostly the easiest way to get access to the
data and you have no extra cost or maintenance of additional database or something like this.
The cons are that the connector, that there must be a connector to Matomo available in
the visualization solution, or you need to develop one, or it must be a workaround there,
we take a look at this later.
It could be slow, like other solutions, if you want to access wide range of data, also
we take a look at that.
And the API, that's something that needs to be mentioned.
Much people have worked with Google Analytics before, and perhaps they know the Data Studio
Connector from Google Analytics, and the Matomo API is not as flexible like the Google Analytics
API.
In Google Analytics, you say, I want to have that dimension with that metric and combine
them and use them, that's not so easy with the Matomo API.
Let's take a look on the SQL database access.
The pro is the most visualization solutions has a connector for MySQL, that's easy, so
you don't need to develop one or something like this.
And if you have access to the database, you also have access to the raw data from Google
Analytics to build reports which are based on that.
But the cons are that setting up a secure connection to the database from the visualization
solution could be difficult, because you need to be sure no other people out there can,
access your MySQL database.
And if you are using aggregated analytics data, so these predefined Matomo tables, the
same thing like in the API is that you don't have the flexibility like in Google Analytics.
And it can harm the data page performance if you try to use that raw locked data to
build the reports.
So you must be careful there.
One other con is that it's not available in the Matomo cloud, so you don't have access
to the SQL database there.
The other last option is to transfer data out of Matomo and save them in, as example,
Google BigQuery.
So you can use a service or a solution like Abyte, which is an ELT toolset, where you
can say, oh, grab the data from the raw Matomo API, put it into BigQuery, and make something
there.
If you want to do that, it has some pros.
So analytic database connectors are also available in the most visualization solutions.
You can work directly with the locked data because there's no restriction of some performance
hints if you work with them.
And you can combine metrics, dimensions in another way, like with the predefined data
sets on Matomo, and it's fast on large data sets.
Cons are, yeah, setting up the data transfer could be difficult.
You need to write some complex SQL queries.
And yeah, you can calculate additional codes for the data transfer from Matomo to the analytics
database, and you must pay the analytics database.
That is something.
So if we compare, the API is really easy, and the cost is minimal, or none, if you use
it.
And you have a little bit of restriction and flexibility compared to the other solutions.
The SQL database access, yes, not as easy to access as the API.
Most could be medium if you want to think, but if you want to, you have direct access
to the database, it's also small.
And you're a little more flexible, like the API solution.
Data transfer is really complex in most cases, the costs are higher, but it's more flexible.
So if you have some requirements, other solutions can't give you this, this could be a solution.
In the next slides, we won't take a deeper look at the data transfer part, because it's
much more complex.
We stay with the API or the SQL database access.
So if we have some people who have said that they are using an external visualization solution,
which data transfer option are you using?
Is it API, SQL, or transfer to external, just type in text to get an overview of what you
are using.
I will take a look at the chat later, and that would be great to get a look inside.
So now we talk about getting the data into the visualization solution a little bit based
on these transfer methods.
There are some options, so the one is the native connector.
So if a solution has a native connector to Matomo, you can use that, and it's the most
easiest way.
We take a look at a workaround with Google Sheets, where you can use the API to use that,
and we will take a look on the SQL connector, that's the most solutions.
So we have some answers in the chat, it's a wide range of these options, we have some
who are using the APIs, someone using the SQL database, I don't see someone who uses
data transfers in some way.
So API and SQL database is I think the most used options here for the most people.
So yes, to get data into a solution, it's mentioned Google Data Studio, but in the most
cases other solutions are also connected to Google Sheets.
So it could work also for other data visualization tools.
And the process is you have the possibility to, below each chart you have an option to
export data, and you have the option to export data and get the URL, and with a workaround
you can export the data in Google Sheets.
So the data is then in Google Sheets, and you can configure the visualization tool to
use that Google Sheets as data source.
You will find here two links where Matomo, there's some information on Matomo Org is
and some other who describes these process step by step.
The best, it's a free solution for getting Matomo data into a data visualization tool.
So that's a great benefit for that, but you need some time to set this up for different
charts and sources.
For each, not for each, but for each report you want to have to be shown as a data visualization
tool, you need to add one spreadsheet that you write in there and so on.
And there are some limits based on the data range, possibilities, filters, and segments
must be predefined and so on.
Then I've taken a look on the possibilities about connectors to the solutions out there.
The Looker Studio has a Matomo connector available, it's developed by us, so some advertising
here, but for the other solutions we haven't found some.
If someone knows it, it would be great, so we can add it here.
I've seen at 16 o'clock there is a session by Thomas Persson about open source dashboards
on top on Matomo with Apache superset.
I don't know what it is, I will take a look into it also, I think it's interesting for
all who participate here.
I think there's no connector, he uses the SQL access directly, but we will see later.
So yes, at the moment a native connector is only available for Looker Studio at the moment.
So what we need to know, I've mentioned it a little bit earlier, is what is the structure
of the Matomo data when we want to work with that.
You have different reports here on the left in the navigation of Matomo about visitors
behavior, accretion, and so on, and Matomo data is structured in that way that mostly
each of these reports has its own table in the database with the pre-processed data,
so the data can be loaded fast.
MySQL has no analytics database, so this pre-processing is needed.
And each report has its own API request and its own dimensions and metrics in combination.
You can't, if, as example, the campaign report has a campaign name, you can't add another
dimension because it's not pre-processed.
So you need to keep in mind regarding what solutions if connector, Google Sheets or SQL,
for each of these reports you need to create your own data source in most cases.
So you work later with different data sources, one for Geo, one for visitors, one for campaigns
if you want to build a dashboard, it's recommended to name them good so you find the data later.
So with that in mind, the steps for creating a chart are the same for different charts.
So the first thing is the configuration, you need to know which site, which report you
want to have, and also create segments of filters if needed.
And then you have configured it in the Data Studio Connector or the Looker Connector,
it looks like this.
In Matomo itself, you will see where the data is, grab that report and put, grab that table
or chart, et cetera, and copy the export URL.
Then you need to connect the data, that's the next step.
So if you have the API URL, import a spreadsheet, set up a schedule, and import the schema from
that, the same for the SQL database, you need to choose the table or use the connector.
After that, you have the schema for that data source and can work with the data.
And the last step is then, it's the same for all these solutions, is to visualize the data
so you have the possibility from range of dimensions and metrics to create time series,
bar charts, map charts, et cetera.
So that are the different steps to do that.
So one thing, if you want to work with, if you have some requirements to use real dimensions
and metrics who are not in one of these pre-prepared reports, you need to create a custom report.
So as an example, if you want to know what campaigns work in what countries, so you need
two dimensions, country and campaign, and you want to know what's the results, what's
the bounce rate and so on, you need to create a custom report on that.
This custom report, you can import in the data visualization tool like the other options
that after you have created it, it's the same process there, but that's the only way to
combine dimensions and metrics which are not in one of these default reports already combined.
If you work with the API or also SQL, there are some performance considerations, especially
if you work with some dashboards.
Loading data from a Tomo is fast in the normal dashboard settings, but it can also be slow.
Just a little example, if you request results over time over the last 12 months compared
with the previous period with the selected segment, you can take over 30 seconds or longer.
In that case, also in the Tomo Cloud for the demo side, out there, there are much bigger
size and data sets, so yeah, the loading can be really tough there.
If you have more data and requesting longer timeframes, add filter segments that can also
expand the loading time.
For that, here are some tips we have discovered while people working with our Data Studio
Connector.
If you use the spreadsheet solution, that's not the case in most parts because it's pre-processed,
but if you're using the Data Connector or MySQL Access, we recommend to use a smaller
date range in the default view of the dashboard, so just select the month and not three years.
Add a date range if needed, and add a date range control if someone wants to get a longer
date range there.
Avoid the main metrics report.
It's a report which comes through the API where much metrics are in, but it takes longer
to load, in the most cases, most metrics are also in some sub-reports.
Avoid transferring a big amount of result rows, so if you have a landing page list and
you want to report the top landing page and you have 5 million ULs, don't send them all
to the data visualization tool and then cut them in Matomo.
Just get the top 100 rows with a filter option and show them in the visualization tool.
One other thing is to use custom reports.
If you have a complex query with segments and landing page ULs containing and so on,
create a custom report so it's pre-filled and you can only access the data instead of
each data visualization request you need to segment and filter the reports by itself.
One other option is to reduce the number of elements loaded at one time, so not to show
500 charts on one page, reduce it to a good amount.
In Looker Studio there's an option which is named extract data, if you use that, it extracts
the data from the source, stores it somewhere in the Google Cloud and you do only the access
against this fast storage and it gets the updates each night and you have a fast report.
That could be a solution, especially if you want to show a page time range from three
years and filter down by, so that could be a solution.
So yes, that was a rough overview about the topic data visualization, how data can go
from a Tomo to a visualization solution and what options are there and how that works.
Any questions from the audience here at the moment?
Thank you very much, Marcel.
If questions, any questions, please drop them in the chat.
Just to also inform you about this, there's a 40-second delay between the stream and the
chat room, so that's also why the poll was a bit delayed, I think.
I mean, already in the chat there's still a few answers about the question what people
are using for connectors and also a few fan messages, I think.
Thanks.
I get it, right?
So I see some answers, I've seen someone also exporting data through the GUI to show
them visualization solutions.
I think the spreadsheet variant could be then something who helps there to reduce the amount
of work and Thomas has written that for superset he built an own connector with SQL, so that
could be interesting in the session from him later.
I see there are actually some questions now as well.
So there's a question that Diana Ferber wrote that they are working on moving away from
Google Analytics using the non-privacy-friendly point as one of the main reasons.
So that question is how privacy-friendly is it to move the data back to Google Data Studio?
Yes, good question.
I'm not a lawyer, so just my opinion at that point.
If you are using Data Matomo to get the data saved somewhere, it depends how your setup
is.
If you have no customer data in your instance and just working with aggregated data and
so on, there's no personal data in there, so the IP is blocked by Matomo and so on.
So in my opinion, if there's no personal data in Matomo, you can't transfer it to any service
without harming your DSP flow and so on.
Yes, that's the one thing, if you have customer data in there, like order ID or something
like this, if you do that, it depends how your tracking is set up there and if you have
a reason for having it in Matomo already and you have access to it and some people have
said yes, you can save it, you can also, you need to check your lawyer if you can transfer
such data to a data studio if you have a contract with them, but yes, that's something you need
to check out there.
But as long as you have no personal data in Matomo, you can transfer, in my opinion, to
any tool out there.
It's just statistical data.
Another question by Niklas Terenstedt is if you can show an example of a visualization.
So the question is what do you mean by an example of a visualization?
I can show you something if I, let me see if that works here.
That is Luka, our data studio, Luka Studio.
I've created here a data source with, in that case, our connector, but that has explained
that could also be a SQL connection or a spreadsheet workaround there.
And yes, you have then these data source and you have the different dimensions and metrics
in here.
That is the channel type report.
So I have the channel type and here I've chosen the channel type and the wizards and have
made a normal time series chart.
And you can then change it to, I don't want to filter here, change the metric as example
to the order revenue or something else, what is available from the API call.
You could also make other charts from the same data as this one is just aggregated scorecard.
And you could also do some by charts the same way or change the charts in different ways
to make your visualizations here and it shows the data you need.
So there are much guides for visualization data in data studio out there.
I think that's something which is covered there already, but yes, it's the same procedure.
You have a data source with one of the, from one of the reports in Matomo and you can use
it here to visualize the data the way you like.
So that doesn't make sense here, the source should be the channel type.
Yes, I hope that answers that question.
I hope so too.
I mean, the person who asked the question is now still typing in chat.
So maybe you just, we have to wait a few seconds for the delay to allow them to reply.
So yes, well, in the meantime, okay.
So if there are no other questions, I mean, the chat room will remain open for further
discussions anyways.
I would once again like to thank you very much for your talk, for your very insightful
talk and yes, thanks a lot.
Thank you.
Thank you very much for listening and if you have any questions later, you can contact
me on LinkedIn or via email.
Yes.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.