[Autogenerated]
okay so first of all thank you
for everyone for attending this Pre-MatomoCamp
events are today so from now
until the let's say the next the
sixty minutes so forty five minutes of
presentation plus fifteen minutes of
questions and an answer i'm going to
talk about the specific topic which is
a Matomo tagged manager and i'm
going to try to cover as many
things i can so that's why i
decided to name it from eight to
setup my name is a whole new
sheldon i'm a professional consultant and trainer
on net more analytics and as well
i got to weave a couple of
friends this crazy idea of creating an
event named metal camp which will be
added next the monsoon sell two days
exactly from now where the id is
twelve people from all over the world
to come on stage and make a
presentation about met to move
analytics so as i am doing to
dish about to the sub presentation so
i choose the specific topic because the
last summer we ran a salvage on
the matter will cancel my promote kemp
dot org silva asking about what kind
of topic would you like us to
cover
during the multiple camp event which would
be on november the fourth and november
the fifth and the one topic which
was highly asked was a madman tag
module so the idea was to dare
to talk about met more tag manager
and why are we talking about an
events prayer event to date rest of
you shall evan
we'll be in one nonce the idea
is that as it's the first time
that we organize such an event we
have a team who will it said
don't know each other was no let's
say i t infrastructure define we decided
to launch a prayer event in order
to test our i t infrastructure in
order to ensure that under the day
we are able
to scale the different conferences for the
volume of attendees so this what we
are doing to death or what he
would like to thank two guys while
behind the screen of his behind the
several let's say lucasfilm glad that you
just hear indian tradition wasn't going to
me and as well as vinyl top
weezer from the company name of hunter
digital and huila in fact the scale
to silva and installed a different software
on the several in order for us
to be able to add this printer
to my camp and the met to
move camp event asthma issue have any
questions at any time
please feel free to drop us an
email directly unmet to mowjcamp dot org
so i can shook his website silk
here is the the websites or metal
can that blog just need to go
over here and write and contact us
so as what you can do is
you can go on the live thats
met to move or come the dog
so you can click over here and
if you click over here you will
get in fact access to the stream
that you are currently viewing right now
and in addition to that at the
bottom of the page or you're going
to see the metrics chat which is
at the chub that we use in
order to communicate with wifi chosen and
of course the place
where you can ask some mark some
questions or so yes if you have
some question please feel free to use
fazer contact us page and all you
can as well use directly to chat
over here or on which you cannot
send some question i can see already
that someone is typing in something so
if you have some question didn't
weave hazel event all the presentations attending
to their bed metamora take my job
please feel free to do so
i saw the topic of today is
metamodel tag manager so we're going to
first start with a definition metamodel tag
manager is what we call it target
management systems authority already like three big
word here tag management and system management
system you
probably already and you are probably familiar
with it so if you are taking
a content management system for example such
as group power such as wordpress such
as i dunno proprietary solutions such as
weeks of that kind of thing you
know whether you what it refers to
content management system is
software which is here in order to
manage some content such as posts suggest
pages such as media or any kind
of also that said content that you
can imagine in a tag management system
instead of managing contents like must be
media and text content
you have to manage what we call
tags and tags are nothing more than
in fact tracking codes and some of
you may not be familiar with tracking
codes but you may i guess i've
seen at least once when you access
to you matter more installation and then
and the first let's add the first
step that you need to know he
built up to send some data to
your manual is to copy and paste
a snippet of tracking code or we
can call even if the tag which
looks like this and this is exactly
what we are talking about here times
are nothing more than those nipples of
god that you insult on your
a website in order to push data
to matter what would you sweat about
so metamodel tag manager is nothing more
than a piece of software a place
where you're gonna manage instead of content
you manage tags you manage striking codes
in order to push yield that i
could
tion to the next level is what
it is about so of course for
most of the people that don't really
see the advantage of fit because they
are used to play with these single
tracking code which is pushing most of
the time enough information in order to
to start in fact your analysis because
it's b
rushing out of the page that you
are looking out is pushing out for
the enabling trekking two clicks which are
performing downloadable clicks donated by fighters and
out links but it meant then that
in some cases you may want to
collect more interaction than the switch for
exam
for tomorrow he might be interested in
in measuring the fact that people are
scrolling down the page because you would
like to know is they read your
content entirety or at least if they
view it entirely if you have some
videos on your website you may be
interesting and no english people are clicking
on the play button pause button if
shoves
the picture on on your website and
when you although your mouse of a
damsel cause it gets bigger lakes elsa
zoom which is happening that's typically the
kind of thing that you want to
perform with an additional let's add tracking
data collection and let's say scenario system
and it's exactly what you do live
a tight measurement system
right away within this presentation i will
have cause nemo which was a website
and really implemented tech management system in
order for you guys to syria how
you can push your that that prediction
to the to the next level
this is exactly what i what i
just mention i'm not going to go
back on it and why should you
use a tag management system or why
she views net html tag manager while
for better management so it's exactly like
a cms so in the cms you
create a lot of blog posts
post credit different pages you have different
hotels and you know when it's published
who has done what and when is
exactly the same thing with a tag
management system the idea is to have
a backhand on which you know what
the different tracking codes which have been
implemented on your website who has done
what what has been implemented
did and here we are talking about
project management that's more transparency within your
organization about knowing about what your colleagues
have implemented already abouts i'd say so
about better communication between your i t
teams and marketing and communication teams it's
of course easy
to to know the what happened in
the history of your website in terms
of in terms of data collection it
says well better in terms of sexual
eighteen the sense that you know at
least what is deployed and when it
is deployed and it can in some
cases decrease the loading time of your
website because
most of the time what what you
do when you implement for the first
time your basic tracking code on on
your website you'll just cutting and pasting
it everywhere and when you add some
other tracking code you may have the
same lets said the same configuration like
putting it everywhere was with the tiger
management system you can decide
when you would like those tags to
be triggered or not and of course
if you optimize this while you can
only measure what you need and not
the extra data that you'll probably never
look at
and those as well and this is
very important to get them awkward to
me too marketing and communication team that
said to none they keep teams and
it allowed them to more easily deploy
advance a measurement without relying on let's
say on some deployment time from
the eighty two
the whole tag management system or a
walking while you've seen it it's pretty
similar to what you are used to
because most of the time you copy
and paste the striking color you put
it on all the pages with the
deployment of a tag management system or
do you need to do is that
instead of copying and pasting this code
and all the pages what you do
just click over here as it's very
simple isn't a metal type measure and
in fact you take this snippet of
code that you put those wet on
all the pages in fact this code
is going to substitute this one okay
so you take this one you copy
and paste it on all the pages
on your website and what
then on this one is deployed everywhere
on on your website on all the
pages on your website then you can
in fact use the back end of
the tag management system which will be
displayed over here so if you cannot
seats right now in your manual installation
that's probably because
maybe he doesn't have been installed so
it's a plugin that you need to
download and activate it's a flipper again
you don't have to pay for it
all either it means that someone give
you an access to maximo that you
have extra rights in order to have
an access to its we met tomorrow
you have the super user you are
and mean
you have the right access to have
the read access and you'll get done
and use access and you get as
well as special rights for the tag
manager so in order to play with
it you will need to escape to
your admin also beggars i don't remember
which one you know they'll fold them
to give you an access to it
and to get an access to it's
what you just
need to click and then you would
see shield the the backend and healed
the backend in fact over here represent
all the the tags and then different
configuration i'm going to talk about later
on which will in fact of fighting
the failed thanks to the tracking code
that i was that way string you
just right so in fact here this
is what we can call a master
tracking code which gun control okay what's
going to execute everything which is located
over here within this this beckon
i
to make it simpler this is the
classical configuration that that's odd so far
so this is your your website without
tag management system so you have let's
say one tracking code one tag for
every solution that you want to do
that that you use in order to
collect some data so let's imagine that
here instead of analytics the jazz it's
your classic metal tracking code here is
another tracking code that juggling started because
i dunno you are playing with some
advertising networks okay without naming it like
the big
the big american one of let's say
conversion tracking code and then in addition
to that you have as well and
those are tracking code such as let's
say that'd be testing and a b
testing submission with a tag management system
was going to happen is that you'll
just going to have your contain over
hips which is the messed up tag
that was showing you some minutes ago
so the metal motel manager digests container
and then in fact all those scripts
are going to be added within this
one thanks to the eu-wide that we
can see over here so here i'm
going to go into detailing this one
but as you can see i can
add tags so it's not like
i only sent out around that tomorrow
technology's a genuine name in order to
be able let's say to collect together
all the different tracking codes that you
would like to send to was a
playoffs all was the solutions that you
are on your on yourself out so
all you can do
is probably one of the one that
you will play the most with which
is custom html which allows you to
cook and paste any script that you
want over here and i am on
small flat out this is exactly what
what we want to to perform here
is that to us within one single
system and a tag management system all
all different tracking
codes held out to organize better or
that connection modem
and this is what i just explained
so this is the messed up tracking
code that you need to implement on
your website in order to get started
of course according to a different cms
that you are using ours as already
some plugins which are yelled down in
order for you to ever make this
installation event event faster
i hold does the tag management system
walk while he talks we've made me
three components the first one is what
we call a target so the tag
represents the position for which you would
like to send the data to so
is what we have over here this
is the list of the different tracking
code that's that can
can pick up unless you choose a
tag so let's i want to send
the data to metromile then you're going
to configure it i'm going to go
into detail into this one electron and
then you need to explain when you
would like the given tag to be
triggered said to be executive i'm going
to take that exempt
follow the diet some minutes ago which
was about cap you would like to
measure the fact that people ask calling
down your website and you would like
to send this information to mathml so
what you will do is that you
pick up a tag which is met
to one that he takes tag you're
probably going to send what we call
an event which is an interaction
one so you send an interaction to
maximal and you would like this to
happen every time that someone is cutting
down and to do so what you
will do is that you will select
a second let's say nickname the components
that we have willing to take measurements
of vocabulary which is a trigger
and this is what we have over
here so here you get the list
of trigger so to send a condition
in order for the tracking code to
be executed and here you are going
to select toys r borrow e underscore
rich enough to say okay if someone
is cutting down the page i want
the tag to be filed and here
by default is going to be failed
every time that's the people are going
to scroll down more than fifty percent
of the page or you can of
course change that out and say okay
when the score up to ninety percent
of the page and this is what
it's going to walk so as a
recap it's you select the list
i do
the place where you would like to
send data to as a matter more
a zone advertising platform or a seventy
and he was a tradition that you
have on on your sarah denver hill
as a trigger you defined a condition
you know deaf on the stack to
deploy
johan in order to execute your tracking
code and the lesson that not least
exactly like in content management system when
you write the blog post is by
default written as a draft and then
if you want to put the clive
to send it for real on your
website you need to pub
leash and this is exactly what we
have over here you see we put
a small rocket's it's the publish button
and when you click on it it
means that's what you configure over here
there's going to be sent to the
solution that you want is a matter
mole or as though they just hazing
platform or any wives
i am not going to detail much
about oid yourself it's a possibility because
i can talk about the profumo they
get dark as would have been valuable
and so on and so forth that's
not going to make it complex so
far i'm just going to make a
brief demo you know the for you
to clearly identify what's the point then
what we are talking about so just
to conclude with lid so the theoretical
approach is that you select a tag
to link it to a trigger and
then you publish okay you send it
live for the sake of the conference
where i'm going to do is that's
i am going to take a real
use case they did is that's
i use a website in the useless
web dot com which is randomly picking
up a website just for you
to know that not undertaking any website
from a client's ninety six this and
i ended up with a differing website
i saw
i dunno this website at all i'm
just going to try to show you
the whole attack metro will be useful
here so as i don't know the
webmaster of the website where i'm going
to use a great extension which i've
been recommended to me by a guy
named thomas pearson from digital his eighties
that's you will probably cease during the
night and the campus is doing a
lot of conferences about animals this extension
is available for google chrome chromium and
everything which is a google from something
it's name user css and javascript and
it's very useful because it allows you
to insult some tracking code
on the websites that you don't own
it's pretty good for fun demoing so
that's that's what i'm going to do
here
i thought first things first that i'm
going to show you what on the
website will look like in metal if
i will have use the tag management
system so i'm going to take the
classic tracking code i'm going to go
over on the website i'm going to
use this given the given extent
so the extension would just require me
to remove the html comments so as
the script tag like this and now
we are good to go so i'm
going to call it originally maximo maximo
camp okay save and let's go okay
so
so now what's going to happen is
that if i look at the website
right now the tracking cubs going to
be implemented so normally if i go
over here on this page i should
see that they get my visits okay
great talks and so this is this
is myself so nothing in craig
bore here okay it's exactly what we
were used to see we were traditional
matter more tracking can as you can
see a face cord down the page
and i've kept my my maximo
in crazy we've come and the reason
is that this is the classic tracking
code so it's just measuring the page
you and just a click as well
on outings and we mentioned it's as
file extension downloads so here let's imagine
for example i would like to track
the number of people which while clicking
on this
given the nature you see him like
clicking like five times on it
nothing's going to happen why is that
why because the classic tracking code of
metal has not been
he's not hyper here if i click
for example hill and our sis as
you can see on the bottom left
of the page is going to go
on the same
i think it's going to go down
index i gonna double check if this
will be measured by metal
yes this one's going to be measured
that may matter more it's just it's
not telling me that his analysis fit
but i could somehow guess it get
in touch either made too so i'm
going to click on it's gonna see
if
if it's gonna walk
no it's not walking so here this
is just what i wanted to show
you is that the classic metro mode
tracking code won't measure up probably everything
that's in it so if you want
to know for example if people are
interacting with your images if you want
to know if people are clicking we're
here on the image if you want
to know
if they reach a specific part of
the content of your page you cannot
do it by default with the classic
tracking code of medical never been to
see what's going to happen if i
deploy a net html tag match of
tracking code so i'm going to go
over here and type manager i'm going
to pickup the
container as i previously mentioned it's what's
going to happen is that's i'm going
to use on small disk this extension
ships so it's arched which one do
i want to play with it's this
one okay i'm going to remove this
one
and now we're gonna see what's going
to happen so
perhaps an unsafe okay what would i
do
now i go back on the page
nothing's going to happen and nothing nothing's
going to be incredible right now because
as you can see from the backend
of my solution i have not yet
configure the different behavior that i want
to measure like the score tracking like
the peak and made two and so
on and so forth so
this is what we're going to do
right now so i'm going to create
a new tag these tags then it'd
be like
the credit makes cool events matter why
it takes so i just want to
have a name which is different than
those of time which is what would
be implemented which is just measurement of
paid you
she i'm going to say okay i
want to measure nevins not pedro because
it does the sense i mean someone
who is running down the pages still
on the same page sure i don't
need another pitcher to be to be
recorded
then i'm gonna have to insult here
different values to see is specific to
events because an event is defined by
category inaction and and the name i
mean that that's what madame louise expecting
twelve as an event so here i
can i can fill them with whatever
day
today was the last time you organize
your company you organize your identity system
in a certain way and you want
to have a naming convention which has
which makes sense so most of the
time it's category and from there events
will be something like cat we want
to measure interactions the action
is
let's send the discord
when people performed a core and name
i could put the same name as
this one but will be like redundant
and so i'm going to do here
is that i'm going to pick up
over here what we call invaluable instead
so valuable means it's not going to
be out coded value like like i
did here is going to be some
sandwiches day
dynamic based on what we called the
dumb of the page document object modernity
which is the information we are on
the page and so here they are
then the one that i'm interested in
is technically being fucked a page where
i but i would rather prefer to
know who felt people are scrolling down
the page
page so i'm going to pick up
over here and scroll and it's this
quarter vertical doesn't they show and to
which level two people score down and
now i'm going to add a trigger
sort of trigger is as i previously
mentioned is the condition for which the
data will be collected so i'm going
to pick up over here those are
rich and i wanted to be filed
i would consider like yeah fifty belsen
please find a niche and and and
that's it so i click over i
can create new trigger so what i
did or healers that i said to
the system police met
tumblr tag manager send an event with
those values was a category direction as
an action score and as a name
have become the dynamic value to which
people scroll down and i want you
to fire every time that someone is
reaching more than fifty percents of
the score of the page and i
can i can create my tag and
i can decide to publish which means
like everything which is now within the
container i wanted to go live so
i go over here
i give up
the name of depression so like a
scroll
deployments deployment and i click over here
and now what's up what is happening
is that every scene which was within
my container so hailed the measurement of
the page you the measurement of core
event
should have been if my team always
going in the right direction shouldn't have
been deployed properly so if i go
now back on the website while nothing
impressive is happening because i have not
yet scored down my page or if
i go over here i would still
say that's ok i'm over here and
the page is chris
city of your time is correct but
i have not yet scored down so
there was no score event with chalmers
job and now he face quarter down
as you can see i'm not yet
at fifty percent so i'm like fifty
percent here if i go back and
let my refresh nothing should happen and
this is no more because i have
not yet reached the fifty plus sometime
in which the fifty best this is
a long page on it's probably ok
i'm
i'm not yet at fifty percent but
i'm just going to refresh in order
to show you that's still not deployed
and now if i go that i
do ok here i guess i reach
a kiss to sixty or seventy percent
so normally if i'm lucky enough i
should fish well ok i'm lucky enough
to see as you can fish
the evans has to be measured so
like okay i reached the more than
sixty percent of the page it's pushing
to the system interaction scored and fifty
reach represent exactly what i wanted and
on those data sent as i decided
to send them as an event that
would sharp overhead and b
behavior and then event and i wish
them over yourself cause it's going to
give me a lot of valuable information
that they didn't have so fossil so
far we've a let's say classic tracking
measurement or i could say that people
are going into page but i don't
know if they are reading the content
one artist
i dunno is that interacting with the
patent owner and thanks to escort tracking
i can or would you say that's
ok at least understood that they can
also go down the page
and let's take maybe another exam poor
i'm going to take this burden which
is the the get in touch i
saw here it's a this one is
more for eye contact interaction so this
is of course very interesting because probably
i mean this guy i don't know
who is behind the website but probably
he or she wants to get
his move to chase or anything slightest
so getting the measurement of people whedon
intend to contact him i think it's
important so i'm going to do is
that i'm going up over night my
mouse of our found the on the
on the elements because i will need
this adamant info
formation in order to configure and i
met him one time manager here what
they can see is that i have
it's a link which is in a
cif which contains an information which is
made to such so as
i text him and which is get
in touch so he like i can
play differently i can configure it differently
but i guess that in my case
i would probably be so okay everytime
someone's going to click on the link
on the page which contained information get
in touch as a text sediment i
want and information
to be sent to more so that
that's what i would do so i'm
going to go back over here with
maximal i'm gonna select matawan ethics as
a target group definitely decide to send
the data to a sub of the
player i mean that that's the refinement
of course depends of the different permission
system that you are using but in
my case i'm just using that one
a tick so i'm going to cut
it like a intense them to contact
intend to contact
the kid when they met more antics
and so here i could decide to
send it as an event or to
send it as a as a goal
maybe for the sake of this example
i'm going to use a goal the
reason why i would like to use
a good just for this presentation for
you guys to see the difference so
let's imagine that i want to
it has a goal like the purpose
of my website is ready to get
some leads to get some contacts and
probably decent direction as family values and
just cutting down if people are screwing
down nothing is standing in the dugout
contact and they'll chase my books receives
a contact me to get in touch
there's probably a highest probably tsh that
all those people convert so that's probably
why i wanted to find a good
heel result in an event
i'm going to add the trigger now
so the trigger will be an interaction
which is based on the click which
lays on the link elemental could it
like link click
me too
and here i'm going to use a
filter because if i just set it
like this it will be like every
link that they click on the website
which will be measured as a goal
that's typically not what i want to
do because they have many links on
the page as you can see i
got one here i got one here
i got i got many
so that that's not what i want
to do so i want to filter
it and i want to socal is
just every time that someone will click
on the element of the page to
say healed the the link where the
value equal to get in touch ok
so click decks get in touch with
him saying okay if someone click on
the link which contain the text which
is in my case getting in touch
okay and now i can i can
crate made by tag us it's nothing
to walks right to work or i
need to do first is to go
over a hill in maximal and i
need to add to the goal because
i haven't done it yet
and then to contact thought for the
people who don't know what the goal
is is that the most important action
that you would like to measure on
your website ie i'm going to select
men will gore because that's whole the
matter with technogym recognized goals which achieved
you need to send them as a
as an
one
i i'm gonna select the logo to
be converted more than one village just
for the book proposition as well because
probably want us on during the visit
camp
the interesting contact me multiple times it's
not making much sense but wouldn't have
done it
i saw this what i just what
they do so same thing as last
time nothing extraordinary is going to happen
right now because i have not yet
i
i published my walk so now i
can decide to publish it
but in my case i'm going to
use something that i have not yet
shown you which is the preview and
debug because if i publish it means
finding enough to make some dimwit stuff
but if you do it for real
and that you mess up something up
it means that's everybody's all the visitors
who are going to go on your
website when
i probably send you some fake data
on the wrong data on the six
i do so it's a good practice
to never publish straight to web just
to prove you first notice okay and
i want to see if my implementation
is correct rather than directly publishing it
live
in fact using the preview mode it's
like reviewing your content draft before publishing
it so that's what i'm going to
do here so in order to activate
pretty much you need to enable it
within the maximum talking about just so
as i did and then you need
to append the fourteen parameter at the
end of the us if false
the reason it doesn't work like like
right now it's probably that's you need
to clear your cache first so ctrl
f five and then issue are lucky
so as i do you get inside
the preview mode which is activated here
so here had preview monday studying your
camp the first tag has been deployed
which is the
the page you want the fact that
the page has been viewed the score
tracking as not been yet filed and
that's normal because they are not just
scroll down up to fifty percent and
intend to contact the target has not
been deployed yet executed because they haven't
yet to kick them get in touch
just for the sake of the example
you see if i scrolled down the
page if i go up to fifty
percent i get discouraged over here and
discourage his executive okay so this is
what the preview mode is about it's
about showing you debugging and helping you
in knowing if the tag that you
implemented is walking on
i want going to do anything anything
with a creek and get in touch
and if i'm lucky enough no matter
what's going to happen the warheads that
never will be filed in order to
say hey you know what's the trigger
that you implemented with the tag associated
to it walked and it has been
recorded bassist system so i'm going to
pick on getting to
ouch since that time kind of like
as you can see the link click
have been deployed and here i am
getting it so it's great it's nice
that the data has been sent
to to maximal so i can now
peacefully look over here and have in
fact as you can see the gold
which have been deployed so this is
in fact what matt moore talking about
jelly's abouts as they say dislike pushing
your data collection to the next level
by giving you the possibility to implement
very complex tracking let's say method is
edi thanks to a beckham kept soft
cross shown like this you may have
the feeling that's okay it's like super
how to do it is like it's
going to take me i what else
to do i needed training and so
on and so forth while just
veteran just by watching this video watching
this training let's say this conference you
already learn a lot after all it's
a lot about practice so in order
to practise what you can do is
exactly the way did it is like
using this extension and use a javascript
and css implement it on a website
that you don't own and then
send the data to a net to
more website the twelve will be just
for the sake of the demo just
on the sake of practice and this
is how you can learn a lot
then you have as well unmet to
move the quality of the food guide
which is over here that you can
you just need to type the tag
manager and you will see in fact
a fool
guide over here from the from the
net with cima and then at the
end of the of the guide you
even get a tag match of training
also until jackie that's me again that's
with full videos that you can watch
expanding you everything that i just show
you step by step in order for
you guys
i used to feel more confident with
the the tag management system so that
that's really what i wanted to show
you as a said the didn't tell
me yet let's do it sam
the it's the basic and intermediate level
of using a mat to move the
majority to talking about joins in war
this is about understanding what it is
about and being able to play with
the use user interface in order to
get ready to make some data collection
then of course have to accept some
practice
the effect of stuff to be used
with it and the next spot which
is about how to go to the
next level is about knowing what we
call the jews of the so that's
my that's my
i that's night presentation but the next
but not have to move to the
next level is ready to understand what
is it that talia and how you
cannot use it and why is it
useful
so here's the controversy around the tag
management system a time management system as
you can see is mostly other ties
for communication and marketing department guys now
though to tell them okay now you
have a super tools which can make
super complex things and you don't need
to rely on
the i t guys any more
that's the way it is advertise but
you have to know that's the way
you play it the way i show
you how to play with the tag
management system it is just one part
of it that's the part which is
the less techy that's fallen to advanced
and complex project you will need to
use what to call it that talia
which
dispatch rely on your i t deference
and will explain myself little bits
that little is that let's use another
example here in order for what i'm
expecting you to to make more sense
let's imagine for example that you would
like to collect other data for this
given page the hotel the page ok
you would like to push to maximal
decided that this gives
page this given piece of content has
been written by john okay
the problem here is that's the name
john is not on the page you
see i can i can look under
the page oh by the way of
john okay bad example i'm going to
say like it's written by jones okay
to get to know though joe dublin
i don't have any johnny on the
page ok so
that's that's problematic because i cannot send
this data to know more than me
as a webmaster i know that johnny
who was just given page so how
can i do this i was just
with the time my jailed away showed
to you i cannot between let's add
to the contribution of the
eighty guys thanks to that idea i
could make this data available because you
know within your internal system your cms
for example or annual database that this
is john the world the content because
on your cms you have the possibility
to insult the data that the auto
focus on board is just that you
decided to know
up on the page but you need
this information in order to send it
to met
so what you need to play with
what you need to have here is
what we call it that area which
consists of a piece of additional code
that you add on the page in
order for met with a module to
be able to grab this information and
then push it out to the system
as it consists of lines of
cut that ad like this like this
one therapy on on the page and
of course here what we call devalue
are written in programming language most of
the time it's peach peach all was
a language that you'll def seems he
is familiar with in order to fetch
the data
bays require the data that you want
and then make it available for you
within what we call it that and
a jar that you can afterwards
get within the system so for the
sake of the example where i'm going
to do that i would go back
over here and i'm going to add
physical use this is definitely a thing
so i just was going to do
here i'm gonna just name like nato
then i'm going to give him the
name which is as i said it's
going to dejan so
yips so
journeys and i should be good to
okay so this is what i have
now i have that idea on the
page with valuable which is a though
which has a value which is johnny
and what i can do now within
the tag management system since was going
to go back on it gibbs amendment
system doesn't create this valuable and you're
gonna see that we can grab this
value and make it available for the
time angeles i'm going to go over
here and i'm gonna select what we
call the the
thirty yo i'm going to give it
the name which is explicit on which
of course correspond to the thirty one
that i created which is auto and
now is going to make a bridge
between the tag manager and the
and that talia and now i need
to ask my several cat how can
i push it to the system so
in my case i'm going to
i hook related to it's just thinking
about disease that's going to be accustomed
i mentioned i'm going to go over
here and we'll create a custom dimension
the custom dimensions going to be a
detection level going to be a photo
is going to be active and that's
all for the people who don't know
what is
custom dimension its and it's and then
trish that we create in metamora which
is custom sickness it doesn't exist by
default it's just it's correspond to what
your website collect that met them was
the entry fight so that's why it's
a custom one then i just created
it you know to be able to
have a place where
where to send the data to within
within maximum and that's mostly it's what
they need to do now is just
to do in fact correct this given
type because this tag is the one
dealing with the page you and i
just want to modify this one and
say every time
and the the page is going to
be loaded i want as well to
send information dealing with the auto because
i want to know who what the
page so i'm going to go over
how they can select the the thirty
one valuable that they created and now
if i'm lucky enough on small one
but not not going to publish
and just understand pretty much that's if
i've done this thing properly patients each
photo showing up within no met and
so on small i'm going to go
over here within the visit club showing
you that so far the information is
not collected did it via the page
or here for example fight
all my mouse on this page i
not know who is the author of
the page that now if i'm lucky
enough and if i could make some
screen preview mode like this ceps okay
so here the page has been loaded
so nobody the valuable should have been
sent as well so i'm going to
look at that and are you here
we've ended today i know
details no to name johnny which is
exactly what they wanted and if i
look at the met to move configuration
nobody on small i should have ah
yes yeah that you see custom dimensions
index one but eugenie's that's perfect so
i can now go back we didn't
they matter more i can refresh my
page and normally if i
i although my mouse over the page
as you can see that was accustomed
i mention named auto equal journeys which
is damien this page has been written
by jonny so if i gave up
getting behavioral issues see photo and i
should see the name johnny if i'm
lucky enough
it's loading the page it's a chips
over their health that's the reason white
sticking some time and shows you can
see i get to report a photo
with giannis and then it gets different
pitches which have been written by john
and that's everything that i wanted to
show you for the thought to dish
and when they look at the different
questions which are asked within the chat
for the people to what the chance
to to watch it i just would
like to say thank you for all
the people were attending it today i
think we and can tell the lead
say technical issues so that that's great
that we organize this for him
back to the camp issue of any
any questions dealing with madam we're talking
about jail just feel free to send
them spoof i met the moon camp
adult also a contact form offered free
as well to send directly your questions
derek is proof spoof metrics that we
have right now running at the moment