the hello
so i started the recording so since
it's ten a m we're about to
start with a session today we have
a richard stark who is a
Matomo support member and Matomo analytics expert
in his talk Matomo tips and
tricks he will tell us more about
a collection of Matomo features which
you might not know about so let's
hear richard for more
good evening from new zealand thank you
everybody for joining this MatomoCamp
session for tips and tricks alright so
for those of you who have never
heard of me before hi i'm richard
i am part of the mid-term a
support team based here in new zealand
and for those of you who may
have
said to some emails over the past
couple of months maybe you are so
you might have seen my name pop
up i in your email inbox maybe
now and then so if this is
not the first time thank you so
much for joining us if it is
first time hearing about me it's great
to meet you will all rights as
you saw in the previous slide my
session for today's titled
mattel mode tips and tricks i've really
tried to include a bunch of different
tips and tricks for everybody kinda from
the everyday users of moto mo as
well as tips and tricks for those
responsible for managing the summer setup or
four meter mo administrators alright so i've
broken down
down the tips and tricks into four
different categories they are number one you
eye tips
number two performance tips number three useful
cla or command line interface commands and
how to figure out what options to
use and number for useful free plugins
that are not installed by default in
moto mo
and then at the end of the
session i will have a short q
and a session so please feel free
to pop any questions he might have
in a chat room during the session
we do have a dedicated chat room
available for this live session on chat
dot matua camp dot org i have
asked the moderator to grab a few
of the more interesting questions to answer
at the end just to make sure
that we don't
miss any of those bureaus are more
than welcome to be a questions at
the end if they do get missed
if we do have enough time we'll
also be opening up the floor to
any questions at that time that you
may have just randomly so let's get
started number one we've got some ewi
tips so the first tip of gut
fee today is called zenmate
note so for those of you who
have never used zen mode before what
it basically does is it provides you
with an uninterrupted view of your mature
reports or your mattel dashboard and it
can be really really useful for situations
where you want to have a dashboard
on a dedicated screen or a dedicated
vice if forced
showing reports for example she might have
a dedicated screen in your office for
looking at dashboards are pretty numbers and
charts that is the perfect thing to
use for this it can also be
quite useful if you wanted to embed
for example the entire matua you i
into an i frame so toggling zen
mode on and off can then add
allow you to quite easily navigate between
the different reports within the i frame
and then when you want to bring
that into so full screen mode you
can quickly toggle the zen mode and
you have that awesome uninterrupted view of
your dashboard or for your reports so
if you've never seen what zemo looks
like before and i'll go
to show a screen which hopefully a
lot of you are familiar with this
is what the standard you i in
matomo looks like i'm pretty sure this
is something that a lot of you
see probably on a daily basis maybe
less often for other people but what
zen mode basically does is this it
gets rid of the the top menu
bar gets rid of the menus on
the left hand side
and in the screenshot here i've kind
of added the screenshot including the ural
bar at the top but if he
did once have this nice big screen
you can go to full screen and
you can have that really awesome uninterrupted
view of your mature reports
see if you've never used it before
there's actually two different ways we can
get to zen mode how he can
toggle it on and off said the
one option of course is to just
click on a small little toggle button
at the top of the page over
here the other option which is my
preferred option is just to hit the
z key on your keyboard that allows
you to quickly switch between
when zen mode on and off
i to my next tip for you
today is the search function shortcut so
the first search function shortcut helps you
can quickly navigate within the midsummer you
i using your keyboard and keyboard arrows
so what it does is it allows
you to search for and switch between
websites and segments quite quickly
ie without having to touch your mouse
it also doubles as a search tool
to look for more information on the
matua dot org site for example you
can quickly search up for user guides
or maybe you have a question or
two that hopefully is answered in an
f a q so most of you
have probably seen the search bar up
in the top left hand side of
the matua ewi before but if you
wanted to quickly access this search feature
just hit the f key on your
keyboard
i the next you i tip for
today is themed so for those of
you who've who've kind of use matua
for a long time and have never
never really tried themes before it's really
something that you can use to kind
of customize the look the feel and
layout of the midsummer you i there
are actually several
all different themes available pretty much for
every midsummer you user in the world
that you can quickly install and activate
on your moto mo to get a
really customer that can field so some
of the default ones you can see
up in the screen now for example
we've got modern we've got the minimalist
themes we've got the dark themes but
then we have
have some of the themes that are
specific gst customizing fonts some that give
you really cool visualizations of us and
spock lines things like that
the really great thing about themes though
is that you're really not just limited
to these few themes that are available
themes are completely customizable you can customize
them to your heart's content and it
really requires very little skill if you
have a basic understanding of css
or maybe a little bit of less
you can customize as much as you
want and then upload those themes directly
to your midterm are you i say
if you've never installed or activated themes
before you probably wondering how do i
download and install themes now we see
we can have a look on the
website directly at themes dot moto mo
dot org
but you can also directly have a
look at the themes from within your
matua you are so to do that
we just go to the administration icon
we go to platform and marketplace and
we click on the drop down menu
and we select themes from here you
can select any of the themes that
are available to download but you'll also
have a nice little button
but the top of the screen that
lets you upload your custom themes in
a zip file format that you can
then install and activate on your midterm
or instance
alright the next section is performance tips
so one of the biggest performance improvements
that you can make to your maternal
instance is to disable browser archiving and
then set up a crontab for archiving
you might be wondering why do we
we recommend disabling browser archiving now for
the majority of users out there that
have very small websites or websites that
might have only a few hundred visits
a day it's definitely not worth the
effort going ahead and setting up those
cron tabs and disabling browser archiving but
for those of you that are tracking
a little bit more
or you know maybe a few thousand
hits a day or maybe tens of
thousands of hits a day this is
probably one of the biggest improvements ie
you can make to the performance of
moto mo that you can see very
quick and tangible results so when we
have browser archiving enabled almost every time
a
user views a report matua needs to
process the the report that they're trying
to request their needs it needs to
go fetch all that raw data nisi
crunched the numbers and he should put
everything into pretty charts and numbers and
lines and presented onto the screen and
it does this on the fly or
basically in real time
so you can imagine if you're loading
a report that has a load of
data or reports that cover a long
period of time this can sometimes really
slow down and your experience in potomac
can sometimes could take quite a long
time for those reports to load
this sort of effect can really be
compounded when users are not aware of
this and it you know they might
be going around jumping through a bunch
of different reports wondering why the heck
is this thing taking so long what
i mean thereby compounding is if a
user clicks a one report it takes
three or four seconds to load and
they don't see
anything on the screen they decide hey
i'm going to have a look at
this report that report does the same
they can go through five or six
or seven different reports in a matter
of seconds and every single one of
those reports once you start loading them
in the user interface those requests have
already been sent them to my server
is working on them in the background
to try and process all that data
now the good thing is is when
they go back to those other reports
that they've already requested the data for
it should load relatively quickly the problem
is if they come back and do
that again in one or two hours
later it's going to need to do
that whole process over again so by
pre processing all of those reports using
we call a crontab for the core
archive command and setting up a schedule
and disabling that browser archiving we can
be one hundred per cent certain that
all of those reports can load really
really quickly and your matua users can
have a great experience so this setting
can actually be changed directly
within the general settings of your maternal
instance but it can also be set
up by setting the specific config setting
in your config that any to ph
pi but of course if you're not
familiar with messing around with the files
directly on the potomac server disabling this
within the u i is just perfect
alright it is still important however to
understand that there are going to be
some cases where mahama will still need
to to kind of process reports when
they're requested from the browser this is
specifically important when you're requesting for example
a date range report because a date
range report
cannot be pre processed and the other
thing as well if you have users
who have created segments in those segments
have been configured to be processed from
in real time or on the fly
those segments will also be triggering some
browser archiving requests alright the next
that we got for you has to
do with segments so what we talk
about with segments where it comes to
performance is we're talking about how far
back segments are processed by default on
your meter the server so when you
have a segment in the terminal you're
creating a segment or editing a segment
the default
the tumor is going to process that
root segment for is what we call
the beginning of time and that basically
means that the tumor is going to
process that segment from the very first
day that you have raw data now
for a lot of people this can
mean that you know there have
owing to process segment data going back
two or three or even more years
five or six years into the past
and so this can have a really
big impact on performance especially for those
people who have a lot of historical
or a lot of raw data
so
by changing this to a different times
frame for example you can change it
to automatically process on a back thirty
days or you can do it for
sixty days or three months or six
months or even a year you can
really customize and prevent your thomas server
from working too much and reports that
you might not need to use
so to change this setting we basically
need to add the following to our
config file now if you're wondering how
the heck are you going to remember
this all of this information is available
you can have a look in your
config file you can have a search
for it on the tumor a website
you can hopefully find some more information
about how to set this config file
well otherwise if you wanted to look
for this specific one you could maybe
take a screenshot have a look at
this recording afterwards and then you can
implement this into your config file settings
and of course like you can see
in the slide it's on the screen
there's a few different ways we can
set this up for example the one
at the top is the segment creation
time so
basically that means that no historical data
for that segment is going to be
processed from before the date was created
so for a lot of people that
are tracking may be tens of thousands
or even millions of hits every single
month this might be the most beneficial
one you can also have a smaller
time frame for the example
the one at the bottom is the
last ninety three so that's roughly about
three months historical data
so now that i've told you how
to disable browser archiving and that to
change how far back potomac goes back
to process all of the segment data
you're probably wondering how do i get
historical data when i've configured this setting
in the tema and that brings us
really nice
nicely into our next segment and that
is useful see ally commands now cla
is a acronym for a command line
interface and that might sound really scary
obama tomo when you install it onto
your server has a really cool what
we call the console script and the
console script allows you to run some
really specific
quick commands directly on your thomas server
that allow you to do things or
accomplish tasks that you want to do
so we've got a couple of different
seal ai commands that we're going to
talk about today we're going to talk
about how to invalidate specific date ranges
so this is very useful for archiving
specific segments further back
then what we've just recently changed in
our settings we're also going to have
a look at invalidating specific segments and
then number three which is something that
you might not have been aware of
his invalidating specific plugins so if you
don't know matua four actually ships with
a new feature that
allows plugins that support that new feature
to automatically archive reports going back a
certain number of months or for example
if you've just installed a brand new
plugin or you've just purchased a premium
plugin and you go ahead and install
that onto your midterm a server the
great thing is that moto mo is
going to go back and on
automatically archive the last six months of
data for that new plugin so that
means that you have instant access to
a great wealth of historical report data
for that new plugin
however sometimes it's still going to be
necessary to archive reports going further back
than what we've just set up in
our settings this is especially useful when
you just install the plugin you want
to have a look at we know
what was the data for this plugin
a year ago or two years ago
or even further back than that as
far back as what you have
of raw data
so that is when the core invalidate
report data console command it comes in
so as you can see an example
on the screen in this example we're
running the invalidate report data console command
so this command always requires a dates
option as you can see in the
example
we have guts for example from the
first of june up until today so
that will basically invalidate all repeat were
all report data for your entire matua
instance going from the first of june
till today you can also use other
types of date format such as the
last thirty or last seven or last
night
ninety you know things like that to
kind of just get a general date
range invalidated
and so some of you if you're
having a look at this might be
remembering that we do have what we
call the invalidate reports plugin that also
allows you as you can see in
this example to invalidate segments the biggest
difference of course between the plugin and
the console command is that the plugin
is
kind of like what we would consider
a sledgehammer when you're trying to invalidate
report data it it doesn't necessarily differentiate
between different specific dates or specific plugins
it's kind of an all or nothing
deal and that's where it really comes
in handy knowing how to work with
the cla command
ns and you can combine a lot
of these different options together to get
some really specific date ranges or specific
report data that you're looking for so
as you can see in the example
over here we've just put the plain
text name of our segment and in
the next one you'll see that we
can
now also invalidate some very specific plugins
so this is really where the seal
ai commands are a lot more useful
than just invalidating report data in the
us so when we combine all of
these together we get the ability to
not only invalidate reports for a specific
day
date range and for a specific segment
but also for a very specific plugin
so this is really really useful and
that once you've done all this of
course it then becomes necessary to re
process that data and that brings us
to the very last step in this
specific section and that is reprocessing the
report data that we've just invalidated using
the force
date range option so in this example
we're looking at the last one that
we use the core invalidate report data
where we set the dates as the
first of june to the last of
june and when we run this last
core archive command with the force date
range similar to or exactly matching where
we
just invalidated metamora is going to only
go ahead and process that specific date
range for that specific plugin
so some plugins do actually have their
own console commands that can be used
for archiving which we'll talk about in
a minute but what a load of
you may be wondering is like ooh
do i have to take a screenshot
of this page do i have to
memorize all of this information that's in
front of me right now so that
i know how to use it and
the great
news is no you don't have to
memorize or take a screenshot of any
of this data because all of this
is directly available when you run the
console commands directly on your potomac server
and we can find this information by
using the dash dash help option that
the dash dash help option
when you're working the cla commands is
your absolute best friend if you've ever
forgotten what the specific command is or
what type of input you need to
give for a specific option the dash
dash help option is going to show
that so here for example in this
slide we've got with the help output
for the core
archive command so as you can see
in the screen hopefully the text isn't
too small we can see all of
the potential options that we could add
to this kind of really narrow down
and get some very specific commands that
we can use for our server
so as i mentioned earlier we do
have some plugins that might have some
very specific commands a good example of
a plugin that has it's own archiving
command is the customer reports plugin so
where the customer ports a console command
it allows you to actually go in
and specifically just archive the customer
ports for a specific date range without
needing to first invalidate that data
now a lot of you might be
wondering you know do i need to
have a look at that do i
need to go look at a guide
for that sort of information and here's
the next really great tip is that
no you really don't have to know
that information beforehand the console command if
you just type in console on an
ssh or in a terminal window in
the midterm
root directory and you add the dash
dash list option it's going to give
you a full list of all of
the console commands that you can run
directly on your matua server and now
that you've got this great list of
console commands you can then run those
specific commands each with their own dash
dash help or dash
ash help option to get a list
of all the optional parameters or required
parameters that that specific plugin requires
so
the important thing to remember whenever you're
working on this thing is that just
because a command works on one meter
amr server doesn't necessarily mean that it
works on every other tomato server and
the reason for this is that every
plugin that you install has the ability
to add options to that list so
in other words wait
we're talking about all of these console
commands can be or are in a
lot of cases server specific sir if
you're ever curious about how to run
these console commands how do i figure
out how to use all of this
stuff use the list command use the
help command and build your command from
there
alright so our next section is going
to be useful free plugins and these
are specifically plugins that are not installed
in moto mo by default but are
available to be downloaded and installed directly
from within your maternal instance without requiring
any additional information all you basic
we have to do is click download
and install from your meter maintenance and
we're going to start with the first
one on my list at least and
in my opinion one of the best
free plugins that you can install called
the cute tracking plugin
so the queue tracking plugin it improves
the performance and the stability of your
motto my server by reducing the load
on the potomac database during tracking it
also at the same time really greatly
improves the speed of tracking requests sent
to your maternal server
so how this works does take a
little bit of an explanation so we're
going to do that now so hopefully
you'll see a graphic on your screen
and what we're looking at here is
what we would consider a normal tracking
requests so you can see it with
the top there the browser sends that
http tracking request that tracking request then
gets received by the
toma server and needs to be processed
it's then inserted directly into the potomac
database into that role visit slug and
then once it's inserted we send that
response to the browser
now the queue tracking plugin this behavior
changes in a few key ways says
you can see in the next graphic
as soon as the moto mod server
so here at the top again we
can see the http tracking request as
soon as that is received by the
server it's put into a queue
and then immediately the matua server responds
to that browser or to that device
or that application to say great i've
got that tracking request you can carry
on once that tracking request is then
placed into the queue there's a few
different things that can happen now number
one you can either set up your
moto instance to automatically process
is all of the requests that are
in the queue when the queue reaches
a certain threshold but it can also
be set up to be run on
a schedule so for example you can
process all of the requests in the
queue once every minute or once every
two or three minutes and what this
really does is that
like you saw in the beginning it
not only improves the tracker performance but
it also enables your mid toma server
to handle very large traffic peaks without
bringing down your database server and the
way that it does this is that
instead of sending you know small little
individual single tracking requests every single time
one
this tracking request is received to the
database server it can process all of
the tracking requests in that queue as
a batch tracking requests so it really
helps your matua server and it really
makes it a lot more stable and
capable of handling those very large tracking
peaks
i the next one on the list
is the tracking spam prevention plugin so
the tracking spam prevention plugin gives you
some really good options that you can
enable to prevent spam tracking requests being
sent or logged in your matua server
so it does this by giving you
a couple of options for
first option gives you is blocking requests
from cloud providers so this is really
useful for example if you have a
malicious or a bad actor that's sending
you a lot of tracking requests from
a server somewhere specifically in the world
and the problem might be that they're
using a lot of different servers you
can't block all of those ip ranges
will the great news is the spec
tracking spam prevention plugin is going to
really help you in that
number two is that it can automatically
block requests from headless browsers headless browsers
are notorious for people that tried to
send these sorts of requests because the
load that it puts in the device
sending those requests is a lot lower
than a fully fledged browser
number three it can restrict the number
of actions in a single visit or
the maximum number of actions that matua
will track in a single visit this
is especially useful to prevent spam visits
that might spoil that can sometimes track
hundreds or even thousands of actions in
a single visit
we've seen some examples with people that
we've provided support to in the past
from the potomac team where they have
had individual visits tracked over ten thousand
actions in a single visit in a
matter of minutes or even hours and
the great way is that you can
automatically block this or cap the number
for tracking requests that can be tracked
in a single instance and number for
it kings exclude specific countries or it
can allow you to only include specific
countries so this is really useful for
example if you have a website that
is specifically targeting or spin
civically only working in a single country
or in a single group of countries
to automatically exclude any tracking requests from
countries outside of that but it can
also be useful to very quickly and
easily exclude specific countries if you notice
that you're getting a lot of spam
or non legitimate tracking requests from those
countries
nice
alright the next plugin on the list
which is an absolute must have is
the marketing campaigns reporting so by default
matomo will give you the option or
we'll give you the ability to track
campaigns and it comes with a really
useful campaign your l builder directly in
the matter where you are
however a lot of people or let
me rather say most people probably already
have campaigns set up that they're using
to drive traffic to their site using
campaign needs that are oftentimes set up
in their ad networks or with specific
social networks and the marketing campaigns reporting
plugin extends that do
default capability that default campaigns reporting to
give you access to all of the
possible campaign parameters used by these platforms
as well as providing support for some
of these campaign tracking parameters without needing
to use any of the mid to
most specific campaign
parameters we have a really great blog
post available on our blog that you
can go and read up about the
marketing campaigns reporting and i would definitely
recommend installing it on your meter missouri
alright that extra one on the list
is probably a little bit more for
the moto mo administrators out there sir
that's called the log viewer so the
log viewer is kind of more just
a quality of life or convenience plugin
that you can install to have a
quick look at the moto mo application
logs so this can really save you
some time and effort
i instead of having to ssh into
your server and grip some logs or
download your logs from your syslog server
you just log into me tomo go
to administration you i and have a
look at the logs directly
alright and the next one on our
list is the custom alerts plugin so
the customer alerts plug in is really
great especially if you're not somebody who's
looking at the reports every single day
or the customer alerts plugin law allows
you to do is to get notified
when something change
changes or something happens something specific happens
in your midterm or instance or on
the websites that you're tracking for example
you can set up an alert when
your website gets more than three hundred
views in a day you can have
another alert set up for example if
a specific product sells less than one
hundred items in a specific
but alerts can be set up in
other ways as well for example you
can set up alerts as percentages so
you can set up alert for example
that notifies you if the traffic to
your website drops by more than fifty
percent in a given timeframe and obviously
if a fifty percent drop
over a given time frame probably indicates
that something big has changed or something
has happened you can also set it
up for if you have zero visits
now we see sera visits would be
a pretty bad outcome for you you
want to be sure that you're getting
all of the tracking data and that
nothing is wrong with that tracking data
so for those types of alerts you
can actually set them up not only
as an email alert but also as
an sms alert so if you're setting
up an sms alert you'll need to
make sure that you also set up
the mobile messaging plugin now the mobile
messaging plugin is included in potomac core
but it might not be activated on
your motto
i'm a server so if you want
to set up sms alerts with a
custom alerts plugin you'll need to go
ahead and activate that plugin as well
and the last plugin on our list
for today is the ip to company
plugin this one kind of explains itself
and what it does is it adds
the functionality to your motto my server
to easily see if visits to your
website or app or connecting from any
known ip array
wages for specific companies so this is
really useful especially for if your website
or even your marketing campaigns are specifically
targeting a certain market segment or even
a very specific company it also provide
you some reports for these as well
as you can see which companies are
visiting your website
or using your application more than others
and at all of these plugins can
be found on the midterm or plugins
website at plug ins that mattel dot
org there is a massive list of
plugins that didn't make the cut unfortunately
for this session today see if you're
ever curious if you wanted to know
how you can ex
attend the capability of your matua server
have a look at the list of
plugins available there
and that alternatively you can also find
them in the marketplace section of your
matua server from there you can directly
install and activate and start using these
awesome plugins
alright and that brings us to the
end of the last segment for this
matter my camp session so we're going
to move on to some question and
answers now so if you haven't yet
had an opportunity to send some questions
through to the chat just gonna take
minutes the moderator has sent some questions
through to us on the show
that on the side as well so
we'll just have a quick look through
those questions and see if we can
answer some of them
how is it liked to work for
the miss tomoe or inner craft team
this is a question from ronan and
honestly it's been probably one of the
best work experiences that i've ever had
in my life the team is amazing
it's awesome to work in a group
of people that are us
conscious about open source mit software conscious
about being open and sharing and it's
it's really just a great company culture
overall what are the next big features
the team is working on and so
yeah there's not a lot of big
secrets when it comes to how you
know what sort of features
we're working on if you want to
know what features we're working on next
you can probably have a look at
the git hub issues page and you
can kind of see kind of looking
at those milestones and they get how
page you can kind of get a
feeling of what features are going to
be worked on next what is the
priority for those sorts of things
can we add new shortcuts with moto
mo this is actually something i'm not
one hundred per cent sure and i
don't think we have the option to
have keyboard shortcuts but that's definitely something
that i'll have a look at and
asked the team about as well
do we have any plans to develop
more documentation about how to make more
attractive teams so i'm not sure who
asked that question specifically but we do
actually have a developer's guide available on
our developer documentation on how to create
themes
obviously there are no there's not necessarily
very specific examples of what you can
do the main reason for that is
that it's it's kind of really open
if you know a little bit about
css you know a little bit about
less you can go happy and hack
away all day every day and create
really cool custom
my steams something that i may not
have mentioned earlier is that you're not
just limited to using css or less
you can also include javascript files in
your plugins to kind of extended even
further than what css or less would
allow you to do
alright linaro asks in the chatroom does
the spam prevention work retroactive to filter
out already made spam visits no so
that the the tracking spam prevention plugin
doesn't work retroactively said this is something
that you would need to install too
prevent future spam tracking requests if you
do have a very specific spam tracking
requests the best way to get rid
of that data those spam tracking requests
is to use the gdp are tools
available within moto mo and that can
be kind of useful especially if they've
for example all of the tracking requests
came from a certain ip address or
if they came from a certain country
or they track certain specific things to
your meter or instance you can use
those gdp are tools to very quickly
and easily delete all of that data
alright that's all the some of the
questions that we've got on the are
we having any plans to make the
config that he need a ph p
file accessible from the eu i know
i don't think we've got any plans
to make that config file editable from
within the eu i but
it is possible to view the config
file from the eu i do not
necessarily just limited to the config does
he need a ph be but there
is a section under the diagnostics tab
that you can actually go and have
a look at all of the settings
that are currently set either in the
global config file or the
config does he need a page p
within your matua instance the reason why
we wouldn't necessarily make it directly edit
editable from the u i is because
a lot of the settings that you
set in the config that you need
a ph pi can override some of
the settings that you might set in
your user inter
face
i just having a look for a
couple more questions do you have any
tips for solving upgrade issues sometimes the
upgrade fails and the database and core
are not the same version there have
been several questions on this in the
forum but there isn't a good solution
that's a really great question and it's
actually something that i helped one or
two customers within the last couple of
weeks as well it might be really
useful from our end just to put
that into an f a q it's
something that i've kind of been planning
to do as well but yes there
is actually a way that you can
roll back the version that is stored
in the database so
that matua can re rerun all of
those database upgrade commands so stay tuned
i dunno if you have it any
way that you can kind of keep
an eye on some of the f
a q's otherwise feel free to shoot
us an email at support admitted org
just asking about that information about those
specific step
oops and if we don't yet have
that effect you out there will be
more than happy to send that information
on to you
could you give a general definition of
what archiving means yet so archiving is
basically the process that matua uses to
kind of process all of that raw
data so as you can imagine if
you're sending hundreds of thousands of tracking
requests or hits to your
matua interface that data on it's own
isn't really useful other than just to
kind of look at in reality so
what archiving does is it takes that
raw data and it parses through every
single piece of that raw data and
that is used to then generate the
reports that you view
in your maternal instance
alright anyone else got a couple more
questions for us
alright that looks like all the questions
for today and so that means that
we're actually almost out of time i
really just wanted to say thank you
everyone for joining thank you so much
for the awesome questions that you that
you asked i hope that everybody learned
something new
you today that will help give you
success with me tomo and i'd also
like to give a massive thank you
to the volunteers that have made matua
camp possible this really is a community
driven event and none of this will
be possible without the awesome contribution of
the volunteers as well as the sponsors
have a great day everyone buy anything