Today, I will go through the basics of the Matomo Tag Manager and also the basics of
getting consent management to work together with the Matomo Tag Manager.
For those interested in the tracking of SPA applications, I will do that tomorrow.
All right, so let's look into what this is, but let's first talk a little bit about me.
As the introduction said, I've been working with analytics since 2010-ish.
I usually refer to myself as some kind of a generalist when it comes to web development.
I started working within the web industry around 2000 and have had a mix of roles.
I started off as a front-end developer, but today I'm more of a business developer,
but I still love the coding, so I can't get my fingers away from the commit messages, so to speak.
So what I usually do on my daily job is to help our clients at Digitalist with implementing
Matomo in their organizations, and that can be everything from helping out with tag management
issues or more technical deep dives or educating or training developers or whatever that needs to
learn about Matomo. So who are Digitalist? Well, we're a digital product agency that loves open
source. I think we've been contributing to different open source projects since 2005,
and our main project to contribute to has been Drupal, where we're pretty well known within the
Drupal community, the CMS, but the three, four last years we've been starting to contribute more
and more to Matomo, and we hope to do much more of that as well. What we offer as a company is,
of course, a SaaS solution for Matomo and professional consulting to help people with that.
We're also building and selling premium plugins to Matomo, so that's something we will hopefully
share more news about soon. I have a presentation about one of them tomorrow called the User
Feedback Plugin, but that's for tomorrow. So let's get into today's topic, and that is tag
management. Tag management isn't super new in the Matomo world, it is, but basically tag
management, a tag manager is a tool that helps us structure the tracking code that we can add to our
websites. Once we have it installed, it means that we can implement tracking without actually
changing code in our CMS system or on the production servers. We can do that through the tool
tag manager. Why should we use a tag manager? Well, first of all, it gives us autonomy.
We don't have to depend on developers or ops team to actually implement new tracking, and this is
actually a great thing because if you're working with tracking, it's usually a lot of fast,
short-term jobs we need to apply. We need to maybe meet a campaign that has a tight deadline or
start to track things and continuously improve what we're doing.
So tag management is great from that perspective. Tag management also gives us a better visual
structure of what we're doing on our site. So by using it, we can actually jump between websites
and learn pretty well and understand how things have been done, and we don't have to invent a
and we don't have to invent the wheel over and over again. So that means that the quality will
actually be better. And this, of course, leads to better security and quality, less loading time,
often since we don't invent the wheel, the code that is implemented through the tag manager is
fast and consistent. And, of course, we can be faster with our development and applying new
changes to our websites. The concept of tag management has three components, basically.
We talk about tags, triggers, and variables, and together with these three components, we can build
pretty much anything once we start to learn how it works. First of all, triggers are actually
connected to events in browsers. So events can be such a thing as reloading a page, clicking on
something, or if you use the scrolls, or submits a form, or basically anything that has to be with
interaction on a page or in a browser. Tags are the actual code that we are executing. And this
can also be pretty much anything. We have predefined code snippets within the tag manager
that help us, for instance, to do the Matomo tracking. But as my example here in the presentation
shows, we can basically execute any type of code, like the alert hello world. Finally, we can use
variables to fetch data from the page or the browser and use that data within our tags or
the triggers to create logic. Altogether, they create a really, really nice way to structure our
tracking. So, let's look at the next example. I'm actually going to demo how to set up tracking in
Matomo. So, I'm going to go to Matomo's tag manager, and what we're going to look at here is
the default setup for page view tracking. So, to do that, you basically have to click here to create
a new tag. You select the tag type called Matomo Analytics. And as I explained before, this actually
means that when you click on any of these, you're getting prewritten code. And if you click
on this tag, Matomo Analytics, I'm actually going to go back and click on the one I already created.
You're getting a set of predefined configurations. So, in this case, I'm going to track
data to Matomo, and I'm going to track page views, the thing we normally start with when we implement
a new website. As you can see here, I have different fields that I can change and configure,
but in this case, we're doing it really easy. The second thing I need to do here is to tell
the Matomo tag manager when to execute this code. And as you see here, I already selected
page view, and if I click on this little button, I can actually start to edit it. And this is
always, of course, when a user reloads the page, I want to send a new page view to Matomo so that
we can track that within our website. So, it's pretty simple, actually. Let's see. Do we have
any variables? Yes. In Matomo, we also have a variable that helps us to get the standard data
data that decides what to send. So, in this variable, for instance, we can
set up things like if I want to disable cookies or if I want to
send beacons, which is a quite techy setup, but we can also force requiring a consent here.
So, this is a pretty nice way to start off with. So, I'm going to go back to my presentation,
and I'm going to talk a little bit about a more detailed case, which is tracking users without
asking for consent. And the background to this task, which is pretty common, is that GDPR requires
GDPR requires us to ask for consent from users before we start to track them. And this relates
to that GDPR is describing that if you're storing personal data or if you do profiling, you need to
ask for consent. So, we're looking a bit to what that really means. So, personal data is, of course,
the IP address in many cases. But the reason why we want to do tracking without consent is that,
of course, if we start to ask consent from all the users, we will lose a lot of data.
So, depending on how your website is set up. So, the interpretation of GDPR that many organizations
do is that if we implement cookie-free tracking, we can actually track users without having the
consent, which is, of course, nice if you want to have correct data on your website. So, what is
actually profiling in Matomo? Well, when a user visits your website for the first time, we set a
cookie. And that cookie contains a little number, which is the visitor ID. And that ID is stored in
Matomo together with the data we collect. So, the next time a user visits your site, Matomo
script can find that cookie. And it will actually start adding data to the already created profile
in Matomo so that we're building a profile in Matomo. It looks like this if you look in the
interface. So, you can see here, like, there's visit number one and visit number two. And
then the data collected from that user is stored to the same profile. And this is what GDPR talks
about, that it requires a consent if you start to do that. So, the solution is, of course, to
not do profiling. And that means that when a user visits you the first time, we are not setting
persistent cookies, meaning the data stored in Matomo is connected to a session cookie only. So,
the next time the user gets there, we don't have any persistent cookie that can connect that ID
to any previous visits. So, we create a new profile in Matomo. And this is actually the
definition of profiling. So, we can avoid that through having Matomo to not set these cookies.
So, let's look into how to do this. Step by step, you need to basically disable cookies by default.
You need to identify the consent. And this is usually happening through the CMS.
So, we need to know if someone clicked the consent dialogue button or button or something similar.
And then we need to have some kind of logic to execute
some particular functions in Matomo. I will show you pretty soon.
That will, if the user has given a consent, we will actually start setting cookies. And the reason
we want to set cookies is that it's because it's sometimes nice to have that extra information we
get from cookies to be able to see recurring visits. Because if you're using Matomo without
cookies or persistent cookies, basically every user will be reported as a new visitor. And when
you're starting to analyze your application, it's often nice to know and perhaps create
segments of recurring visitors or visitors that has been to the site more than 10 times, et cetera.
So, this is, of course, nice to do if we have the consent. So, that's the background to why we
usually want to do this as well. So, first of all, you go to your Matomo configuration variable.
So, we looked at it here before. It's basically this little checkbox. So, we can click disable
cookies. And we can also check another checkbox further down. Now it's a bit up. Where we're
forcing, let's see. Okay. Now I missed that. But this one, I'm actually going to do it manually.
Sorry for being confusing. But we go by disabling cookies like this. The second step is to identify
the cookie consent from our CMS. Now I'm looking at the European Commission site. And normally we
have a button like this that says accept all cookies. And that's the behavior we want to
start looking into. So, when that happens, we want to identify this somehow. And to do so,
I usually create a variable that reads that cookie information from the browser.
And by doing so, I can create a new logic so that if the cookie is set, basically, I can
execute that we have a consent given to Matomo, which is the yes option down here. And when we're
doing so, Matomo will start setting cookies. And if we don't have the consent, or actually on every
other page view, we will run the code above that requires us to get a cookie consent.
So, that in combination with the track without cookies will give us the wanted behavior.
So, let's jump to the next step. The final step is to do a trigger, as I said, that if we have
the cookie consent, we will execute this little code. And let's look at how that looks in the...
So, what I have done here is that I have a Matomo configuration variable as we looked into before,
where I have disabled cookies. I also created a tag for several tags. The first one is require
consent. This one will always be executed. And the only thing it does is to run a custom JavaScript
saying require consent. The second logic is that if consent is given, which my trigger I talked
about is here, I'm going to execute this code. Remember cookie consent given. And the trigger
I configured in this case is that we're looking at the value from the cookie. And this one is
actually configured to work with the European Commission site. And I will show you that in a
while. It's actually a bit advanced. So, looking at this site, I have to go to code inspection.
And I have to go to code inspection. And go to our cookies. And there is actually a cookie called
CK1. And they have an array of data in this one. So, CM equals true means that we have a consent.
So, if I remove this one and reload the page, I will probably see the cookie consent again.
So, reading this one now, we have CM false. So, as long as that one is false, I will not execute
the script cookie consent given. As you see here, Matomo already stored this. I can actually remove
that cookie. And hopefully, if I reload the page, we can see that we don't get the Matomo cookies.
But as soon as I do that and reload the page, we're going to get the Matomo cookie consent
stored. And we're also setting the persistent cookies from Matomo. So, in this way, we're able
to track the consent and handle the cookieless tracking for users that hasn't been giving a
consent. Let's see. So, one thing that I can share as well is that I'm not working with the European
commission and helping them with Matomo. But instead, I am using a little plug-in in my
Chrome browser that helped me to simulate tracking on basically any site I would like to play with.
The little plug-in is called user and JavaScript and CSS. And if I click this one,
I can add both JavaScript and CSS that will be running in my browser on basically any site.
So, you can see it's connected to this domain. So, what I usually do here is that I go to the
tag manager. I go to the install code section. I grab this JavaScript. I add it to this site.
And then basically press save. And by doing so, I can also make sure that it's green up here.
I know that I will always execute this script on this site. So, that's a great way to simulate
tracking. Let's see. So, let's go back to the presentation. Yeah, we looked at the demo. And
actually, this was a pretty quick demonstration. I will do a bit more advanced
session tomorrow displaying how to track single page applications. So, right now, I'm going to
open up for questions and details about this. I hope to be able to share the presentation with
you guys afterwards. So, let's go ahead with questions.
Yeah, thank you. So, if there are any questions, please type them out now so that they can ask
them and we can answer them.
Okay. Seems to be quite, not quite. Now we'll get one question maybe.
Okay. Where to disable cookies? Good. So, when you go into the tag manager, you usually have
a variable called the Matomo configuration. And when you edit that one, scroll down,
and you will find this little check box, disabled cookies. Maybe I should do this actually from
scratch. That's actually, I'm actually going to create a new tag manager container and just do it
from an empty container. So, you can follow it step by step. So, now I have a totally empty
tag manager. So, what I usually start with is to create a Matomo tracking tag. So, I want to
track page views. I'm not going to do much more now. But before, normally here, you select the
Matomo configuration variable. So, I will click on this one. And this will actually bring up
a new variable. And pretty much everything pre-filled. I will check the disabled cookies.
And I will scroll down and just create that variable. So, now my page view tag is connected
to the Matomo configuration variable. The last thing I need to do is to create the trigger.
I will click on page view because that's when I want to fire it and create it. So,
basically, and I need to create a tag. So, if I publish this, I can give it a version name of one.
I basically have page views running. So, I have a tag executing that. I have a trigger for page
views. And in this case, I only have one variable containing the Matomo configuration. So, if I
install this code now and go back to my European Commission page and we change the JavaScript I
use, I have to remove the script tags. And we can save it. So, to see that it really works now,
I need to go to my network tab. And I usually filter my IP address. And when I reload this one,
when I reload this one, I can see that we have a Matomo PHP called and an action name. So,
I can actually see that this one is sending data to Matomo. I need to remove this one and
reload it again. Yes. So, right now, we disabled cookies for all the users. And the next step
would be to let's see. Just lost my screen there. Okay. The next step would be to
create a variable that looks at this cookie. So, let's create that variable. We create a
variable of the type. Where are we? The first party cookie. I'm going to go back to my site.
And the cookie I want to look for is this one. CCK1. So, I'm just going to name it like that.
And this is where I actually name the cookie I'm going to look into. And this cookie, in this case,
it always exists. If you have a simple solution that a lot of sites have cookies that either they
exist or not. And if that's the solution you have, you can actually set a default value here to not
set. That won't matter right now because this cookie is always set. But if you do that,
you can use that in your logic for the trigger later on. So, we'll actually write it like that.
So, first of all, now we will read that cookie on the page.
The next thing I need to do is to require the cookie consent.
So, that's a JavaScript. And I'm going to actually copy this code from my other tag manager instance.
Because now we're going to do this one. I'm just going to copy the code here. Sorry.
So, this is the current tag manager. I'm going to create a new tag of the type custom HTML.
Require consent. I'm going to paste the script here. Require consent. I can then create the
trigger. And the trigger I want to use here is doom ready. That's actually a bit before
before our page view is triggered to make sure that we're requiring it before the page view is
sent. So, creating this tag. Now we're requiring consent. And the last thing would be to
set the logic for the consent given. So, I'll show you how that works. I'm just going to copy
the code here again. So, going back, creating a new tag of the type custom HTML. Now we'll paste
it here. And now to the perhaps more trickier part. Now we need to create this custom trigger.
So, we're going to do it on doom ready. And in this case, I want to look at my previously created
variables. I'm going to go to custom. And here you find my variable called cck1, which was the
cookie consent cookie. So, now to the logic. The easy solution is normally to
make it like this. If your solution is that the cookie doesn't exist until you have a consent.
And you remember I gave this variable a default value. So, if you do it like this, not set.
So, you're actually going to do a negative logic here. So, if it doesn't equal not set,
we know that we have a consent. But in our example here, the cookie always existed. So,
I had to create a little bit more advanced regular expression to do that matching. So,
I had to do a regular expression with not matches to make it work. So, that would be
the where do we have it? Not matches regular expression. So, it can't say CM false basically.
I could actually write it equal CM true as well. So, creating this tag should
be what we need. And if I do this, I publish it.
If we go back to this site, let's delete this and reload.
Let's remove that as well.
Okay. So, now I'm looking. And it seems like we're not having the Matomo cookie set.
We can see that CM false. And if I click accept on this one, we see that the value changes to CM
true. If I reload now, we can also see that we get the Matomo cookie consent. So, that's how
it works basically. Let's see if we have more questions.
So, another question is if it is possible to separate or look into users who didn't give consent?
And well, no, not really. You can only see users that are new. But that is not necessarily the
same thing as giving a consent. What you could do is probably to create a dimension in Matomo
and store the consent given value. And do it that way.
Okay. Thank you. Another question or something that has been discussed in the chat is if there's
a way not to write a version name for every published version of the tags?
Yeah. So, I think I showed you. So, when I publish something new, if you add a number here to
Matomo, it will actually start counting up automatically. So, if I publish now, I always
start by just writing one. So, every time I create a new version and publish a new release,
it will actually be added automatically. So, now I created a new version, probably if you see it
in the version number, it's number three. And if I click create new version, it will automatically
be four. So, that's actually a pretty nice one. And then you don't have to write in the descriptions.
Thank you. Another one. If I go back to an earlier published version, are both the tags,
triggers, and variables back to the earlier versions?
Yeah. So, you can actually, if you go to the version history, you can actually see which
version that is published live. And I should probably do this one. Oh, yeah. Now I'm looking
at different Tag Manager accounts, I think. This is a bit, but yeah. So, here you have more versions.
So, basically you can go down here and just click on this little icon and publish
the old version like this. So, now this version will be running in your live production.
So, that's pretty easy. What I would like to see is a better way to do a diff between versions
to do that right now. At least as far as I know, you basically have to export the configuration
here. So, that's also a nice thing. You can click on this little icon and that will actually give
you a JSON file containing the current version. But it would be nice to have an interface
really telling us what's happening. All right. Anything else?
Okay. Another thing that has been discussed in the chat before, I don't know if the answer is
enough yet. It would be what's the regulation in Sweden regarding the use of Matomo?
There is no regulation in Sweden in terms of Matomo. There is GDPR and there is
some other laws in regards to privacy. So, right now it's a lot of discussions on how to interpret
it. What's the judgment to do? As I think that most of the European Union is discussing.
So, there are no real statements about Matomo. But what we see is that basically the whole
public sector in Sweden is leaving Google Analytics and most of them are moving to Matomo.
The discussion I have with a lot of them right now is whether this solution I showed you today
is legally okay or not to actually track users without the consent or not.
And that refers more to the cookie law than GDPR.
Thank you for that. I think that's all the questions that have been asked until now.
I'm going to wait a few more seconds just to see if another one comes up.
It would seem that is not the case. So, once again, thank you for your talk. And if there
are any other questions, the chat stays open as with the other talks. We'll be available for 10
more minutes to answer questions or have a dialogue in the chat. Thank you and have a good evening.
Thank you. You too.