today I will go through the
basics over the Matomo tag manager
and also the basics of all they're
getting consent management to work together with
the matomo tag manager air for those
interesting in the tracking
of s p a applications i will
do that tomorrow ah alright so
let's look into what this is but
let's first talk a little bit of
on me as the introduction said i've
been working week a analytics since two
thousand and ten each and i usually
refer to myself as some kind of
a generalists and when it comes to
web development i started working within the
web
the industry around two thousand and has
had a mix of roles or i'd
have started off as a friend front
end developer but
today i'm more of a business developer
but i still love the coding so
i can't get my fingers away from
from the commit messages so to speak
and so what i usually do on
my daily job is to help our
clients at the littlest with employ
lamenting hematoma in their organizations and that
can be everything from helping out with
tag management issues or a more technical
deep dives or educating or training developers
or whatever that needs to learn about
moto mod soul who are digitally well
where digital practice
agency that loves open source i think
we've been contributing to different open source
projects since two thousand and five
under our main project to contribute to
has been drupal where we are pretty
well known within the drupal community the
seamus but the three four last years
we've been starting to contribute more and
more to matter more and we hope
to do much more of that as
well as what we offer as a
the company is of course a sauce
solution for matomo and
professional consulting to help people with that
and we're also building and selling premium
plugins to matomo so that's something we
will hopefully share more news about soon
i have a presentation about one of
them tomorrow called the use of feedback
planet but that's for tomorrow so let's
go
get into today's topic and that is
tag management tag management isn't super new
in the matomo world it is but
basically tag management's the attack manager is
a tool that help us structure the
tracking code that we can add to
a websites
at once we have it installed it
means that we can implement tracking without
actually changing code in our cms system
or or on the production servers we
can do that through the tool type
an id tag manager
why should we use a tag manager
well first of all the gifts of
autonomy and we don't have to depend
on developers or ops team to actually
implement new tracking and this is actually
a great thing because if you're working
with tracking it's usually a lot of
fasts or
short term jobs we need to apply
we need to maybe meet a campaign
that has a tight deadline or start
to track things and continuously improve what
we're doing fatigue management is rate from
that perspective and tag management all again
gives us a better visual strict structure
of what we're doing on our site
so by using it we can actually
jump between websites and learn pretty well
and understand how things has been in
in done and we don't have to
reinvent the wheel over and over
again so that means that the air
the quantity will actually be better
and this of course leads to better
security and quality and less loading time
often since we don't even have the
meal there the code that is implemented
through the documentaries fast and consistent
and of course we can be faster
with our development and applying youth changes
to our websites
at the concepts of tag management tag
management has three components basically we talk
about tags triggers and variables and together
with these three components we can build
pretty much anything once we start to
learn how it works
first of all triggers are actually connected
to events in browsers so events can
be such a thing as reloading a
page clicking on something or if he
uses scrolls or submits a forum or
basically anything that has to be with
interaction on a page or in a
browser
her tags are the actual code that
we are executing and this can also
be pretty much anything we have predefined
code snippets within the tag manager that
help us for instance to do that
matomo tracking but at as my example
here in
presentation shows we can basically execute any
type of code like the alert hello
world
finally we can use variables to fetch
data from the page or the browser
and use that data within our tags
or the triggers to create logic altogether
they create a really really nice way
to to structure our tracking
so
let's look at the next example
i'm actually gonna demo
how to set up
tracking in motto so i'm going to
go to bhutan was tag manager and
what we're going to look at here
is the defaults setup or form
a page view tracking so to do
that you basically have to click here
to create a new tag you select
at the tag type called matomo analytics
and as i explained before this actually
means that when you click on any
of these
you're getting a pre-written code and if
you click on this tag motto wanna
lyrics i'm actually gonna go back and
click on the one i already created
or you're getting a set of predefined
configurations from this case i'm going to
track it up too
matomo and i'm going to attract page
views the thing we normally start with
when we we implement a new website
as you can see here i have
been different fetus and i can change
and configure but in this case we're
doing it really easy and that the
second thing i need to do here
is to tell
the matomo tag when you're when to
execute this code and as you see
here i already selected page view and
if i click on this still about
and i can actually start edit it
and this is a
of course when a bow user reloads
the page i want to send a
new page view to matomo so that
we can track track that we didn't
our website
so it it's pretty simple actually
yeah let's see do we have any
variables yes in moto when we also
have a variable that helps us to
to get the standard data
and add to that that decides what
to send so in this example for
instance we can add
set up things like if i want
to disable cookies or if i want
to
sand the beacons are witches are quite
techy and set up but we can
also force requiring a consent here
so this is a pretty nice way
to to start off with so i'm
going to go back to my presentation
and i'm going to talk a little
bit about a more
detailed case which is tracking uses without
asking for consent and the background to
this task which is pretty common is
that gdp r requires us to ask
for consent
from useless before we start to track
them
and that this relates to that gdp
earth is
describing that if you're restoring personal data
or if you do profiling you need
to ask for consent we're looking a
bit too what that really means and
but
yup so so personal data is of
course the ip address in many cases
but but the the reason why when
going to do tracking without consent is
that of course if we stopped to
ask consent from all the users we
will loose a lot of data
depending on where your how your website
is set up
so
interesting interpretation of gdp aren't that many
organizations do is that if we implement
cookie free tracking we can actually
track users without having the consent
which is of course nice if you
if you want to have correct data
on your website so what is actually
profiling in moto mobile when a user
visits your website for the first time
we set a cookie and that cookie
contains a digital number
which is the visitor id
and that
id is stored in moto more together
with the data we collect though the
next time a user visits your site
a matomo script can find that cookie
and it will actually start adding data
to the already created profile in matomo
so that we're building a profile in
in
in matomo it looks like this if
you if you look into it in
the interface so you can see here
like there's the visit number one and
basic number two and the data collected
from that user is stored to the
same profile and this is what gdp
year talks about that your it requires
a console
sent if you started to do that
so the solution is of course to
not do profiling and that means that
whenever use envisages the first time we're
not setting persistent cookies meaning the data
stored in matomo is connected to efficient
cooking only so the next
time to use it gets there we
don't have any persistent cookie that can
connect that id add to any previous
visits so we create a new profile
in matomo and this is actually the
definition of of profiling
so we can avoid that through having
a matomo to not set these cookies
so let's look into how to do
this
step by step you need to basically
disable cookies by default
you need to identify the consent and
this is usually happening through the cms
so we need to know if someone
clicked the consent
dialog button or button was similar
and then we need to have some
kind of logic to execute
some particular function similar to my will
always show you pretty soon
that will if the user has
even a consent we will actually start
setting cookies and and the reason we
want to set cookies is that
that is because
it's sometimes nice to have that extreme
for medicine we get from cookies to
be able to see recurring visits
because if you're using my told me
without cookies or persistent cookies basically every
user will be reported as a new
visitor and when you're starting to analyze
your your your application it's often nice
to know and perhaps create segments of
a recall
foreign visitors or beast visitors that has
been to the site more than ten
times etc so this is of course
nice to do if we have the
consent so that's the background to to
why we usually want to do this
as well
so first of all you go to
your matomo configuration variable we looked at
it here before it's basically
this little checkbox so we can click
disable cookies
and we can also
and check another checkbox further down now
it's a bit up where we're forcing
let's see
okay now i missed that but this
one
are actually going to do money sorry
for being confusing but we will by
disabling cookies like it's the second step
is to identify the cookie consent from
our cms now i'm looking at the
european commission sites and know
normally we have a button like this
access accept all cookies and that's the
behavior we want to start looking into
so
when that happens we want to identify
this somehow and to do so i
usually create a variable that reads that
cookie information from the browser and by
doing looking create a new logic so
that if the cookie is set to
basically
i can
execute that we have a consent given
to matomo which is the yes option
down here and when we are doing
so not only will start setting cookies
and
if we don't have the consent or
actually on every
other patriots will run the code above
that requires us to get a cookie
consent
so that in combination with the attract
without cookies will give us the wanted
behavior
so
let's jump to the next the the
final
step is to do a trigger as
i said that if we have a
cookie consent we will execute this little
code and let's look at how that
that looks in that
so what i have done here is
that i ever
matomo configuration variable as we looked into
before where i have disabled cookies
i also created a tag
for several tags the first one is
require consent this one will always be
executed and the only thing it does
is to run accustomed javascript saying require
consent
the second logic if that
if
consent is given which might trigger i
talked about is here i'm going to
execute this code remember cookie consent given
and the trigger i configured in this
case
if that we're looking at their value
from the cookie and this one is
actually configured to work with the european
commission site and i will show you
that
in a while it's actually a bit
advanced so looking at this site
and i had to go to code
inspection
and go to our cookies
and there is actually a cookie called
c
c k one and they have an
array of data in this one so
c m equals true means that we
have a consent so if i remove
this one and reload the page would
probably see the cookie consent again so
reading this one now
we have cm force so as long
as step one is false i will
not execute the script cookie consent given
as if the hematoma all are distort
stored this i can i can remove
that cookie and hopefully if i reload
the page we can see that we
don't get them
tormo cookies but as soon as i
do that
and reload the page
we're going to get the matomo cookie
consent stored and we're also setting
the persistent cookies
from all on this way we're able
to to track
the consent and and handle the
the cookie cookie less tracking for uses
that hasn't been giving a consent
let's see
so one thing that i can share
as well is that i'm not working
with the european commission and hopefully helping
them with potomac but instead i'm using
a dental plugin in my chrome browser
that helped me to simulate tracking on
basically
any site i would like to play
with and the lily plugin is called
you sir and your user javascript and
css and if i click this one
i will be i can add and
both javascript and css that will be
running in my browser on basically any
site so you can see it connect
it's connected to this domain so what
i usually do here is that i
go to the tag manager i go
to the install code section i grabbed
this javascript
i added to the site and then
basically press save and by doing so
i can also make sure that it's
green up here i know that i
will always execute this script on this
site so that's a great great way
to assimilate
tracking
let's see
so let's go back to the presentation
yet we looked up the demo and
actually exposed to a pretty quick
demonstration i will do a bit more
advanced
it's a bit more more of an
efficient tomorrow displaying how to track single
page application saw right now i'm going
to open up for questions and details
about this i hope to be able
to share the presentation with you guys
afterwards
so let sir
let's go ahead with questions
yeah thank you if any questions please
let them know
so that they glossed over because of
them
okay seems to be quite quiet no
get one question maybe
okay where to disable cookies good
so when you go into the tag
manager you usually have a variable called
the moto m all a conflagration
and when you edit that one i
scroll down and you will find this
little checkbox disable cookies
well maybe i should do this actually
from scratch that's actually i'm actually going
to create a new tag manager container
and just do it from an empty
container
so you can follow it step by
step
so now i have a totally empty
tag manager so what i usually start
with is to create a tomo tracking
tag so i want to crap track
page views
i'm not going to do much more
not now but before normally hear you
select that the atomic confirmation variable solid
click on this one
this will actually bring up a new
variable and pretty much everything prefilled i
would check the disabled cookies
and i will scroll down and just
creates a variable so now my page
view tag is connected to the atomic
configuration variable
the last thing i need to do
is to create the trigger
i will click on page view because
that's when i want to fire and
created so basically
and i need to create a tag
so if i published if i can
keep it to version of one
i basically have patriots running so we
have a tag
executing that i have a trigger or
page use and in this case i
only have one variable containing the moto
configuration so if i install this code
now
and go back to my european commission
page and with the change to javascript
or use up to remove the script
tags
and we can save it
so to see that it really works
now i need to go to my
network tired and i usually shelter my
ip address and when i reload this
one i can see that we have
a moto mod pizza pie called and
an action name so i can actually
see that this one is sending data
to matomo
but a cookie store links i need
to remove this one time reloaded again
yes so right now we disabled cookies
for all users
and the next step would be to
yeah
the seat
just lost my screener okay the next
step would be to
create a variable that looks at this
cookie
so let's create that variable we create
the variable of the type
or are we the first party cookie
i'm going to go back to my
site and the cook i want to
look for is this one cck one
you're just going to name it like
that and this is where we're actually
name of the the cookie i'm going
to look into
and this cookie in this case it
always exists if you had a simple
solution that
a lot of sites have cookies that
either they exist or not and if
that's the solution you have you can
actually set a default value here to
not set at won't matter right now
because these cookies always but if you
do that you can use that in
your logic for the cheddar later
m and some will actually write it
like that so first of all now
we will read that cookie on the
page
the next thing i need to do
is to require the cookie consent so
that said java scripts and i'm going
to
shall i copy this code from my
other tag mentor instance just now
welcome to the swamp the scammer copied
culture sorry
back so it is the current tag
matter i'm going to create a new
tag of the type custom html
red wire called sam i'm going to
paste
the script here required consent i can
then create a trigger
and the trigger i want to use
her is doom ready that's actually bit
before
our page series is triggered to make
sure that we're requiring it before the
patriots sent so creating this tag
now we're requiring consent and the last
thing would be to
set the logic for the consent given
i would show you how that works
and you're just going to copy the
code handwritten
though going back to creating a new
tag
while the type custom html
read ma'am there
even
now replaced it here
and now to the perhaps more tricky
part now need to create this custom
trigger
we're going to do it until i'm
ready and in this case i want
to look at my previously created variables
i'm going can go to custom and
here you find my
a variable called cct one which was
the cookie consent or cookie
so now to the logic
corn sunk given that nice solution is
normally too
make it like this if your solution
is that the cookies
doesn't exist until you have a consent
he remembered i gave this variable a
default value for if you do it
like this knocked said
so you're actually going to do a
negative logic here so if it doesn't
equal not set we know that we
have a consent but in our example
here they actually the cook crooked always
existed for her to create that a
little bit more advanced
regular expression to do that matching and
so i had to do a regular
expression
and with not matches to make it
work so that would be
where do we have it
not much just regular expression
so it can't face cm or false
basically
may trigger
i could actually write it the equal
see him too as well so creating
this tag
should be what we need and if
i do this i publish it
the if we go back to the
site
delete this and reload
the remembered as well
okay so now i'm looking and it
seems like we're not having their matomo
cookies set and we can see that
see him false and if i click
accept on this one we'd see that
the value changes to see him true
if i reload
now we can also see that we
get the limit on the cookie consent
so that's how it works basically
let's see if we have more questions
so while another question is if it
is possible with this setup to separate
or look into users who didn't give
consent
or
well no not really nah you can
only a fee
you says that are new but that
if not necessarily the same thing as
keeping your consent and what you could
do is prohibitive to the store create
the dimensioning matomo
and the store the consent given by
you
and do it that way
cave thank you
another question or sup it has been
discussed in the ted is if there's
a way not to write a personal
name for a published burst version of
the text
yeah
so i think i might i showed
you so when i do i'm gonna
publish something new if you add a
number here too much more it will
actually start counting up automatically though if
i publish now i always thought by
just writing one now so ever
the time i create a new version
of promise publish a new release it
will actually be an added automatically so
now i created a new version properly
if you see it in the version
number it's number three and if i
click create new version it will automatically
be four so that's actually a pretty
nice one
and then you don't have to write
in the descriptions
thank you
another one if i go back to
the earlier published version above the tags
triggers and variables back to the earlier
versions
yeah so you can actually have a
if you go to diversion history you
can actually see which version that is
published live than i should probably read
this one oh yeah now i'm looking
at different segment or accounts i think
this is a bit but yeah so
here you have marked more for version
so basically you can go down here
and just kick on this little icon
and publish the old version like this
so now this version will be running
in your light production so that that's
pretty easy there what i would like
to see is a better way to
do a diff between versions to do
that right now at least as far
as i know you basically have to
export the configuration so that's also nice
thing you can click on this little
icon
and that will actually give you a
jason file containing the current version but
it would be nice to have an
interface that really telling us what's happening
alright anything else
cape another thing that has been discussed
in the in the thread before the
notice that the answer is curse is
enough yet it would be worth regulation
in sweden regarding the use of adobo
and there is no regulation in sweden
in terms of of matomo there is
t de pr and there is some
other laws are in regards to privacy
so right now it's a lot of
discussions on how to interpret them
i thought what was the judgment to
do as i think that most of
the european union is discussing there are
no reading lamp statements about matomo but
what we see is that basically the
whole public sector in sweden if leaving
google analytics and most of them are
moving
two matomo
the discussion i had with a lot
of them right now is whether the
solution i showed you today
is legally ok or not to to
actually track users without the consent
or not
and that refers more to the cookie
law than gdp are
thank you for that and i think
that's all the questions that have been
asked until now i'm going to wait
a few more seconds just to see
if if another one comes up but
it would seem that is not the
case and so once again thank you
for a thought
if the any item requested the ted
stays openness as with yellow ducks
i will be available for ten more
minutes to answer questions or have a
dialogue in the chat is on then
ticket and have a good edit youtube