Hello everyone, thank you for joining this session and sorry for the technical issues.
Now we will welcome Nathan, who is the founder and director of the Guardian Project, an award-winning
open source mobile security collaborative.
In this talk, Using Clean Insights for Privacy-Deserving Analytics Based on Matomo, you will learn
how to use the Clean Insights SDK from the Guardian Project to maximum privacy for your
users.
Let's hear Nathan's talk for more.
Great, thank you Silva, thank you Lukas and everyone who's organized MatomoCamp.
We're really excited to be here with you and to start more collaboration and just to learn
from all of you how you are using Matomo to achieve better privacy and control of measurement
and analytics.
This is kind of near and dear to our heart at Guardian Project, which is an effort that
I started almost 12 years ago when smartphones were becoming very interesting and possible,
but I also quickly realized that while these devices that we carry around in our pockets
are quite powerful, they were also clearly tracking devices as well as the potential
of apps, which I've been working in mobile since for 20 years plus back to the Palm Pilot
and Apple Newton, that the fact of all of this binary code running on these little devices
and these little supercomputers in our pockets was going to cause a lot of trouble.
So at Guardian Project, our focus has been initially, from the beginning, was saying
how can we bring great privacy technologies that exist in open source and in desktop computing
to mobile devices that we didn't even know if that was possible.
So something like Tor or PGP or OTR encryption for chat, could you run that on a phone?
And people didn't believe that you could, and I thought that you could.
So one of the things we're best known for is bringing Tor to Android and more recently
iOS with Orbot, the version of Tor that runs on your phone that can provide a VPN and through
the Tor anonymity network.
So there's a case where we're very clearly connected to confidentiality and privacy concerns
and work with one of the leading projects in the world on that effort.
Another piece of the puzzle that we quickly realized in the mobile space was needed was
app distribution beyond what the gatekeepers of, say, Google or Apple or others provide
in that much like Debian, the Debian system is really built upon the process of a community
building and curating packages and distributing those and ensuring that you have good quality
free and open source software.
We needed that for Android.
And the FDroid project had already existed, to be clear.
We did not found it, but it was something that we really appreciated and wanted to support
and have become a big part of through one of my main collaborators, Hans Christoph Steiner.
So we're really proud of the work we've done and supporting that effort for privacy, you
know, an app store that actually tells you, hey, this app is tracking you.
You may not want to install it as an example.
And that also itself doesn't track you.
Another piece of work we've done in the middle there, the icon is called Proof Mode.
And this is work we've done with Witness, which is a human rights organization focused
on gathering eyewitness reports through video and photos and media captured on phones.
And they had the vision that now there's cameras everywhere in every pocket and what can we
do about that?
And of course, many people there might think, oh, we need more tracking and analytics and
surveillance of every photo and every picture because we need to use this as evidence for
justice.
But that's tricky, you know, we don't, yes, maybe we want some of our things we capture
on our phones to be used to help people, but we don't want ourselves to be part of the
sort of panopticon surveillance state of surveillance infrastructure in all times.
Depending on that, we built an app called Haven with the well-known privacy activist
Edward Snowden, who, again, had this kind of interesting idea of like, could you use
your phone as a personal security device to monitor physical spaces, like if you're a
reporter, a journalist, an activist to monitor a place like a home or an office when you're
not there?
Or could it be a kind of a watchdog or a, you know, I often think like a small robot
like R2D2 that is on your side and helps monitor and protect you as opposed to a Skynet type
phone.
Anyway, Snowden had this idea and we've worked through it and built something called Haven,
which is quite interesting.
And lastly, we've been in recent years working with trade unions and organized labor in many
countries around a project called Weclock, where workers are saying, I want my data about
my work day.
I don't want the corporation or the on-demand platform to be the only one who's tracking
me.
Like, there's value in me knowing about my own day and then I should have the power to
share that data with others to collectively organize and use the power of that data.
So these are all the kind of dances and investigations and things we've been doing around who should
measure, who should have analytics, who should have this data and why and where, and how
when you get this very either precious asset of gold or toxic asset of, you know, oil or
how do you take care of it appropriately?
And yeah, we're very proud of that work and we have a great, a lot of great relationships
in the space around privacy, security, open-source software, and this is some of some of the
team and, you know, Benjamin Earhart in the top middle there is based in Austria is been
real lead on the Clean Insights project, as well as a lot of our work with Tor, so I want
to give him a shout out.
We also have Kerry Winfrey, who's thinks about consent and the user experience around consent
and how we engage users with more than just a pop-up box, so we'll be talking about that
today.
I mentioned Hans Steiner, who works a lot with F-Droid and Debian and reproducible builds.
Dr. Gina Helfrich has been a supporter, funder, mentor, organizer, and really thinks about
equity and, again, the sustainability of open-source and how measurement is part of that.
And then Ian Lermont, who has worked at Tor on measurement, works in Debian and works
is just great on infrastructure, DevOps, and a lot of other really important pieces to
this solution.
So a little while ago, I got inspired and wrote a manifesto around Clean Insights that
was inspired by this brand of soap we have called Dr. Bronner's Soap, which is quite
old, maybe over nearly 80 years or something.
And on the soap bottle, there's all of these slightly creative words around what the soap
is about.
And I thought, well, if he can write such great lyrical prose about soap, maybe I could
write something around our work and put it on an interesting product that people can
read every morning.
And I did, and we actually make coffee that is part of our sort of instigation, our hope
to be a catalyst, and you can read this manifesto and more on the link there, cleaninsights.org
slash beans, which gives you a sense of, yeah, this is a little bit crazy, but it's also,
we really do want to change, beyond just our software, we want to change some ideas and
thinking about measurement and analytics and privacy and how it's done.
And we need a manifesto to do this, and also we need lots of coffee.
So if you want to join us, you'll see, and you go to that link, that you can actually
get free coffee.
We have a distribution network, nearly global, of our insightful beans, and we hope that
every morning when you're making coffee, you'll read our manifesto and think a little bit
more about this.
And it's important.
This is really important, and I'll go through this more in my talk about why and how it
impacts our whole lives.
But free coffee if you sign up for a meeting as a follow-up to this talk, so that's the
enticement.
This work for me and us as a team began a project I was in at Harvard University.
I'm based in Boston, so it's nearby, and I'm an affiliate fellow now at the Berkman-Kline
Center for Internet and Society there.
And we had a sort of a 12-week workshop called Assembly, where we were meant to take some
ideas and put them into code.
And my colleagues on my team there, my cohort, were from Apple, Google, Square, and the UN,
and then myself.
And we brainstormed a lot of use cases, and fortunately my need emerged, which was I have
all of these apps and technologies and solutions and communities that I'm trying to help, but
I'm afraid to measure them, because I feel like there isn't a solution out there yet
that can uphold the privacy kind of compact we've made with them, and that I want to know
more about what's working and what's not working, but I don't want to do anything that would
harm them.
And so this team took it seriously, and it was really a brilliant group, and kind of
we kick-started, so to speak, the first implementation of Clean Insights, and we also started by
looking at what was happening in the market.
And we saw that often, not just in apps and websites, but you have things like the emergence
of smart cars, of machine learning-based platforms, where there's so much measurement analytics
going in order to make the self-driving better, to make the car better, to make the product
better, whatever.
But then, so often, that same data was being used against customers, journalists, people
inquiring about the product, right?
And so this was a case where a journalist had written an article, a critical of Tesla,
and then Elon Musk went and pulled out all of the data from that journalist's drive
and said, well, this is what you did here, and this is your turn here, and you went too
fast here, and this is how you drove wrong, right?
And that was kind of, I know there's lots of details in there, but it's pretty shocking
to me that the corporation could do that, take that data and use it back against their
critic so easily in real time.
And that's something that was meant to be beneficial to the customer who was being used
to harm them or to counter their claims.
And this has happened in a number of cases around driving and accidents and other court
cases with some of the tech in Tesla.
There are also other cases where someone was a criminal, and in this case, there was a
homeowner said his house burnt down, but in fact, turned out to be arson.
And the way they discovered it was arson was they found out he had a pacemaker, and they
extracted data from his pacemaker that maybe he didn't even know was there to show that
his story wasn't right about when he was sleeping.
And this, I mean, this is like the most dystopic, like the thing keeping you alive in your body,
your cybernetic implant.
The police are jacking into it and sucking out data in order to like, you know, convict
you.
It's criminal, sure, but you know, obviously, there's a slippery slope.
And the more and more that we have technology in our bodies, how and when can it be used
against you?
You know, and I know, as a small aspect of this, many in the US, at least, there's programs
called wellness programs where you get to a free Fitbit, and then it taps into your
company's systems.
And if you wear it, you get some coupon or credit or bonus or something, because you're
proving you're healthy, right?
Or yeah, and so what next?
You know, after that in the workplace, and, you know, we know, already know that Amazon
and others are using kind of, again, things that are supposed to benefit you to improve
your life, to improve the service are being used against you often.
Now, there's some highlights, and I, we had the chance, you know, through this, the program
at Harvard to work with Professor Cynthia Dwork, and there's people thinking about really,
you know, new kinds of maths in the order of, you know, what end to end encryption and
kind of the work there has produced.
And there's similar work around statistical privacy and computing data that, you know,
we're inspired by and that we're hoping to work towards.
And, you know, we have dabbled in, but this is sort of like, you know, there is something
on the horizon here.
There's many things on the horizon, and we were kind of able to, you know, tap into some
of that thinking.
We also, you know, saw that what we were doing isn't just a activist cyberpunk, cypherpunk,
you know, dream.
This is something that Apple was actually already implementing as an example, because
they wanted to know what emojis were popular, but they didn't want to log every single thing
you were typing, because they understood that that was a toxic asset and not something they
wanted to hold on to.
But they needed to know, you know, just how popular the poop emoji was, so they could
decide where to put it in the order of emojis.
But that actually had a benefit without harm, so it could work.
So you know, we have, we knew that the problem was monumental.
We knew that, like, there were some possibilities.
And I should also say, you know, back then, with, you know, Pewick and then Matomo, like,
we were always inspired by this work in this community, building open source self-hosted
analytics that, you know, kind of fit in the world of the web that we believe in, in terms
of decentralized technologies and self-hosting.
And we always were like, look, these guys are doing it.
This team is producing products that people are starting to adopt, you know, and could
we build something like that or build on it, right?
And so the seeds were already there for connecting the work we're doing with the Matomo community.
Now, most recently, you know, in the last year, we've also seen that there's continued
to be kind of big gaffes and missteps and problems with even beloved software and open
source community.
I love Audacity.
I'm a huge fan.
I've been a fan for a long time.
And you know, we saw a real misstep by this new parent company that acquired the code
or the team.
I don't know all the details.
But the point is, there's still a lot of lack of awareness around, like, why would it be
bad to just drop in, you know, permacookies and UUIDs and commercial toolkits into this
product?
Like, that's what we do.
That's what everybody does, right?
There's still a basic, huge, actually, chasm to cross around what is okay, what is okay
to do, you know, why shouldn't we?
And even in the human rights community, even in the Harvard community, people just drop
in Google Analytics.
And I know that's a thing that you all are working on and probably have a lot more experience
in how to get people to understand the other possibilities and what can be done there.
And that's part of our work, especially in the open source community.
We also see this continued kind of attack on users around conflating usability improvements
with advertising, tracking for advertising.
And I think that is a big thing that gets still combined quite a bit where you say,
oh, we need your help to do X, Y, and Z and make this better.
But then that data is, you know, combined for other purposes.
And again, if we are building software for human rights, humanitarian purposes, and then
this kind of gets introduced in the process where we say, oh, you have to use this other
tool and then it's going to track you, it's an overwhelming kind of number of data points
start being collected on people we're trying to help.
And you know, I don't, kudos to Apple for what they've been, you know, some of the moves
they've made have been really interesting with injecting into the user experience around
consent a new model, you know, and I think people are starting to respond and it's interesting
to see how it's impacted companies like Facebook.
And then, you know, with the pandemic, you know, we saw a lot of, and in recent years,
emergence of smart kind of civic and health technology, you know, be it, you know, measuring
people in cities, measuring people around each other, you know, having more data about,
you know, COVID and testing and having more public infrastructure, like in New York City,
these Wi-Fi hotspots that are meant to provide people without access to the internet, you
know, free Wi-Fi and Chromebooks and all of this stuff and, you know, we've been through
a lot and, you know, I hope all of you, you know, are doing well and your families are
well and that, you know, we're all on the road to a better, brighter day, but there's
been a lot of kind of changes in, again, what is happening in our society around infrastructure
and, you know, on the one hand, there's horrific security, which is a different topic for most
of these things, but on the other hand, you know, again, what is, what are you collecting
and why and when what data is collected, how long do you retain it and all of this that
I think is very different country to country as well, so I want to recognize that based
on different regulations, but there's still that vision, like if we just knew everything,
everything would be okay. So, you know, back to our core story, we have a lot of these
users that we want to help authentically to make our software that doesn't track them
and doesn't harm them better, but we don't and we haven't been and we needed to figure
out a way to do that. And so there's a lot of others that are in the same quandary and
that we work with and that we've been trying to provide a solution for in our space and
I'm here today to kind of share that work and see maybe there's broader adoption possibility.
So as I said, the Tor project has actually done a lot of thinking about this and they
are a big inspiration with their metrics portal, which is completely public and it's so interesting
that an anonymity system actually has the best measurement and analytics system as part
of it, but they figured out how to do it. They found that compromise and that way to
do it without copying their users and they've communicated and it's a kind of a key, very
transparent piece of their system to say is Tor working? How many people are using it?
What's the throughput? Where is our infrastructure located? So all of these things are there
and they continue to do this and really have been excellent. There's others like the Open
Observatory of Network Interference and other groups doing measurement that we take inspiration
from. We also did outreach and a research project that's published on cleaninsights.org
and through partner sites with groups like KeyPass, Cubes, TunnelBear, Lease Authority,
Syphon, Umbrella, a bunch of different projects to say, hey, how do you feel? What are you
doing with measurement and how are you? If we could offer more, would you take it? And
this is the big question really in how they interact with their users and what they expect.
So we were excited to collaborate and there's a lot to learn from that report. And part
of it was also that fed into a symposium we held last year and we hope to hold another
one next year that really brought us together into a lot of the questions around consent
and what should they know and what should you know and how should you measure it?
So out of all of this, finally, getting to the point here, we decided to build some software
and I mentioned my collaborators earlier and we said, look, can we actually build something
that... And we had tinkered since 2017 on different little pieces and trying things,
but I think we started to get a much clearer idea and a specification of what we would
use in a toolkit for measurement and what we would need as part of that. And a big part
of it was just this idea, again, I mentioned the idea of toxic assets and liability and
how do we separate that risk from the actual thing we want to know? And so our model is
not to log everything and then figure it out later, but it's to ask specific questions
and measure specific things and do edge client side processing in browsers, in mobile apps
and then submit the data in a way that is as clean as possible. So some of the basic
kind of guiding principles is around that, but we have our displayed here and we work
through a variety of mechanisms to achieve these things about aggregating and averaging
and pointed focus data collection, measurement windows of time so you don't get specific
timestamps, getting consent to opt in and how we explain what's going to be measured.
This is all part of what Clean Insights is designed to do. And a bit of a different view
of this, I should mention at this point, we decided very early, we don't want to build
our own backend system. We want to focus on our client side SDKs. And so we chose Matomo
as the sort of infrastructure we wanted to integrate with the analytics and visualization
and kind of long term or short term storage of data. And it's been great. And it's also
interesting because many organizations want to use Matomo for their basic web analytics,
for their web page, for their marketing still. And that's fine. What we're talking about
are applications and infrastructure and specific interactions. And so it actually works well
together to say, oh yeah, set up Matomo. We'll run it for you. Drop in the JavaScript in
your website. Let's tune it for privacy. There's a lot of great settings in Matomo. We love
for that. And then for your app, for your other things, we'll use Clean Insights on
top of that. And they get this really great combined view of kind of what they're used
to with something new. And we've been really happy about that. And so a lot of that backend,
I'll talk about the privacy proxy in a moment, but we have this client side SDKs that are
configured and have measurements of events and views that have a bit of processing in
the storage queue and then are sent at a certain period back to this privacy proxy we built.
And then that goes into Matomo. So as of today on GitLab and on cleaninsights.org, we have
actual SDKs that have shipped and are very exciting to, I'm proud that they're there
and we're integrating in applications as we speak for lots of languages. And I think we
actually also have the Rust SDK is our newest one. And I know Rust is emerging in many environments
as like the most secure way you can build something that is a binary kind of application.
But we support server applications through Python. We support Apple, Android, JavaScript.
So there's lots of ways to start dabbling in it and using our code in different environments.
And then I'll talk a bit more about Matomo proxy. So this is all on our website. Everything's
through GitLab, published in the places you'd expect for dependencies and so on. So very
easy to integrate. A piece early on that we realized we needed to achieve some of our
goals was a privacy proxy in front of Matomo. And this is what our SDK speaks to in order
to interact with the data in the way we collect it and then put that into Matomo in the appropriate
way. So this isn't a great slide, but this is really the information from the GitLab
and the README and Benjamin Earhart, who's here, designed most of this. But we had certain
requirements and the idea was we would, you know, we kind of aggregate records together
so they're not always being logged in real time, as an example. We also wanted to filter
some of the headers from mobile devices and things so that we could really control some
of those things before they ever went into Matomo. And recognizing that in some cases
no one would pull the Matomo maybe as precisely as they wanted. And yeah, and it's a pretty
simple layer, but it was great that we had the Matomo API to work with and that we could
build this layer that we needed. So again, it's about flexibility, control, and it was
awesome that this was possible and it's been working out very well.
So when you work with Clean Insights, the steps are that first you set up a campaign
and this is through a JSON or configuration file that defines kind of the measurement
period, some local persistence, how often to measure, when to start and when to end.
And you know, this can be set very broad or it can be set very narrow. And so one of the
ideas is you might say to users, I'm just going to measure you for two weeks. We're
doing a study for two weeks. Do you want to join? It's going to be focused on improving
this feature and you can join and participate in this study. That's a big key concept here,
which is not sort of endless measurement. And we think people are more likely to opt
in and say, sure, I'm excited about that if they have that ability. So then we get consent
and we have some various UX I'm going to get to quickly because I'm running out of time.
And then you choose to measure specific events with custom data or specific views. Some of
this relates to what you might be used to in the Matomo SDKs around events and views
because we knew the data was ending up there in the end, so we wanted to be able to map
it into some of what you would see in Matomo on the back end. So there is that heritage
there and thinking about the data, but how we process it and it gets there over time.
So you might do a bunch of measurements of someone clicking on a button or interacting
with something and then once a week that data is aggregated as a count and sent to the server
as opposed to going constantly to the back end. So cleaninsights.org has a lot more information
on this and we're also doing a workshop tomorrow morning that if you really want to implement,
we're going to be ready to talk to you about your specific needs and I'm always available.
A big part of this in our apps was also this idea of consent and we've spent a lot in consent
user experience design, a lot of energy around the messaging. Contribute for this number
of time. We'll be doing these things to gather these pieces of data and here's how you'll
benefit and we'll reach back to you. And so really make it a participatory co-design process
to improve your software or your site in a way that's transparent and collaborative.
This is key for us and we think it's an important model moving forward. Again, you could say
we're going to measure you for a year or for a month or longer time periods, but you do
want to kind of have an experience where people in the US, there's a thing called Nielsen
ratings where you used to be super excited in the old days of television to be a Nielsen
family because they wanted to know what you cared about and which television shows were
good and you had a box in your house and it felt like everyone wanted to be that family
and I think we're trying to recapture some of that positivity around providing feedback
to services. Yeah, ultimately there's an idea of why, what you're gathering and why and
that we want to tap into. So I'm going to keep going. So we have a bunch of designs,
Figma files, blog posts through our partner, OK, thanks. Carrie on our team is, that's
her design studio and really has done outstanding work here and we're actually building all
of this into multiple applications like as I mentioned earlier. F-Droid themselves have
already implemented a piece of this, though we haven't fully done the consent user experience
yet. But if you go to the F-Droid blog, there's a post on Clean Insights and the idea was
we wanted to understand the insight was how often do people fail to install an app they
choose and then what are the most popular apps this week across all repositories and
that felt like something that they were comfortable using Clean Insights to measure as people
opted in and that would be that people would be excited maybe to share that, right? And
so those are the idea of insights that we feel are clean that we are able to generate
there. So, you know, in the future, there's a lot more we want to do with more advanced
kind of solutions and more filters and how to batch data. We're also looking at secure
multi-party computation and some of the interesting work there with kind of, you know, how to
expand what we're doing into larger datasets and have solutions for a broader market. Again,
free coffee. So good. So delicious. So if you come to our workshop tomorrow, I think
you get free coffee sent to you and then so good. And, you know, but this is also if you
please, if you go there, you'll see, you know, it's a chance for us to connect and we really
want to do we have so much to learn from you and from people that have already been doing
measurement or already implementing things like Matomo have been through this or who
have other thoughts or other ways that they've solved the issues we have brought up. So we're
really wanting to get that that feedback for sure. And oh, my slide is a little messed
up, but I am, you know, N8FR8, Nate Freight, in many places on Matrix, Nathan at guardianproject.info
and cleaninsights.org. Benjamin Earhart is TLA. He's often around in various rooms. And
yeah, so I think that's my talk for today. And we have time for questions, I think, because
we did start a little bit late. But I also want to, you know, respect all of your time.
So I love ending early. And I have more time tomorrow. So if you have deep questions and
want to work on this more with us tomorrow is a good time as well. Have a sip of coffee.
Yeah, I think we're also I mean, in an area that while I'm waiting for questions, please
ask away. We do want to talk to we know a lot of people use Matomo with web analytics,
but we are really interested in people that are using the Matomo mobile SDKs and how you've
integrated into native apps. It would be great to hear from you either now or tomorrow or
through the chat rooms. And to kind of talk about how you we might you know, you can migrate
to using Clean Insights, the SDK instead, perhaps, or why you wouldn't.
Thanks, Bjorn. Or hey, appreciate that. Good. That's easy, softball. I will say, boy, our
Hans just posted something in our feed about how Android apps can track users based on
their wallpapers. And it's, you know, there's so many problems on mobile devices in this
area with, you know, perma cookies, essentially fingerprinting a device as a way to get a
perma cookie. And I guess wallpaper is the latest. So I was, you know, I often set custom
wallpapers. So I'm, you know, that's a problem I have. Yeah, okay. Well, thank you for all
the kind words. I will be attending other presentations today as well. So hope to hear
all of your other work there and seeing I know there's a lot of other relevant topics.
So but again, please come tomorrow morning if you want to talk through your own implementation
or sign up at cleaninsights.org slash beans for a private consultation with coffee and
stickers to get stickers. There we go. I think we're done then if there's no questions.
Many thanks, Nathan. I think people are a little bit shy for the moment. But we can
also continue the conversation in the chat. Sure. I'll be there and in the cafe as well.
Thank you. Thank you. Usually I have my ukulele or guitar here and I could play a song, but
I don't know where it went. Children took it. All right. This is this
instrument is a I'm Nathan, by the way, if everyone's watching, this is called a dromian
or Tibetan banjo. And it has double strings. And the interesting thing is the bottom string
is kind of a drone, like a bass. And it's not tuned up because this is more of an instrumental
ornamental instrument. But yeah, it's a really beautiful instrument. And this is just waiting
music while we're figuring out the technical difficulties. Anyway, it's a pretty fun instrument.
It's got this cool like bass drone, like, like I'm kind of Tibetan Mongolian, you know,
that throat singing sound and we get this real low bass and then you play the melody
on the top strings. And yeah, I brought this back from Tibet many years ago. This beautiful
skin there. Okay, we're going to go with the PDF file.