Hello. So, I started the recording. So, since it's 10 a.m., we're about to start with this
session. Today we have Richard Stark, who is a Matomo Supporting Member and Matomo Analytics
Expert. In his talk, Matomo Tips and Tricks, he will tell us more about the collection
of Matomo features which you might not know about. So, let's hear Richard for more.
Good evening from New Zealand. Thank you, everybody, for joining this Matomo Camp session
for Tips and Tricks. All right. So, for those of you who've never heard of me before, hi,
I'm Richard. I am part of the Matomo Support Team based here in New Zealand. For those
of you who maybe have sent us some emails over the past couple of months, maybe a year
or so, you might have seen my name pop up in your email inbox, maybe now and then. So,
if this is not the first time, thank you so much for joining us. If it is the first time
hearing about me, it's great to meet you all. All right. So, as you saw in the previous
slide, my session for today is titled Matomo Tips and Tricks. I've really tried to include
a bunch of different tips and tricks for everybody, kind of from the everyday users of Matomo,
as well as tips and tricks for those responsible for managing the Matomo setup or for Matomo
administrators. All right. So, I've broken down the tips and tricks into four different
categories. They are, number one, UI tips. Number two, performance tips. Number three,
useful CLI or command line interface commands and how to figure out what options to use.
And number four, useful free plugins that are not installed by default in Matomo. And
then at the end of the session, we'll have a short Q&A session. So, please feel free
to pop any questions you might have in the chat room during the session. We do have a
dedicated chat room available for this live session on chat.matomocamp.org. I have asked
the moderator to grab a few of the more interesting questions to answer at the end just to make
sure we don't miss any of those. But you're also more than welcome to repeat your questions
at the end if they do get missed. If we do have enough time, we'll also be opening up
the floor to any questions at that time that you may have just randomly. So, let's get
started. Number one, we've got some UI tips. So, the first tip I've got for you today is
called Zen Mode. So, for those of you who have never used Zen Mode before, what it basically
does is it provides you with an uninterrupted view of your Matomo reports or your Matomo
dashboard. And it can be really, really useful for situations where you want to have a dashboard
on a dedicated screen or a dedicated vice for sharing reports. For example, if you might
have a dedicated screen in your office for looking at dashboards or pretty numbers and
charts, that is the perfect thing to use for this. It can also be quite useful if you wanted
to embed, for example, the entire Matomo UI into an iFrame. So, toggling Zen Mode on and
off can then allow you to quite easily navigate between the different reports within the iFrame.
And then when you want to bring that into sort of the full screen mode, you can quickly
toggle the Zen Mode and you have that awesome uninterrupted view of your dashboard or for
your reports. So, if you've never seen what the Zen Mode looks like before, I will get
to show a screen which hopefully a lot of you are familiar with. This is what the standard
UI in Matomo looks like. I'm pretty sure this is something that a lot of you see probably
on a daily basis, maybe less so often for other people. But what Zen Mode basically
does is this. It gets rid of the top menu bar. It gets rid of the menus on the left
hand side. And in the screenshot here, I've kind of added the screenshot including the
URL bar at the top. But obviously, if you did want to have this on a nice big screen,
you can go into full screen and you can have that really awesome uninterrupted view of
your Matomo reports. So, if you've never used it before, there's actually two different
ways that we can get to Zen Mode, how we can toggle it on and off. So, the one option,
of course, is to just click on our small little toggle button at the top of the page over
here. The other option, which is my preferred option, is just to hit the Z key on your keyboard.
That allows you to quickly switch between Zen Mode on and off.
All right. So, my next tip for you today is the search function shortcut. So, the search
function shortcut helps you kind of quickly navigate within the Matomo UI using your keyboard
and keyboard arrows. So, what it does is it allows you to search for and switch between
websites and segments quite quickly without having to touch your mouse. It also doubles
as a search tool to look for more information on the Matomo.org site. For example, you can
quickly search up for user guides or maybe you have a question or two that hopefully
is answered in an FAQ. So, most of you have probably seen the search bar up in the top
left hand side of the Matomo UI before, but if you wanted to quickly access this search
feature, you just hit the F key on your keyboard.
All right. The next UI tip for today is themes. So, for those of you who've kind of used
Matomo for a long time and have never really tried themes before, it's really something
that you can use to kind of customize the look, the feel, and the layout of the Matomo
UI. There are actually several different themes available pretty much for every Matomo user
in the world that you can quickly install and activate on your Matomo to get a really
custom looking field. So, some of the default ones you can see up on the screen now. For
example, we've got modern, we've got the minimalist themes, we've got the dark themes, but then
we also have some other themes that are specific just to customizing fonts. Some that give
you really cool visualizations, some spark lines, things like that.
The really great thing about themes, though, is that you're really not just limited to
these few themes that are available. The themes are completely customizable. You can customize
them to your heart's content, and it really requires very little skill. If you have a
basic understanding of CSS or maybe a little bit of less, you can customize as much as
you want and then upload those themes directly to your Matomo UI. So, if you've never installed
or activated themes before, you're probably wondering, how do I download and install themes?
Now obviously, we can have a look on the website directly at themes.matomo.org, but you can
also directly have a look at the themes from within your Matomo UI. So, to do that, we
just go to the administration icon, we go to platform and marketplace, and then we click
on the drop down menu and we select themes. From here, you can select any of the themes
that are available to download, but you'll also have a nice little button up at the top
of the screen that lets you upload your custom themes in a zip file format that you can then
install and activate on your Matomo instance.
Alright, the next section is performance tips. So, one of the biggest performance improvements
that you can make to your Matomo instance is to disable browser archiving and then set
up a crontab for archiving. So, you might be wondering, why do we recommend disabling
browser archiving? Now, for the majority of users out there that have very small websites
or websites that might have only a few hundred visits a day, it's definitely not worth the
effort going ahead and setting up those crontabs and disabling browser archiving, but for those
of you that are tracking a little bit more, you know, maybe a few thousand hits a day
or maybe tens of thousands of hits a day, this is probably one of the biggest improvements
that you can make to the performance of Matomo that you can see very quick and tangible results.
So, when we have browser archiving enabled, almost every time a user views a report, Matomo
needs to process the report that they're trying to request. It needs to go and fetch all that
raw data, needs to crunch all the numbers, needs to put everything into pretty charts
and numbers and lines and present it onto the screen. And it does this on the fly or
basically in real time. So, you can imagine if you're loading a report that has a lot
of data or reports that cover a long period of time, this can sometimes really slow down
your experience with Matomo and can sometimes take quite a long time for those reports to
load. This sort of effect can really be compounded when users are not aware of this. And it,
you know, they might be going around jumping through a bunch of different reports wondering
why the heck is this thing taking so long? What I mean there by compounding is if a user
clicks on one report, it takes three or four seconds to load and they don't see anything
on the screen. They decide, hey, I'm going to have a look at this report. That report
does the same. They can go through five or six or seven different reports in a matter
of seconds and every single one of those reports, once you start loading them in the user interface,
those requests have already been sent. The Matomo server is working on them in the background
to try and process all that data. Now, the good thing is, is when they go back to those
other reports that they've already requested the data for, it should load relatively quickly.
The problem is if they come back and do that again in one or two hours later, it's going
to need to do that whole process over again. So by pre-processing all of those reports
using what we call a crontab for the core archive command and setting up a schedule
and disabling that browser archiving, we can be a hundred percent certain that all of those
reports can load really, really quickly and your Matomo users can have a great experience.
So this setting can actually be changed directly within the general settings of your Matomo
instance, but it can also be set up by setting the specific config setting in your config.ini.php.
But of course, if you're not familiar with messing around with the files directly on
the Matomo server, disabling this within the UI is just perfect. All right. It is still
important, however, to understand that there are going to be some cases where Matomo will
still need to process reports when they're requested from the browser. This is specifically
important when you're requesting, for example, a date range report because a date range report
cannot be pre-processed. The other thing as well, if you have users who have created segments
and those segments have been configured to be processed from in real time or on the fly,
those segments will also be triggering some browser archiving requests. All right. The
next tip that we've got for you has to do with segments. So what we talk about with
segments when it comes to performance is we're talking about how far back segments are processed
by default on your Matomo server. So when you have a segment in Matomo, if you're creating
a segment or editing a segment, the default that Matomo is going to process that segment
for is what we call the beginning of time. And that basically means that Matomo is going
to process that segment from the very first day that you have raw data. Now, for a lot
of people, this can mean that they're having to process segment data going back two or
three or even more years, five or six years into the past. So this can have a really big
impact on performance, especially for those people who have a lot of historical or a lot
of raw data. So by changing this to a different time frame, for example, you can change it
to automatically process only back 30 days. You can do it for 60 days or three months
or six months or even a year. You can really customize and prevent your Matomo server from
working too much on reports that you might not need to use. So to change this setting,
we basically need to add the following to our config file. Now, if you're wondering
how the heck are you going to remember this, all of this information is available. You
can have a look in your config file. You can have a search for it on the Matomo website.
You can hopefully find some more information about how to set this config file. Otherwise,
if you wanted to look for this specific one, you can maybe take a screenshot or have a
look at this recording afterwards, and then you can implement this into your config file
settings. And of course, like you can see in the slide that's on the screen, there's
a few different ways that we can set this up. For example, the one at the top is the
segment creation time. So basically that means that no historical data for that segment is
going to be processed from before the date was created. So for a lot of people that are
tracking maybe tens of thousands or even millions of hits every single month, this might be
the most beneficial one. You can also have a smaller timeframe. For example, the one
at the bottom is the last 93. So that's roughly about three months historical data. So now
that I've told you how to disable browser archiving and to change how far back Matomo
goes back to process all of the segment data, you're probably wondering how do I get historical
data when I've configured this setting in Matomo? And that brings us really nicely into
our next segment, and that is useful CLI commands. Now, CLI is an acronym for command line interface,
and that might sound really scary, but Matomo, when you install it onto your server, has
a really cool what we call the console script. And the console script allows you to run some
really specific commands directly on your Matomo server that allow you to do things
or accomplish tasks that you want to do. So we've got a couple of different CLI commands
that we're going to talk about today. We're going to talk about how to invalidate specific
date ranges. So this is very useful for archiving specific segments further back than what we've
just recently changed in our settings. We're also going to have a look at invalidating
specific segments. And then number three, which is something that you might not have
been aware of, is invalidating specific plugins. So if you don't know, Matomo 4 actually ships
with a new feature that allows plugins that support that new feature to automatically
archive reports going back a certain number of months. So for example, if you've just
installed a brand new plugin or you've just purchased a premium plugin and you go ahead
and install that onto your Matomo server, the great thing is that Matomo is going to
go back and automatically archive the last six months of data for that new plugin. So
that means that you have instant access to a great wealth of historical report data for
that new plugin. However, sometimes it's still going to be necessary to archive reports going
further back than what we've just set up in our settings. This is especially useful when
you just installed a plugin. You want to have a look at, you know, what was the data for
this plugin a year ago or two years ago or even further back than that, as far back as
what you have raw data. So that is when the core invalidate report data console command
comes in. So as you can see in the example on the screen, in this example, we're running
the invalidate report data console command. So this command always requires a dates option.
As you can see in the example, we've got, for example, from the 1st of June up until
today. So that will basically invalidate all report data for your entire Matomo instance
going from the 1st of June till today. You can also use other types of date formats such
as the last 30 or last 7 or last 90, you know, things like that to kind of just get a general
date range invalidated. So some of you, if you're having a look at this, might be remembering
that we do have what we call the invalidate reports plugin. That also allows you, as you
can see in this example, to invalidate segments. The biggest difference, of course, between
the plugin and the console command is that the plugin is kind of like what we would consider
a sledgehammer when you're trying to invalidate report data. It doesn't necessarily differentiate
between different specific dates or specific plugins. It's kind of an all or nothing deal.
And that's where it really comes in handy, knowing how to work with these CLI commands.
And you can combine a lot of these different options together to get some really specific
ranges or specific report data that you're looking for. So as you can see in the example
over here, we've just put the plain text name of our segment. And in the next one, you'll
see that we can now also invalidate some very specific plugins. So this is really where
the CLI commands are a lot more useful than just invalidating report data in the UI. So
when we combine all of these together, we get the ability to not only invalidate reports
for a specific date range and for a specific segment, but also for a very specific plugin.
So this is really, really useful. And once you've done all this, of course, it then becomes
necessary to reprocess that data. And that brings us to the very last step in this specific
section. And that is reprocessing the report data that we've just invalidated using the
force date range option. So in this example, we're looking at the last one that we used,
the core invalidate report data, where we set the dates as the first of June to the
last of June. And when we run this last core archive command with the force date range
similar to or exactly matching what we've just invalidated, Matomo is going to only
go ahead and process that specific date range for that specific plugin. So some plugins
do actually have their own console commands that can be used for archiving, which we'll
talk about in a minute. But what a lot of you may be wondering is like, oh, do I have
to take a screenshot of this page? Do I have to memorize all of this information that's
in front of me right now so that I know how to use it? And the great news is no, you don't
have to memorize or take a screenshot of any of this data because all of this is directly
available when you run the console commands directly on your Matomo server. And we can
find this information by using the dash dash help option that the dash dash help option
when you're working with CLI commands is your absolute best friend. If you've ever forgotten
what the specific command is or what type of input you need to give for a specific option,
the dash dash help option is going to show that. So here, for example, in this slide,
we've got the help output for the core archive command. So as you can see on the screen,
hopefully the text isn't too small. We can see all of the potential options that we could
add to this to kind of really narrow down and get some very specific commands that we
can use for our server. So as I mentioned earlier, we do have some plugins that might
have some very specific commands. A good example of a plugin that has its own archiving command
is the custom reports plugin. So with the custom reports console command, it allows
you to actually go in and specifically just archive the custom reports for a specific
date range without needing to first invalidate that data. Now, a lot of you might be wondering,
do I need to have a look at that? Do I need to go look at a guide for that sort of information?
And here's the next really great tip is that no, you really don't have to know that information
beforehand. The console command, if you just type in console on an SSH or in a terminal
window in the Mitoma root directory and you add the dash dash list option, it's going
to give you a full list of all of the console commands that you can run directly on your
Mitoma server. And now that you've got this great list of console commands, you can then
run those specific commands each with their own dash dash help or dash help option to
get a list of all the optional parameters or required parameters that that specific
plugin requires. So the important thing to remember whenever you're working on this thing
is that just because a command works on one Mitoma server doesn't necessarily mean that
it works on every other Mitoma server. And the reason for this is that every plugin that
you install has the ability to add options to that list. So in other words, we're talking
about all of these console commands can be or are in a lot of cases server specific.
So if you're ever curious about how to run these console commands, how do I figure out
how to use all of this stuff, use the list command, use the help command and build your
command from there. Alright, so our next section is going to be useful free plugins and these
are specifically plugins that are not installed in Mitoma by default, but are available to
be downloaded and installed directly from within your Mitoma instance without requiring
any additional information. All you basically have to do is click download and install from
your Mitoma instance. And we're going to start with the first one on my list at least and
in my opinion, one of the best free plugins that you can install called the Queued Tracking
plugin. So the Queued Tracking plugin, it improves the performance and the stability
of your Mitoma server by reducing the load on the Mitoma database during tracking. It
also at the same time really greatly improves the speed of tracking requests sent to your
Mitoma server. So how this works does take a little bit of an explanation. So we're going
to do that now. So hopefully you'll see a graphic on your screen and what we're looking
at here is what we would consider a normal tracking request. So you can see up at the
top there, the browser sends that HTTP tracking request. That tracking request then gets received
by the Mitoma server and needs to be processed. It's then inserted directly into the Mitoma
database into that raw visits log and then once it's inserted, we send that response
to the browser. Now the Queued Tracking plugin, this behavior changes in a few key ways. So
as we can see on the next graphic, as soon as the Mitoma server, so here at the top again
we can see the HTTP tracking request. As soon as that is received by the server, it's put
into a queue and then immediately the Mitoma server responds to that browser or to that
device or that application to say, great, I've got that tracking request, you can carry
on. Once that tracking request is then placed into the queue, there's a few different things
that can happen. Now, number one, you can either set up your Mitoma instance to automatically
process all of the requests that are in the queue when the queue reaches a certain threshold,
but it can also be set up to be run on a schedule. So for example, you can process all of the
requests in the queue once every minute or once every two or three minutes. And what
this really does is that like you saw in the beginning, it not only improves the tracker
performance, but it also enables your Mitoma server to handle very large traffic peaks
without bringing down your database server. And the way that it does this is that instead
of sending, you know, small little individual single tracking requests every single time
one of those tracking requests is received to the database server, it can process all
of the tracking requests in that queue as a batch tracking request. So it really helps
your Mitoma server and it really makes a lot more stable and capable of handling those
very large tracking peaks.
All right, the next one on the list is the tracking spam prevention plugin. So the tracking
spam prevention plugin gives you some really good options that you can enable to prevent
spam tracking requests being sent or logged in your Mitoma server. So it does this by
giving you a couple of options. The first option it gives you is blocking requests from
cloud providers. So this is really useful, for example, if you have a malicious or a
bad actor that's sending you a lot of tracking requests from a server somewhere specifically
in the world. And the problem might be that they're using a lot of different servers,
you can't block all of those IP ranges. Well, the great news is the tracking spam prevention
plugin is going to really help you in that.
Number two is that it can automatically block requests from headless browsers. Headless
browsers are notorious for people that try to send these sorts of requests because the
load that it puts in the device sending those requests is a lot lower than a fully fledged
browser.
Number three, it can restrict the number of actions in a single visit or the maximum number
of actions that Mitoma will track in a single visit. This is especially useful to prevent
spam visits that might or that can sometimes track hundreds or even thousands of actions
in a single visit. We've seen some examples with people that we've provided support to
in the past from the Mitoma team, where they've had individual visits tracked over 10,000
actions in a single visit in a matter of minutes or even hours. And the great way is that you
can automatically block this or cap the number of tracking requests that can be tracked in
a single instance.
And number four, it can exclude specific countries or it can allow you to only include specific
countries. So this is really useful. For example, if you have a website that is specifically
targeting or specifically only working in a single country or in a single group of countries
to automatically exclude any tracking requests from countries outside of that, but it can
also be useful to very quickly and easily exclude specific countries if you notice that
you're getting a lot of spam or non-legitimate tracking requests from those countries.
All right. The next plugin on the list, which is an absolute must-have, is the marketing
campaigns reporting. So by default, Mitoma will give you the option or will give you
the ability to track campaigns. And it comes with a really useful campaign URL builder
directly in the Mitoma UI. However, a lot of people, or let me rather say, most people
probably already have campaigns set up that they're using to drive traffic to their site
using campaign links that are oftentimes set up in their ad networks or with specific social
networks. And the marketing campaigns reporting plugin extends that default capability, that
default campaigns reporting, to give you access to all of the possible campaign parameters
used by these platforms, as well as providing support for some of these campaign tracking
parameters without needing to use any of the Mitoma-specific campaign parameters. We have
a really great blog post available on our blog that you can go and read up about the
marketing campaigns reporting, and I would definitely recommend installing it on your
Mitoma server. All right. The next one on the list is probably a little bit more for
the Mitoma administrators out there. So that's called the Log Viewer. So the Log Viewer is
kind of more just a quality of life or convenience plugin that you can install to have a quick
look at the Mitoma application logs. So this can really save you some time and effort instead
of having to SSH into your server and grep some logs or download your logs from your
syslog server, you can just log into Mitoma, go to your administration UI, and have a look
at the logs directly. All right. And the next one on our list is the Custom Alerts plugin.
So the Custom Alerts plugin is really great, especially if you're not somebody who's looking
at the reports every single day. And what the Custom Alerts plugin allows you to do is
to get notified when something changes or something specific happens in your Mitoma
instance or on the websites that you're tracking. For example, you can set up an alert when
your website gets more than 300 views in a day. You can have another alert set up, for
example, if a specific product sells less than 100 items in a specific timeframe. But
alerts can be set up in other ways as well. For example, you can set up alerts as percentages.
So you can set up an alert, for example, that notifies you if the traffic to your website
drops by more than 50 percent in a given timeframe. And obviously, a 50 percent drop over a given
timeframe probably indicates that something big has changed or something has happened.
You can also set it up for if you have zero visits. Now, obviously, zero visits would be a pretty bad
outcome for you. You want to be sure that you're getting all of the tracking data and
that nothing is wrong with that tracking data. So for those types of alerts, you can actually
set them up not only as an email alert, but also as an SMS alert. So if you're setting
up an SMS alert, you'll need to make sure that you also set up the Mobile Messaging
Plugin. Now, the Mobile Messaging Plugin is included in Matoma Core, but it might not
be activated on your Matoma server. So if you want to set up SMS alerts with a Custom
Alerts Plugin, you'll need to go ahead and activate that plugin as well. And the last
plugin on our list for today is the IP2 Company Plugin. This one kind of explains itself.
What it does is it adds the functionality to your Matoma server to easily see if visits
to your website or app are connecting from any known IP ranges for specific companies.
So this is really useful, especially if your website or even your marketing campaigns are
specifically targeting a certain market segment or even a very specific company. It also provides
you some reports for these as well, so you can see which companies are visiting your
website or using your application more than others. And all of these plugins can be found
on the Matoma Plugins website at plugins.matoma.org. There is a massive list of plugins that didn't
make the cut, unfortunately, for this session today. So if you're ever curious, if you wanted
to know how you can extend the capability of your Matoma server, have a look at the
list of plugins available there. And alternatively, you can also find them in the Marketplace
section of your Matoma server. From there, you can directly install and activate and
start using these awesome plugins. All right. And that brings us to the end of the last
segment for this Matoma Camp session. So we're going to move on to some question and answers
now. So if you haven't yet had an opportunity to send some questions through to the chat,
just going to take a minute. The moderator has sent some questions through to us on the
chat on this side as well. So we'll just have a quick look through those questions and see
if we can answer some of them. How is it like to work for the Matoma or InnerCraft team?
This is a question from Ronan. Honestly, it's been probably one of the best work experiences
that I've ever had in my life. The team is amazing. It's awesome to work in a group of
people that are conscious about open source software, conscious about being open and sharing.
And it's really just a great company culture overall. What are the next big features the
team is working on? So yeah, there's not a lot of big secrets when it comes to what sort
of features we're working on. If you want to know what features we're working on next,
you can probably have a look at the GitHub issues page. And you can kind of see, kind
of looking at those milestones in the GitHub page, you can kind of get a feeling of what
features are going to be worked on next. What is the priority for those sorts of things?
Can we add new shortcuts with Matoma? This is actually something I'm not 100% sure. And
I don't think we have the option to have keyboard shortcuts, but that's definitely something
that I'll have a look at and ask the team about as well. Do we have any plans to develop
more documentation about how to make more attractive teams? So I'm not sure who asked
that question specifically, but we do actually have a developer's guide available on our
developer documentation on how to create themes. Obviously, there's not necessarily very specific
examples of what you can do. The main reason for that is that it's kind of really open.
If you know a little bit about CSS, you know a little bit about LESS, you can go happy
and hack away all day every day and create really cool customized themes. Something that
I may not have mentioned earlier is that you're not just limited to using CSS or LESS, you
can also include JavaScript files in your plugins to kind of extend it even further
than what CSS or LESS would allow you to do. All right, Lenaro asks in the chat room, does
the spam prevention work retroactive to filter out already made spam visits? No. So the tracking
spam prevention plugin doesn't work retroactively. So this is something that you would need to
install to prevent future spam tracking requests. If you do have very specific spam tracking
requests, the best way to get rid of that data or those spam tracking requests is to
use the GDPR tools available within Matomo. And that can be kind of useful, especially
if they've, for example, all of the tracking requests came from a certain IP address or
if they came from a certain country or they track certain specific things to your Matomo
instance, you can use those GDPR tools to very quickly and easily delete all of that
data. All right, that's some of the questions that we've got on the, are we having any plans
to make the config.ini.php file accessible from the UI? No, I don't think we've got any
plans to make that config file editable from within the UI, but it is possible to view
the config file from the UI. Not necessarily just limited to the config.ini.php, but there
is a section under the diagnostics tab that you can actually go and have a look at all
of the settings that are currently set either in the global config file or the config.ini.php
within your Matomo instance. The reason why we wouldn't necessarily make it directly editable
from the UI is because a lot of the settings that you set in the config.ini.php can override
some of the settings that you might set in your user interface. All right, just having
a look for a couple more questions. Do you have any tips for solving upgrade issues?
Sometimes the upgrade fails and the database and core are not the same version. There have
been several questions on this in the forum, but there isn't a good solution. That's a
really great question and it's actually something that I helped one or two customers with in
the last couple of weeks as well. It might be really useful from our end just to put
that into an FAQ. It's something that I've kind of been planning to do as well, but yes,
there is actually a way that you can roll back the version that is stored in the database
so that Matomo can rerun all of those database upgrade commands. So stay tuned. I don't know
if you have any way that you can kind of keep an eye on some of the FAQs. Otherwise, feel
free to shoot us an email at support at matomo.org just asking about that information about those
specific steps. And if we don't yet have that FAQ out there, we'll be more than happy to
send that information on to you. Could you give a general definition of what archiving
means? Yeah. So archiving is basically the process that Matomo uses to kind of process
all of that raw data. So as you can imagine, if you're sending hundreds of thousands of
tracking requests or hits to your Matomo interface, that data on its own isn't really useful other
than just to kind of look at in reality. So what archiving does is it takes that raw data
and it parses through every single piece of that raw data, and that is used to then generate
the reports that you view in your Matomo instance. All right. Anyone else got a couple more questions
for us? All right. That looks like all the questions for today. So that means that we're
actually almost out of time. I really just wanted to say thank you, everyone, for joining.
Thank you so much for the awesome questions that you asked. I hope that everybody learned
something new today that will help give you success with Matomo. And I'd also like to
give a massive thank you to the volunteers that have made Matomo Camp possible. This
really is a community-driven event, and none of this would be possible without the awesome
contribution of the volunteers as well as the sponsors. Have a great day, everyone.
Bye.