Okay, and with this it is
three o'clock and i would like to
introduce three people for next presentation namely
to be the poorer with your pierluigi
darcy and cardio
surely him
and in their talk they will give
an overview of how web analytics with
Matomo are used in the public section
in italy include a case study of
the long-term usage of multiple so whenever
you're ready please stand up
hello everybody my name is claridge regina
hansen and santa and i'm responsible for
the
the web development services in the agency
for digital italy and today i want
to present you our solution for monitoring
your website the statistics of public administration
in italy and er
of course we used her and matomo
and the and i explain in this
a very short presentation why we are
we decided to to
to to to him to implementer a
statistical national statistical platform
from a legal point of view are
we are in italy we have a
co
a little context to quiet articulated by
the complex sir
the h's call it is called code
of digital administration in article seven it
says that public administration or
shall publisher on their website data on
user to user just statistics in the
code of digital administration gives you rules
about digital issue for the public and
private entities and that and it's a
rule itself illegal
framework or that must be followed
induction
and it says the public administration should
allow users to express their satisfaction on
the service quality in term of usability
accessibility and timeliness so public administration should
also publish or as i said a
day on the website the resulting data
including a heretic sir
in in in articles fifty three i
don't want to bother you with the
many legislative aspect but the dust to
say you that this is something that
is required by the law
and we added this this a coder
and says that the internet site of
public administration should respect the principle of
accessibility usability as stated in a specific
governmental guidelines and so the public administrations
should create a website that respect this
the spray
principal and about usability find ability completeness
of information clarity of language reliability easy
of consultation on maternity and interpretability well
all the staff work but as we
know must be
add one this this level of quality
can be reached at only by
even about by monitoring the the the
use of a website to
of digital services or by the user
so
of course there are many many other
way of projecting a good web services
but now just to focus on the
suspect in a webpage or agency for
digital he did he brought these guidelines
sir while we define the modalities for
the creation and modification of internet
websites of public administrations these guidelines as
well are something that must be followed
is not something like her and i
can say nice to have a feature
but it's something that the public administration
should respect her
and in this guideline sir we say
that again him and his statistics should
appear on each website the data eg
a day this is very important to
in this case data
you just statistics data remains inside the
public administration with this solution we redefined
and what is this solution the technical
solution
we developed a national platform which is
called web analytics or italia and the
room is an open source solution for
collecting and analyzing analyzing and sharing traffic
and user behavior data dedicated to italian
public
administration websites so in order so to
allies and improve the user experience sir
we developed we did we decided to
to develop the sir
a national platform
and this is the very first time
eatery for for italy for the government
and that we we have as such
a such as such a tool such
as a platform and then already many
many administration have
are are adjoined to the the solutions
and many more are going to to
join they sir
the spot formed by next year and
the
ok
a going out of out of italy
a wii and connected to the sir
platform this solution do with the regulation
of the single digital gateway the regulation
twenty eighteen mina and seventy twenty four
as establishes a single digital gateway at
europe level there to provide access to
information to procedures sir and to assistance
and problem solving services the website addresses
say your europe or africa you can
see it on on my side and
and
so what we have to do with
the web analytics italia based on the
matomo and the sir your bureau platform
well this single digital gateway has thousands
and thousands of links to national web
pages
which contains lots of information specific information
this sir
the statistics about these web pages at
national level must be sent to european
commission and and this is written clearly
stated that in the in the regulation
so national authorities shall ensure that statistics
are
are collected there in relation to users
vz tsa on the gateway and are
on the web page to which the
gateway links in a way that guarantees
anonymity of the users in order to
improve the functionality of the gatwick well
we
yeah we we implemented that we connected
this a national solution with the european
europe europa
single digital gateway and in this way
we avoided as many other member states
are doing now i'll be avoid to
ask it to the single administration to
send the file like an exile of
something stuff like that or to the
european commission about statistics
what kind of information we gather will
number of fees it very very basic
information but the useful number of visits
a number of unique visitors per webpage
countries from which the user are visiting
the webpage type of devices use
austin and the time spent on page
the very basic one spot to
we have set up an automated way
to send this information regularly to the
european commission and more or less this
is the way
the web analytics a connect with the
other
notes of the europa a framework and
then from
it throws for four and till now
the the statistics are related at all
web pages only
and from it and and and and
from twenty three twenty three these statistics
are
will be related to services online which
will be able to or written make
available by the end of twenty twenty
three
my presentation finished here i thank you
very much for your kind attention
i give the floor to debate the
public jan
thank you claudio i switched my presentation
while good afternoon my name is davide
borrow that cure him the lead developer
of web analytics italia the italian national
platform for webinar lee dixon the public
sector
w a i for answered why is
the short name we use for web
analytics he thought
while why am i talking about web
analytics italia it is the project and
now the platform that brought us in
that knowledge of madama why is evolving
of courson and follow the evolution of
madama as well for example one of
the next steps
nowhere roadmap will be to upgrade to
version four of metal
three main points about why the first
as established by the italian lo the
collection of statistical data is mandatory for
public bodies the use of why however
is not mandatory but recommended because a
central collection point as many
the advantages as we'll discuss in a
moment
why turbine is connected to two other
national platforms one is in egypt pr
which is the directory of all the
public administration and the other one is
speed them the italian a digital identity
system
when we started designing webinar dixit alia
madama was the natural choice because as
you all already know it is completely
open source can be extended with custom
plugin and configured according to specific needs
in addition to these cons
immigration attorney law requires public administration to
use open source solution when available so
we had no other choice than metal
the possibility to collect data in one
central point was a strategic decision to
allow a national analysis and to address
certain processes such as the updating of
guidelines for the design of public websites
as cloud
you told before me now that the
platform is a quite stable even if
still in beta we are planning an
extensive analysis of the data collected took
struck valuable information about the interaction of
italian citizen with public administer
sure websites and of course the quality
of the websites
most of the administrations are using the
web analytics entirely and to monitor the
traffic for their websites are more municipalities
or schools the ease of use and
availability of an institutional solution allowed us
to bring these organizations
on board with minimal effort
there is a first step toward our
goal in the short term as if
we wanted to spread as much as
possible the diffusion of web analytics among
italian public administration
bouquet g dpr it can be a
concern we know especially for a small
organization the recent the c n a
a la recommendation has confirmed that our
choice to use matomo was the right
one the guidelines of the time
iam data protection authority also point out
that if we use matomo with the
proper configuration better minimize or personal data
we can collect the statistic without requiring
an explicit user consent
as you can see in the simple
diagram salt we are switching to explain
i'm going to discuss now how we
use matomo while the discussion that until
now was about why we use madam
well as you can see in the
in the symbol diagram our users interact
with why front-end them for logging in
and the websites and user management but
they eventually switched to matar more directly
when they need to view dashboards
wind trucks with madama by a poi
to perform the task requested by the
user in this interaction fence in the
backend the truck inside is completely managed
by matomo with a configuration that i
will discuss in a moment
this is them boarding process a forum
for italian public administration while after logging
in the user selects an administration and
the corresponding ural is retrieved from ethiopia
the directory of italian italiana been stretched
at this point why korea as it
creates a new website he met all
month and provides the tracking code to
the user so it can be included
in the source-code of the specific website
only after the vz starts to be
tracked then y will create a new
account the matomo
thus allowing access to the dashboard for
the user with this pattern we can
be fairly sure that the user has
permission to modify the code of destitution
the website at least the dineen disappear
for the selected administration
single digital gateway was described by cloudian
some minutes ago and is a regulation
of the european commission that states among
other things that each member state shall
collect statistics on vz to the pages
that are part of the euro europe
network your europe is a portal for
a european citizen looking for information rights
for your thoughts and procedures for their
personal and professional activities within the european
union the regulation requires the statistics for
each page
are transmitted using your account treat device
matrix thanks to moto alma we are
able to easily build a system based
on creating a segment for each you
are allowed device pair and then querying
the poi with a user calmed riddle
get countering meta
old for each segment
the resulting data is then structured in
the form of the required and automatically
sent to the servers of the european
commission
while our architecture of whether a dictator
alia
is stood within a cloud service provider
that is made available to the italian
public administration the white platformer is buzzard
that is based on that a room
on i asked subtypes are resistant sorry
within our structure we have installed that
kubernetes cluster that we use dorcas stray
to the different containers that make up
the whole system the only element outside
of the cupboard and a dishcloth series
is that the bms which is installed
on a dedicated to just one machine
for performance reasons
for the portal component which a lot
faster than the other components we have
activated a continuous integration continuous deployment system
that allow us to stay up to
date with the code in our github
repository
in the next slide i am going
to discuss in more detail the different
matomo containers you can see now in
this diagram
we have four different types of matomo
containers obviously we use keyword tracking plugin
saw her the first one is the
ingestion container which only expose the moto
mod note
her p h b and pointer to
the outside world and collect data and
then queue them inside the readies component
the workers containers not exposed to the
outside world which the queue the data
from radisson and load them into
will the database then on the third
that kind of containers the web container
and the easy easy to expose the
to the outside that but only accessible
by authenticated users basically those coming from
the web portal and these for dashboards
and reporting in the in
general
the last one is the apia container
which at the moment the only allow
that visually just shown the visualization sorry
of regents butter with some limitation that
i will discuss in a moment
okay about providing reagents to authorize that
organization in order to provide our users
with a possibility of displaying widgets on
their website without at the same time
allowing the widgets to be included the
inane yet the web
we have adopted the two tire solution
on the web server using a specific
script we add in the response to
a request for a widget to a
content security policy header with the value
frame ancestors and the u r l
corresponding the madama to decide the d
in the request so the browser which
shall be frame only if embedded in
the specified euro
in moto mondays is the second tire
we then use a custom plugin that
rejects all request that do not contain
the module equal widgetized parameter in the
query string to avoid the rejecting valid
requests coming from inside the widget i
fray
graeme the plugin let them pass if
they contain the stringer module equal widgetized
inside the referrer h ttp either
some performance metrics
while at webmoney dixie tally we know
wherever a six hundred and seventy seven
tracking websites these websites belongs or two
oh five hundred and nine the public
administrations and considering that in italy we
have about twenty though
walls and the front administration were still
far from good coverage but the project
has already been quite successful and is
growing fast at the moment we are
getting about fifty million visits per month
for a total of about one hundred
and forty
million page views incoming traffic to the
ingestion component average is something like two
one rather transactions per second the with
peaks of up to three hundred and
fifty transactions per second
they are keeping job is currently our
least performing component because it takes almost
twelve hours to complete bear in mind
however that the ah
five hundred and ninety roll-ups one for
each administration must be added the two
there are six under the and the
seventy seven website so we have more
than one thousand than three hundred websites
to process in there
in their giving job
well the finish is my presentation i
want to thank everyone for listening at
all of what i describe is public
and open source and has two main
repository on github dot com the leche
a g i the leche w a
i
dashboard taller and the other one is
the same but as the the final
part w a i the best infrastructure
okay now i leave the floor to
be rigid assay from emilia romagna region
who will discuss about another experience with
matomo in mind italy
the public sector thank you
sorry hello everybody thank you thank you
for explaining urim your project and thank
you for joining because
two explaining them on the the answer
and the bigger the big project you
are doing in and for entire day
italy on italia non public administration i'm
speaking from bologna and where are you
situated in the region emilia romagna that
isn't as
smaller and smaller administration is monterey area
of administration and the region is situated
in the northern area all over italy
and that is counting the
it's counting up sorry
it's contender for four million and an
asthma residence in an area not in
on an important area is about twenty
two kilometers of big and the and
is at one of them
most devil aboard
or agency in italy and and the
and is a m
i can say am is a m
these are insane choices for other authors
and and as a kind of lighter
on an administration of other regions
aura is a very important to the
forum
economic growth and the industrial growth and
tourism so we have a lot of
products of it for a two tweeter
and you know a audiences are very
very careful about food the assault this
is a a big a big amount
of food but also he's a very
good area of industrial growing about the
motorsports since ages different scene to the
tense of age or year so we
never played a lot of very
i have informed and very famous
examples of the very good the industry
all
and products the because of this that
the region must be and must be
the administration of the region must be
i'm aware like the the private sector
and so
the administration master
accomplish they are their business it's a
very hard the deity because the companies
are always asking for good results for
this sir because of this we have
we have starting started doing analysts
takes a lot of time ago it's
more than time ago then died ten
years ago and am merely in the
us anti sensor sensor twenty thirteen we
started using piwik
now called the matomo and the question
was providing the dead
the privacy for the users just the
just that the only the only them
different to a product that we can
use there was a
the google analytics but we were not
to happy with it because if you're
following the previous of talk it was
explaining that the free free services from
our private companies are always an expansive
entire match
in term of the of privacy and
privacy cost so in a two and
twenty thirteen we immigrate to or system
from a barely logs analytica misery mentor
and to ariel a webinar politics software
and because
yeah
be weaker at that time was already
giving a
a better a better car and better
and i bet the amount of data
to misery misery and overall data because
it's because of its creeps because it
was open source every customer label that
happened before the jd barrel rules
that coma comedy ninety nine twenty eighteen
and the song we were already already
sensitive about to this kinda of problem
of the privacy
and and aura database sides is now
about one hundred gigabytes gigabytes and the
most of the data is the report
table so we are collecting sensor since
the start ok we have a lot
of data
we collected sensor them to twenty and
thirteen
and
during the the last to two year
so we had them and all the
older the werther had the and a
amanda emergency problem with the with the
glow below with the globalise
i
the problem over there and i had
then
the solve the social problem with the
as individuals
and we started from am a situation
we can see here in the starting
point where all of the visits to
our website where about us leaping about
like sleeping but doesn't where they were
weren't really
this is what the aura bigger or
bigger amount of visiting least it's about
and then this event was called the
original election day as happened in that's
up in the in the in the
middle of january over then twenty twenty
and then we had the problem with
the emerging problem with the way the
security national security and the the health
of the people at this time a
italy was the first to reverse the
country now are you in europe or
hit by the health problem and emilia
romagna was the one of the the
regents for one fiesta first hit and
the saw this was the amount of
data we collected by people that were
visiting our website looking for a soul
singer for
the source of the air or feature
information for for their life and this
a decent amount of data he was
also growing into in the months later
and then we expected the and i
and tablet the tablet the traffic on
those websites during the two two twenty
twenty and during this year and it
is not yet the end it and
so i think we are going to
get at the samer the same and
similar
level of visitors you see you can
see that the level it's really a
tablet in the in in this two
years and that's because people was looking
for information about their their health and
also they discover that the aura website
is all the web
sites we have a ara ara field
the body a lotta a user for
information they weren't aware i forgot to
say sorry sorry for missing up with
the slides i'm very sorry
during that time i was watching the
analytics though and i was careful about
that this is more alive or alive
a record the visit the record and
it was like the memory i was
watching these numbers going on
and this is a now or installation
an installation that is based on the
two year twelve machine and who are
balancing the buy
around behind the eye they are on
under a load balancer and we run
and the cron jobs for making reports
every two years every two are worse
every two hours we have a cron
job and this the worker load the
of the two of
the two in stasis
the blue liner is the memory amount
the user to buy him the moto
mo
and the the red line is the
cpu load this is a smaller than
the pasta because of the bhp seven
apple upgrade the disown a waiver is
a and never ages the average requests
per se
second and is this the situation is
not really optimized as your scene you
can run mme on on on containers
and i think is the best solution
to do it because you can be
and you can go with cheaper a
cheaper
configuration and spend the less than than
needed this is needed because we we
are in a situation where we are
not aware how much how much spikes
we can we can afford but this
configuration was enough to
all to enjoy this this a rollercoaster
mountains
so i let's go on on the
plugin development we we are one we
are contributing to maternal and for the
audience or us for more than five
years it's about an it's nearly ten
years long
longer we are doing good with the
metal alamo and the community so am
i you can see me
sometimes in the forum sir helping and
chatting with people and indeed during this
time women aged two public to to
plugins one of them is a plugin
who lets a missouri and let me
make the mutilation of people came
being from the internet the law in
local local law locate an internal location
you're in town the location is pretty
configurable by the console the administration console
and you can you can choose a
urine and you can choose a your
yours your sectors euro how can you
say your address user and the by
simple digits in regular expression
you can get at the sir david
this rapport this is important because
or internal colleagues wanted to do missouri
make amelioration of an internal internal audience
and the external audience on on the
websites i forgot to say we have
collect we are missouri linger more more
than one one
under the and fifteen website and we
have about the two hundred the user
managing and the reading and reading their
analytics
and so la you can find this
plugin this plugin that you can find
it on the on and on and
motto more on the moto mo marketplace
but also you can find that this
your honor or use the oreos on
there
i catalog on the public administration catalog
he knitted this is important because you
say i am in them pasta in
the pasta and
as you see was really you'll have
seen in the past the talks of
by maya by claudio
and there's a lot of effort to
do making the local administration and publishing
their software when they they are asked
to publisher open source software online and
make it shit shareable with
with the way the public and so
this is part of our contribution and
this this part of contribution is also
now available to other public administrations also
and also and even then the shopper
them in the matomo marketplace the second
plugin the set
can plugin is not a dating plugin
because i had the very small amount
of of creativity in that day but
the the naam the name of this
plugin is that your reddit user user
data is not a dating plugin but
it the meaning to it mean and
that you
can the controller and the user
behavior inside that the madama and you
can omit them or you can avoid
them making a customer ranger rapporteur because
this kind of rapids outer bloating overloading
good then
the application so we chose the two
that let them visit only a prerecorded
reports and the stay stick to their
to make this you must accomplish a
small modification of the user interface and
that and so and so this plugin
make your do it we have also
am am personal and team that you
you we use inside the but i
don't field i don't fell to what
was interesting because it's a very easy
to develop your plugin and during this
they did
these days and during this year so
i'd say the
we we also contributed to the to
the development of madam and them's in
the darker boxer you can find the
as small amount of pop pull request
or pull request i've either ask it
in
the pasta and the also there are
many many issues i raise in the
in the past i think
this kind of contribution is very important
to the community and it's very important
to the health of the matomo because
because it make you make them and
makes them the audience and makes the
core developers aware of the audience
sorry for my bad english and the
if y'all
want to learn italian the ha just
joking you can visit the the italian
section of the forum
but the a is not very crowded
it's only it's just an italian part
so if your aura engage in intimate
almost somehow i mean i would like
to suggest to you to participate a
lot more on the far
rooms and also a participating exposing gun
your wishes and your problems on the
issue on the on the tub
and
for now my my presentation is a
is ended and now i think it
is a good time to make a
am
question and answers so i would like
to pass the the the the chat
there the liver the liver to to
the marcos and the let's go with
the question and answers thank you for
thank you and thank all of the
free for the
very nice presentation
so if anyone has any questions please
write them in the tests there have
already been some questions but if if
i didn't miss any any of them
i think most of them have already
been answered
i
so but if there's any any questions
i'm just going to wait once again
amid
to see if anything pops up because
of the delay
well during a w the speech i
was stirring some questions from the audience
and one of them was a question
for
i'll be there and they asked the
if
euro euro servicer and web analytics natalia
is a fork of matomo and the
day also asked the if you made
the also am patterson la la team
and another question was was i dunno
my name
and i think that our nominee quest
if you have a devil but any
any plugin also saying thank you pierluigi
a just as were all the questions
in the in the chapter during your
presentation so i think
there is no need to repeat my
my unsworth and two
to leave the room if there are
more questions than there's one crespo just
that the images have you seen any
other countries contributing to metal as well
while i know other countries are using
moto mo and i know the european
commission made using either using madama butter
i don't know if they are contributing
in the sense of making plugins or
participating in the community
they thank you
then
i think i'm gonna call it once
again if there any other questions the
tread is going to stay open and
you can still ask her to step
i
yeah
and with that thank you once again
for positions and have a great afternoon
thank you very much
goodbye